Okay, let's get started,
welcome back to 006, today we're going to be
creating some of the coolest
data structures we'll see in this class,
maybe some of the coolest
data structures ever were binary trees,
you've probably seen trees in many
forms,
in the past, including in this class
we've talked about using trees as a
lower bound tool
for a decision tree model,
but in this and the next lectures
we're going to be creating
one data structure that pretty much
beats every
data structure we've seen and can do
almost everything
very quickly, first recall all the
data structures we've seen so far arrays
linked lists
dynamic arrays sorted arrays hash tables
and two sets of operations that we
want to support
two interfaces are sequences
where we store elements in a
specific order, we want to be able to
insert an
element right after another or
delete an element in the middle of the list
and always be able to access the i-th
element, we haven't seen any
good data structures for this
problem, we're really good at
inserting  and delete
at the beginning or end of
the sequence, but we haven't seen anything
that's efficient in
inserting ins in the middle of a list or
deleting in the middle of a linked list
you can't even get to the middle in less
than linear time
uh array you can get to the middle but
if you make any changes you need to make
that shift very expensive
so today or, sorry, next lecture
we'll see
all these operations efficient for the first time.
I'll mention our goal where efficiency
means
logarithmic so we're not as good
as linked lists and dynamic arrays in
insertion and
deletion at the ends of those that we
reach constant or constant amortized
time
but up to that log factor we're going to
get the best of all worlds where we can
solve
all the things all the operations that
don't
build or iterate the whole
structure which of course takes linear
time
but we can do everything else in
logarithmic time for
sets sets were maintained by maintaining a bunch of
elements that have
internal keys and we want
to search by key so hash tables are great
if you're doing an exact search only if you
want to find the key
and get a yes or no answer of whether it's there and if it's
there give me the element that's what
python dictionaries do and
they're
great at inserting and deleting but
they're really bad at
finding the previous and next.  This is the
unfortunate case of if I'm looking for a
key and it's not in my structure,
I'd like to know more than just
the answer is no, I'd like to know what the
previous and next elements
are actually in the structure,
so what are my closest matches when I
search for a key, this is a natural query,
and the only data structure that we have that's
good at this is a sorted array
because binary search gives us that,
if we look for a key with binary search
and don't find it,
the position that we end up at is right
between the previous and the next,
but of course sorted arrays are terrible
for dynamic
operations that we don't know how to support,
we can't support a sorted array without
any gaps
when we do insertions and
deletions in a sense today,
and binary trees of the next class allow us
to represent the
sorted order or the order of the
elements
dynamically and still allow us to do
very fast things like go from i and
find the previous key,
so that's our goal, we  we're not going to
fully achieve this goal today
we're going to get an incomparable thing
called tree height and then
on thursday we're going to be able to complete and
achieve this goal today just
in service for this goal
so what is a binary tree
let me draw an example
and then define it more precisely
mathematicians would call it a rooted
binary tree
because if you saw this in o42
say
here's a picture
so this is an example of a binary tree
it has a bunch of nodes that we
draw in circles
in the nodes have elements that i'm
writing here as letters
so this is element a item b item c and it
has these
links between them it's like linked
lists
but in general node
x will have a pointer to the parent the
left child
left pointer and the right child right
pointer and
inside of it there's also an element so i'm going to
talk about node.left
is a pointer  left,
the node at the bottom node.right
node.parent node.item
gives me, so if I
look at node a, its element is
a, so let me draw
some examples for you,
okay, the parent node of a is nothing, so we
call a the
root node, there will be a
unique node that has no parent element
sadly there is no parent, but here,
then we have node b,
whose parent node c is the parent, its visible node
d its parent node b
node e its parent node b, and the parent node f is
d in
alphabetical order here, usually
ordering parent,
then we have the left pointers, I'll just do
a few of them, so the left pointer
a is b the right pointer a,
sorry, b node, well that should be all be
notes,
I'm circling the nodes and just writing
the letter for the element to
make it clear that these are different
things, right  the pointer to a
is c the left pointer to b is d the
right pointer to b is e and so on
okay so in In other words each of these
lines is a bidirectional pointer
in this direction this is the parent
direction in this direction in this case it's to the left
because it's bidirectional we don't draw
arrows we just draw
undirected lines okay so
this is basically what a binary tree looks like.
The key invariant is that if you take a node
and say go to its left pointer left child
and then go to the parent node of that node,
it has to be the same as the right node so
it's just that they're
in the parent, it's always the inverse of the
left or right operation,
it's also true for writing
well, and it's a binary tree, now
the intuition of what
you might say we were
inspired by the
linked list.  A linked list had a very
similar structure,
maybe an element or a node, it
had an element,
it had a next pointer and a
previous pointer
so in a sense what we have is if it's
doubly linked we had a previous pointer
it was singly linked we only had a next
pointer
and if you think about the limitations of
linked lists especially singly linked
lists
if you only have one pointer to a node
you can only create a list
and so the result is
you know this node is going to have a
depth linear depth means how many
pointers do I have to follow to get here
from the root the structure which for
linked lists was the head
it was doubly linked okay I can have a
head and a tail and I can put
bidirectionals here but still the middle element
has linear depth so you can't
get there in
less than linear time with binary
trees because we use
two types of next  pointers left and
right,
we can build a tree, and we know that trees
in general have logarithmic,
can have logarithmic height,
so you can get to
any node in a tree starting from the root in only
log n traversals, so that's the intuition of what's
going on, today
we're going to talk about the height of a
tree,
so let me define,
I'm going to need a couple of definitions
here
subtree and
node height,
so a tree is decomposed into subtrees,
so for example, a subtree with root b
or subtree b
is that part of the tree,
so that's that node and all the
descendants of that node, so since we
have parents and children,
we can generalize in the sense of a family tree,
we can talk about the ancestors of a node, so the
ancestors of f
are its father, its grandfather and grandmother, its grandmother
and grandfather, etc.
together they're all called
ancestors,
this doesn't quite match the
familiar trees, because in family trees
you have
two  parents, here you only have a unique
parent,
or the poor root has no parents,
we also talk about this as a mixed
metaphor of the
leaves of a tree,
these are
people without children, parents will
complain about this,
but many, like many of us in this room, we do
n't have children (children) yet, so we're called
leaves,
you can tell your parents, hey, I'm just a
leaf, you know, blowing in the wind,
so you know, like this is so many
mixed metaphors, but we
always draw trees down, like the
structure of the root of a tree,
but we call the ends of the roots leaves,
which are still
upside down, these are trees for you, lots of
interesting analogies okay, but
ancestors are useful, descendants are
also useful,
so the descendants of b are all of its children
, all of its grandchildren,
and everything way down,
but only inside the subtree, so the subtree of
x
consists of x and its descendants,
and we think of x as the root of
that subtree, so we kind of
forget about everything outside
subtree
when we talk about subtree x Let's
talk about
the depth of a node.
The depth of a node is,
I think, the number of its ancestors,
um, but I usually think of it
as
the number of edges
and on the path from
x to the root
so each node has a unique path that
goes up until it ca
n't go up anymore, so
the depth of e is
two because
on the path from the root a to e there are two edges, one two,
so maybe I'll write some depths well, the depth of
e is two the
depth of these guys is one the depth of the
root is zero
two three, so that's the
depth, I'm going to
clean this up a little bit
so we can focus on the picture, all right,
the height, so the depth is the measurement
down because you know if you
imagine depth in water, that's the
surface of the water and
then we measure how deep you are from
the surface,
the height in the opposite direction we
'll measure from the level of the leaves
up because the leaves are the bottom of the
tree, so the height of
the node is going to be
the number of edges
on the longest path down,
okay, that's the same thing as the
maximum depth of the node
in the subtree x,
let's denote the height in red,
so what's the length of the longest path from
f to the leaf, okay, f is a leaf, so all
the leaves have
zero depth, sorry, height zero,
turn it back,
um, there's this, so there's two
ways down, this doesn't go to the
leaf, uh, this one goes to the leaf,
and its height is zero, so this height is
one, here one edge of leaf b
has two leaves that it can reach, we take the
longest one, so it's length two, and it
also has height three.
Okay, the height we measure up, the depth
we measure
down, one thing that we care about
is just the height of the
whole tree, and this is the
height of the root,
and I'm going to call it h because
we're going to use this a lot,
and today we're going to get to the point where
all these execution times instead of
being logarithmic,
they're going to be of order h,
so our goal today is to make all of the
important things for  us operations map
in order h
and then next we go to lecture to
guarantee that h is always log n
and then we get time log n so we need to
do a bunch of work to get to log n
today we're going to do the work i.e. all the
tree manipulations
and if your tree is nice and
small it doesn't have a lot of height
if it has logarithmic height everything
will be logarithmic of course there are trees
that are really bad
right we can have a
tree like this which is basically a
linked list
where we only use right pointers and all the
left pointers are gone
so there is height there are trees that are really tall
have a lot of height hmm we want to avoid
that but we won't worry about that until the
next lecture question
what is the height of node c the height of
node c is zero
because the length of the longest path
the number of edges in the longest
path down is zero so we
count edges not vertices so
yeah, the height of the tree,
of course just the depth, the
maximum depth, I think that's right,
so the height here is
three, and the maximum depth is a
terribly drawn three,
so they correspond in the
maximum case,
but we use height to always mean the maximum
, so
we're talking about the height of the tree, the
depth of the tree is not defined,
just the depth of the notes, okay,
how can we use these trees to
represent a
sequence or a set, well,
I argue that there is a natural order in trees
called the traversal order of the
nodes or elements
and the tree, so I'll define a
certain order, let
's say in this example
let's do an example first, the
traversal order
would be f
d b
e a
c I feel like I'm in music class, this is
my guitar or something like that, but it's not me I
hope hmm
if this is a coincidence then what is this
order what I would like to do
is
recursively determine the order where the
root of the tree is somewhere in the middle,
and everything in  the left subtree comes
before the root and
everything in the right subtree comes after
so you can see here c comes after a and
then all the other nodes come before
a and recursively if i look at node b
this node b which here comes e
to the right of it
but it's all to the left of a so
e
is between b and a would be to the left
and then f and d to the left of that
and again f comes before d
because f is in the left subtree d
well so we say
for each node the
nodes
at x dot left come before x
and the nodes at x dot right come
after x
and this uniquely defines an order which
is called the traversal order
it is also called the traversal in order
order it is called in order because it is
in order of traversal so it is very
circular but
you may have seen the traversal in order it is the
same there
is a very simple algorithm to
calculate this
if i want  to iterate,
let's call it this way, if I want to
iterate over
all the nodes in a subtree x, rooted
at x,
I'll just iterate over all the
nodes in the left subtree, then output
x itself,
and then iterate over all the nodes in the
right subtree,
okay, you may have seen this algorithm
before, this is just another way of
codifying the same thing,
the result is all the nodes in
the subtree appear continuously without any
breaks,
and then the parent parent will
precede after depending on whether
it's a left or right child,
okay, now it's just a matter of
connecting the dots, since we're
representing the order
and for the sequence, what will that be the
order of the sequence, if we want to store n
elements from x0 to x1,
we're going to create some kind of tree,
we're going to put x0 here,
x1 here, x2 here, x3 here, x4 here, x5
here, you can see that I'm very used to
dealing with traversal orders, this takes
some time,
you can also see it here, we're
going to put x1 on this node  x2
sorry x0 here x1 here x2 here and so on
the same order that I specified
okay this is for sequences for sets this
order will just be a sorted
order
and we will effectively
represent the sorted order of the keys let
's say ascending but before we get to that
let's talk about the different operations that we
can do
just by playing around with the traversal order
and then we are going to use them to
build the sequence and set up the operations
that we are interested in
so the first operation i
will first call the subtree it seems appropriate that
it is called first
this is the first so given a node
which i will call the node this defines a
subtree
which usually we draw subtrees as
triangles hanging from a node
so here i would write x
and then there is some subtree of all the
descendants of x
so first the subtree i would like to
say among
all the nodes in this subtree
which is the first in order  traversal,
so just limiting myself to
this subtree, so the tree of this,
so where is it in this tree,
the note is actually part of many
subtrees, good question, uh,
f f is its own in subtree f
uh
f is also in subtree d f is in
subtree b, as i drew
f is in subtree a, it's
exactly in its ancestor subtree,
but in this operation, when we define a
node,
our node defines only one subtree, it's the
root of only one subtree,
and it's this subtree that we
I want to know, among all
these nodes, which includes the node itself
and other things, which one is
first
in this traversal order, it's similar to the
practice with traversal orders,
so where do I look for this node,
yeah, the leftmost leaf
in the image, it's here, but images
can be misleading,
we just want to go
as far left as possible, when I say left, I
mean this iteration node is equal to
node.left,  you just look at our
definition
all the nodes on the left are before x
and all the nodes on the right so
it has to be in the left subtree if
there is one of
course we can't do this forever so
say until we fall out of the tree which
means the node is out of
order but we stopped before that happens
so it's like instructions like
oh you keep going until you see the store
and this is the block right before that that's
fine this is not very useful
so you keep repeating the node equals no
dot until the node is
zero and then you undo one step okay you
all know how to program that it's not
hard well so that
last
node that is not actually the root it
could be a node
maybe it has no left children but in
that case i would argue that the node is first
in its subtree traversal order
because,
if there are no nodes on the left,
come before x, then x is actually the first,
okay, and that's it, uh, returns
the node,
so I'm changing the node in place here and the
last one before I hit none, that's
the minimum,
that's the first element in the
traversal order, you can also define a subtree
last,
okay, let's make it more interesting one
next
node, so in this case I want to know what
is
next
after the node in the
overall traversal order of the tree, okay, here
I've limited myself to
one subtree now I'm thinking
about the whole tree in the entire
traversal order,
and given a node, I want to know which one is
next,
call it a successor, I feel like I
need to
create some kind of Royal Family joke,
but
I don't know how to do that,
each node has a unique successor, let's
give some examples
so we can start with f, the successor of
f, if we just index this
list, the successor is d, okay, the
successor of d is b  successor b is simplicity
well it's very easy to read successors
when I wrote down the traversal order
but let's think about how to do it
in a tree
well
let's see there will be two
cases
if I look at successor a it has a
right descendant
and in that case the right descendant a is
the successor but that's not always the case i
don't have a good example but if i
had another node here let's call it
g well successor a is
actually g right because
all these elements come after a in
order
but which one comes first the leftmost
leaf
okay this is the problem we just solved
so if a has a right child what
we want is the leftmost leaf
first
in this subtree
right subtree right child subtree
so that's the first case
if well node.right
so if we have a right child then
we want the
subtree first
right child
Great, we can reduce to this other
operation,
but what if a node doesn't have the
right child,
so for example it could be a leaf, let's say
we take the
successor, I mean it doesn't have to
be a leaf, it could be f which has no
children, it could be d which has one child
but doesn't have the right child,
so what is the successor of f, is d
which in this case is the parent, but
that's not always the case, for example if we make
the successor of e,
its parent is actually earlier in
order because e was the right child
f was the left child, so its
parent
was
the successor of d, it happens, b because
it was the left child of its
parent,
okay, so it seems like a simple case, if
we are the left child of our parent,
then our successor is our parent, okay,
based on that  a little example but we can
argue about that in a moment
what is the successor of e okay it's
not b because that comes before actually
everything in this subtree b
comes before or equals
e um so we have to keep moving up
and then it turns out that the successor of e
is a because that subtree
was the left child of a because b was the left child of
a
so the general strategy is to go up the tree
until we we go up the
traversal the reverse direction of which
will be left
okay so go up the
tree when i say i mean node
equals node.parent
iteration
until
we go up the left
branch
so that would mean the node before we
make the change is
equal to node.parent node.parent.left
okay so we can check that and then after
we do this traversal this  the parent node
is the node we're looking for
okay why is that true in general let me
paint a more general picture
so we start with some node
and let's say its parent is on the right
so it comes later in the order for
a while sorry I'll take that back
we make a descendant
so it comes later on the left for a while
so all these nodes will come
earlier in the order because by
definition everything in the right
subtree comes after
and at some point we have a parent that is on
the right meaning this node
was the left child of
this parent and this node by
definition will come
after all the nodes here
and can there be anything between the
node and this well
this parent ancestor grandparent
only if something was in this
subtree and we're in the case here
where there is no right subtree of our
source node
so this is where all the nodes
between the node and here will be
but they are not there and  so this is a
successor
so this is kind of a general argument
why does this
work i see the question yes
placed in the order of traversal so
the order of traversal is never computed explicitly
why we are taught it is always implicit
we can't afford to maintain
this let's say an array it's just
in our heads maybe i'll draw this with a
cloud around it we just think that's
cool this is not in the computer explicitly
in the computer everything we store this is this
and the reason is it's expensive we
we can't maintain an array of
things and be able to insert in the
middle
because it's cheap i can afford to
maintain this structure
and do all these things
so we talk about these
operations because they are allowing us
to manipulate the order or in this case
allowing us to
iterate the order so this was an
algorithm to traverse the
whole order
but it takes linear time it was
start in order find me
first what was in order and it was given
one node find me next
how long do these operations take
at most the height of the whole
tree is actually going to be
the depth of this first node but in the
worst case it's going to be the height of the
whole tree
in total all of these operations
are going to be of order h
we need to think about that in every case
except this one which is of order n
so by going through everything hmm
in this case we just
call the subtree first so it
takes up order h here we
go up the tree not down but
it's going to cost exactly the same as
the height of the node that we
stop earlier but in the worst case the order h
for all of these operations that we're
looking at today we just want to get the
order h bound
and later we'll bind the h so the point is
they're
fast if h is small like log n they're
almost instantaneous
whereas if i had to update an explicit
traversal order like say an array
i would have to spend
linear time every time i make a change
and yes it would be fast to make a successor
if i kept it explicit
but maintain  it would be impossible
to maintain it efficiently it would be
impossible
question about questions
so okay
cool these were the queries that
i want to follow
see what's next in the
traversal sequence now let's talk about actually
changing the traversal sequence so these are
insert and delete operations
which will roughly correspond to an insert
or delete
but that's not quite we're not quite in the
world of sequencing yet instead
we're going to
focus on inserting or deleting in the middle of a
subtree
so i'll have two nodes
so in the
traversal order
so the node already exists in the tree new a
new node that doesn't yet exist in the
tree so i'm calling it new
and what i would like to do is insert a new one
right after the node and there's a symmetric
operation that inserts before
it is implemented almost
identically so we'll just focus on that
so i want to insert this new node into the
traversal order which again is in our
heads this is all
in our thought bubble
this is what we want  to achieve, and we
have to do that by manipulating
this tree and however we change the tree,
it defines a new traversal order, so
maybe let's do an example first,
actually, I probably want this universal
order
to track this, so
let's say the first thing we want to do
is insert
g before e
i I want to illustrate both
operations.
Insert h
after e,
okay, well,
insert g before e, so conceptually
we want to insert g
here and the way we get node
e,
and we get a sort of empty node I
mean a node that only contains g, it
doesn't have any pointers yet,
and we would like to put it before e,
where should I put its
left child, okay,
this is a simple case, if I'm trying to
insert before, and there's no left child,
insert it there, if I'm trying to insert
after, and there's no right child,
insert it there easily, so let me write the
first case,
so here we insert after, so if there's
no
right child,
add a new one
there, okay, I'm using informal language,
put
this new node
b here instead of writing, for example,
node.write equals new
because it's just one operation you
need to do, one thing you would do is set
node.write equals new but  you also
have to set the parent of new to
node.write,
so instead of worrying about these two
pointer changes because we always do
bidirectional pointer changes, I'm just
going to use
pseudocode and then in the recitation you'll
see the actual python code that does all of this
,
so there's another case,
so this should be the second example.
insert h
after right
insert h after a so that we already have a
node after a
in the right child of this right subtree
so where do I want to place
h relative to
the well it has to be to the right of a but
it has to be
before c it has to be to the left of c
so that means we want to place it
here okay in this case it was pretty
easy because this tree was small
where do I want to place it well
wherever the
subtree first tells me to put it right the
subtree first gives me the
successor it's all kind of
parallel um
we're now in the case where our node has a
right child
and then the successor tells us where the
successor is this is the first
node which is the leftmost child in the
right subtree of the node okay there's
a lot of pointers in this sentence but
it's
clearly visible in the image so this is
in this case we had a node but it
didn't have the right child so  we just added
new to be its right child, okay
otherwise
we had a right child, so here's a node,
there's this node here
node.right
which now we assume exists
and it defines a whole subtree, there's
this node
which is the first node in the
traversal order of the subtree, also known as the
successor of the node,
so I'll call this successor of the
node in the current traversal order,
but of course we'd like to make
new the new successor of the node, so
where does it go here,
we want to add it as the left child
of the old successor,
okay so put well
node,
so take the successor and if you look at the
code for the successor we're in this
case so we know it's just going to call the
subtree first from node.right and remember the
subtree first
went left as far as it could go so that
means this  the
successor node is guaranteed not to
have a right left child node because it was
defined by traversing right once and then
traversing left as much as you could
until there's no more left left left which means we
can create another left
just add a new one there and we're
done if you look at the traversal order
it's going to be node then new
then old successor then the rest of
this subtree
okay that's cool in all cases
i mean it was constant time
here we spent constant time after we
called the successor successor costs order h
time
so it's order h new new
well
put new there
clearly well that was an insertion
let's do a delete
define the specification correctly and an example
all of this will have two cases well
let me
i didn't update so now h after a
so it should be like that
you can check the new traversal order of
this tree that's exactly what
i'm going to do next a few
deletions,
let's
delete f first and then we're going to
okay, this is
confusing,
and then we're going to delete a, so
where is f, we assume that we're given a
pointer to f this node,
okay, it's a leaf, so if I want to
delete it I just erase it
easily, leaves are easy to delete, there's nothing to
work on, so that means I
delete the pointer from d
to f, okay, we just erase this guy,
okay, now here's the trickier part,
let's assume I want to delete the root of the
tree, this is the
trickiest case, but generally it's going to be
somewhere in between a leaf and a root,
so if I want to delete, if I just
erase it, then suddenly these
pointers to nowhere appear
and I'm splitting the tree into two parts, I do
n't want to do that, I need to keep
my tree connected,
so I'm going to resort to this trick,
which is I forget whether I'm using a successor or a
predecessor of a predecessor,
so I'll see  on a we already
defined the successor and
there is the predecessor so i'm going to
look at the predecessor of a
which is e you can check that here the one
before a is
e this is the left subtree
find me the rightmost element keep going
until i can get this e
so now these guys are next to each other in
order and i'm going to remove from
order
so i can cheat for a moment and swap
their labels
i'm going to erase a and e here and put
e
after what because this is moving
down the tree and if i get to a
leaf i'm done so
i'm not done yet because it's
not a leaf so i look at the
predecessor of a again now the
predecessor of g
we hope it's always in well further down the
tree and then i change
a to g
well i've preserved the
traversal order except when a
falls by just moving a earlier in
order here
and now a is a leaf and i  can erase it,
okay so this is what we're
going to follow now, actually it's a little
complicated, sometimes we need to use
predecessors sometimes we need to use
successor, okay so the cases are
if the node is a leaf, just
detach it from the parent,
that's kind of the base case in
recursion, otherwise there
are two cases, if
so if we're not a leaf that means we
have a
left child or a right child or
both, that would be an easy case,
but generally I either have a
left child
or I have a right child, either way
I'll be happy, so I don't need
both
okay what do I do if I have a
left child
that guarantees me that if the predecessor of a node
is inside the left subtree, which means
it's lower in the tree,
if I don't have a left child, the
predecessor will actually be higher in the
tree and I don't want to go higher,
okay so if in  I'm left with a child element, I know the
predecessor is lower,
so I'm going to swap
my item with the contents of my node
with the element of my predecessor,
and then I'm going to recursively remove the
predecessor.  Okay, this is the case
that we've been looking at in this code
in this example, because we've always had a
left child, if we have a right child but
no left child, we just do the opposite, we
swap places with our successor,
and then we remove the successor, in
any case we're going down,
so if we start at some node, like a
route, every time we do this operation,
we're going down and then we're
going down,
and in general we're going to keep going down,
picking up where we left off, which means that the
total amount of time we spend is
proportional to
the height of the tree in the worst case of
the question,
so we're not used to having a right child
, so we're changing the
node IDs when we do this,
because we did
n't actually move that
circle, the circle stayed in place, and
we changed the element that
was stored in that circle,
so do you call that  node e or a,
it doesn't matter, it's just the
root note,
okay, so we're going to play a lot of these
tricks, moving elements, which
we haven't done before, we've just been
creating
nodes and placing them somewhere, but now
we're
doing this delete operation, this is the first
time we're changing what's stored
in the nodes,
but we can still
get the traversal order right.  The traversal order of this
tree is dbgehc
this should be what we get here if I
remove f and
a
and sorry maybe f
trees won't keep the join
it's just the name of the game
we have to allow it otherwise we can't
do anything this is the short
version okay okay in the last few
minutes let me talk about how we take
these trees and implement a set
or a sequence okay i mentioned
this
so for a sequence
we just make the traversal order
equal to the order that we are trying to
represent the
order of the sequence
and if we are trying to get the elements of a set
with keys we will make the
traversal order
equal to ordered by increasing key
increasing key of element
some sense but then we need to
think about how we implement
all these operations so maybe the most
instructive to start with is
searching for a key in a tree
so this would correspond to binary
search
if i'm looking for a key let's say i'm
looking for
key g and i know this
can be hard in this example maybe i  I'll
replace all of this with numbers
so I can think about key values,
okay, so let's say 1 7
12 17
19 and 23.
this is now in key order if you think about
traversal order the
property is that all the keys in the
left subtree of the root are
less than the root and the root is
less than all the keys in the right
subtree and recursively all the way down
this is what's called the
binary search tree property bst property
these here we call them binary tree sets
or binary tree sets but they're
also known in the literature as
the term binary search trees which you may have heard
before so this is a
special case of what we
do where we keep the keys in
order
and then if I want to look up a key
like well 13
I compare this key to the root I see
oh it's not
equal and this is on the left because it's
less than
17. So  13 left from here 13 to the right of
13 to the right of 12 so I know that's
where 13 would belong
but there's no right child there so
I know I found I just returned nothing
if I was doing a search for the previous I would
return this note
because I tried to go right
last time before I fell off the tree
I tried to go right and
so the last note I had the
previous element if I was trying to determine the
next what I do is I would just take
this node and calculate its successor
which we already know how to do and it
turns out to be the root
okay now I can do these imprecise
searches where I find the previous and I
find the next as
I fall off the tree I find either the
previous or the next and
then with the predecessor or successor I
can find the other one
okay so how can we find and
find the previous
and find the next
sequences.  We need to
work a little more,
we'll do it next time