we just started a new unit on graph
theory
which is going to be sort of our focus
for the next couple lectures uh in 6.06
uh and so i thought we'd give a little
bit of review at the beginning of
lecture because as usual i
muddled together a lot of notions in our
previous lecture uh
and then start with some new ideas so
basically in our previous lecture we
talked about an algorithm called breadth
first search
uh and then almost always you see that
paired with the second algorithm called
depth first search
uh and following tradition and basically
logic we'll uh do the same thing uh
in 06 today uh but in any event for
today we'll
we'll stick to the technical material so
as a little bit of review
i guess actually the one thing i didn't
do on this slide was actually draw a
graph so
we should probably start with that uh so
if you recall
graph is a collection of nodes or
vertices depending
i don't know is it like a european
american thing or something uh
and edges right so here's an example
which as usual i'm not managing to draw
particularly clearly
uh so this uh graph is kind of like a
cycle so i have directed edges
here here here and here and of course uh
there are many kind of variations on the
theme
right so our basic uh sort of definition
of a graph is that we have some set
v which is like the set of vertices
and then we have a set e which is set of
edges
and this was a subset of v cross v and
this is nothing more than
fancy notation for saying that an edge
is a pair of vertices right like a from
and a two vertex
of course there are many variations on
this theme you could have a directed
versus an
undirected uh graph so this one is
directed
meaning the edges look like arrows if
they didn't have arrowheads they'd be
undirected
uh we defined something called a simple
graph where you have essentially no
repeated edges so for instance you can't
do something like this where you have
the same edge
twice um and then there are a couple
different definitions that were kind of
useful right so
in particular i'm gonna erase this oops
useless edge here maybe make my graph
slightly more interesting so i'll add
another
edge going in the reverse direction so
maybe i have um
i'm going to give my vertices labels x y
z and w then uh we talked about the uh
the neighbors of a given vertex
which are the vertices that you can
reach by following edges in or out of
your your vertex right so in particular
the outgoing neighbors uh which we sort
of implicitly
defined in our previous lecture but
didn't call it out um
we're going to notate with adj plus
and these are all of the things that you
can reach by going out of a
vertex into the next one so for example
uh adj
plus of w is going to be the set of
vertices
well notice i can get from w to y and
also from w
to z yeah so
oop nope y comma z
okay uh so to continue just our tiny
amount of review for the day
uh remember that a graph uh there are
many different ways to represent a graph
uh the sort of brain dead one will be
just like a big long list of edges but
of course for
our algorithms that's not a particularly
efficient way to check things like
does this edge exist in my graph uh so
the the basic representation that i
think we're mostly working from in this
course
is to think of a graph like a set of
vertices each of which
maps to another set of vertices so
roughly every vertex
maybe stores its outgoing uh set of
edges
right and and so this is kind of nice
because of course uh very quickly we can
answer questions like
is this edge inside of our graph or we
can iterate over the neighbors of a
vertex and so on which are the kind of
typical things that we do
in a lot of graph algorithms and then
finally
in our previous lecture we started
talking about paths right so a path
is like a chain of vertices that can get
me from one vertex to the other
only following edges of my graph there
was a term that
i think i forgot to define last time
because it didn't really matter a ton
which is a simple path which is just a
path that doesn't have the same vertex
more than once
uh and then of course there are many
different questions you can ask about a
graph
that are basically different problems
involving computing paths right so for
instance
the shortest path between two vertices
is sort of our canonical
one and graph theory or you could ask
questions about reachability and so on
so there's our uh our basic review from
our previous lecture
uh do our does our course staff have any
questions about uh
things so far excellent okay
and uh there's one additional piece of
terminology that i fudged a little bit
last time
or other uh my my co-instructors
suggested a bit of an attitude
adjustment so i thought i'd better uh
uh clarify really quick there's this
interesting phrase uh linear time which
we all know and love in
in computer science theory and and the
sort of implicit thing especially in
this course is that when we say linear
time we mean in the size of the input
right and so if we have a linear time
graph algorithm
well how much space does it take to
store a graph well we need a list of
vertices and a list of edges
and nothing else so a reasonable way to
interpret this phrase linear time
is that it's an algorithm that looks
like what we've shown on the screen
right the
the times proportional to maybe the sum
of the number of vertices and the number
of edges
if that makes you uncomfortable like it
does for me because one of these can
kind of scale on the other
i think it's always fine to add more
detail right so if you want to say
linear in the sum of the number of
vertices and edges that's that's
perfectly fine
but if you see this phrase that's uh how
you should interpret it
hopefully that's a fair way to put it
excellent okay so um
last time we talked about an algorithm
called breath first search bfs
for those in the know breath first
search uh is an algorithm
uh and and the reason we use the word
breath is because it's kind of remember
we
we talked about level sets last time uh
because we talked about breath first
search
in the context of computing shortest
paths uh and in particular
uh we have our our source uh node all
the way on the left hand side
and then breadth first search
constructed all the nodes that were
distance one away
right that's the first level set and
then all the distance two away and then
all the distance three away and so on
right so in particular like the level
set l3 isn't visited until we're
completely done
with level set l2 today we're going to
define another algorithm
which is called depth first search which
doesn't do that but rather
starts with the source vertex and just
starts walking all the way out until it
can't do that anymore and then kind of
backtracks it's one way to think about
it
uh and so somehow in breath first search
we're like drawing concentric circles
in depth first search we're doing the
opposite we're like shooting outward
until we reach the outer boundary and
then exploring a graph that way
okay and these are sort of the two
extremes in terms of graph search kind
of techniques
uh that are typically used under the
basic building blocks for
for algorithms and graph theory so in
order to motivate and think about death
for search
we're going to define a second problem
which is closely related to shortest
path but not exactly the same
and that's the reachability problem so
here i have the world's simplest uh
directed graph so the black things are
the edges
and the circles are the uh notes or the
vertices
and i've marked one special note in blue
uh and
his name is the source node and now the
question i want to ask is what are
all of the other nodes in my graph that
i can reach
by following edges directed edges
starting with the source right so
obviously i can get to the node in the
lower right no problem
and of course once i get there i can
traverse an edge
upward to get to that second green
vertex
notice that i was really sneaky and evil
and i drew edges in this graph that
might
make you think that the red note is
reachable the red one being on the upper
left i'm realizing now that for
colorblind people this isn't a great
slide
uh but of course uh because all the
edges
from the red vertex on the left here
point out i can't actually reach it
from the blue source node so the
reachability problem is just asking
which nodes can i reach
from a given source it's pretty
straightforward i think
of course there are many ways uh to
solve this right in fact one way we
could do it
uh would be to use our previous lecture
right we could compute the shortest path
distance from the source to all the
other
nodes and then what would the length of
the shortest path from the source to an
unreachable node b
any thoughts from our audience here
infinity thank you uh professor domain
uh right so in addition to this
uh of course a totally reasonable
question thinking back to our
shortest path lecture uh there are sort
of two queries we might make right one
is just what is the length of the
shortest path
the other is like what is the actual
shortest path from the source to a given
vertex we can ask a very similar thing
here right which is like okay
you tell me that the green guy is
reachable but like how like give me a
path as as evidence or
a certificate if you want to be fancy
about it so
uh in order to do that just like last
time remember we defined a particular
data structure that was the shortest
path tree
uh we can do something very similar here
right in particular
this is like the extent of my powerpoint
skill here
if i have a reachability
problem i can additionally store i can
decorate every node in my graph with one
other piece of information
which is the previous node along some
path
from my source to that thing right and
just like last time
if i want to get an actual path from the
source to w
what could i do i could start with w and
then just keep following those parent
relationships
until i get back to the source then if i
flip the order
of that list of vertices i get a path
from the source to the target that's
valid right so this object is called a
path tree just like we talked our parent
tree rather
uh just like we talked about in our last
lecture uh there's no reason why this
thing should ever have a cycle in it
uh it's certainly a tree um
right so uh that's the basic
reachability problem
and in addition to that we can compute
this object p which is going to give me
sort of information about
how any given node was reachable there's
a slight difference between the parent
tree that i've defined here
and the shortest path tree which i
defined last time which is i'm not going
to require
that the shortest path i get or oh man
the path i get when i backtrack
along my my tree p is the shortest path
it's just
a path right because for the
reachability problem i actually don't
care
right like i could have a weird
circuitous crazy long path
and it still tells me that a node is
reachable
uh right so that's our basic setup and
our data structure
and now we can introduce a problem to to
solve reachability again we already have
an algorithm for doing that right which
is to compute shortest paths
and and remember that our shortest path
algorithm from previous lecture
took linear time and the size of the
input right it took uh v
plus e time now the question is can we
do a little better
the answer obviously is yes because i
just asked it and i gave you this
problem
okay and here's a here's a technique for
doing that
which unsurprisingly is a recursive
algorithm i'm going to swap my notes for
my handwritten notes
and this uh algorithm is called death
first search
and here's the basic strategy i'm going
to choose a source node i've labeled
that node one
here i suppose actually would have made
sense for me to actually
zero index this maybe in the slides i'll
i'll fix it later
but in any event i'm going to mark my my
source node
and now i'm going to look at every node
every edge coming out of that node and
i'm going to visit it recursively
right so that's our sort of for loop
inside of this function
visit and then for each neighboring node
if i haven't visited it before
in other words i currently haven't given
it a parent right that's our if
statement here
i'm going to say well now they do have a
parent and that parent is me
and i'm going to recurse you guys see
what this is doing it's kind of crawling
outward inside of our graph so let's uh
let's let's do the example on the screen
and i purposefully designed this
experiment or this example to look a
little bit different from breath first
search
at least if you choose to do the
ordering that i did so here's our graph
one two five
three four okay and let's uh think about
the traversal order
uh that that's first search is gonna do
right so here's our source
and now what does the source do it
record so let's think about a recursion
tree
so we have uh the source all the way up
in here
and now he's gonna start calling uh the
visit function recursively
so um and i'll go ahead and number these
the same as on the screen
well he has one outgoing neighbor and it
hasn't been visited yet
so of course the very first recursive
call that i'll make is to that neighbor
too
now the neighbor two also recurses
hopefully this kind of schematic picture
makes some sense what i'm trying to draw
here
and well now the two has two neighbors
right a three and a five so let's say
that we choose three first
well the three now recurses he calls
four and then the recursion tree is kind
of done so now it goes back
out and then finally well now the three
are oh boy yeah the two looks at its
next neighbor which is the five
uh and envisions that recursively notice
that this is
not following the level sets right the
death first
search algorithm got all the way to the
end of my tree in the recursive uh
calls and then kind of backed its way
out to the two before calling the five
these are not the same technique one
goes all the way to the end
and then kind of backtracks whereas when
i say backtrack what i mean is the
recursion is kind of unraveling
um whereas in breadth first search i
visit everything in one level set before
i work my way out
does that distinction make sense
okay so of course we need to prove that
this algorithm does something useful uh
so let's do that now so
in particular we need a correctness
proof so our claim is going to be
that uh let's see here
the depth first search algorithm visits
oh uh i guess reachable
v um
and that it correctly sets uh the parent
in in the process
um okay so
in order to prove this uh of course as
with almost everything in this course
we're going to use induction
uh and in particular what we're going to
do is
do induction on the distance from the
source so we're going to say that like
for all vertices in distance k
from the source this statement is true
and then we're going to prove this
inductively on k
okay so we want to do
induction on k which is the distance
to the source vertex so
uh as with all of our inductive proofs
we have to do our base
uh case and then our inductive step so
in the base case
k equals zero this is a hella easy case
because of course
uh what is the thing that is distance
zero from the source
it's the source yeah and take a look at
our our strategy all the way at the top
of this slide we explicitly set the
correct parent for the source and in
some sense visit it because
the very first thing we do is call visit
of s so there's kind of nothing to say
here yeah or there's plenty to say if
you write it on your homework
but your lazy instructor is going to
write a check mark here
okay so now we have to do our inductive
step
so what does that mean we're going to
assume that our statement is true for
all nodes within a distance k and then
we're going to prove that our statement
is true for all nodes within a distance
k plus one
okay uh so uh let's do that let's
consider
a vertex v that's
distance k plus one away so in other
words the distance from the source to v
is equal to k plus one right and what's
our goal our goal is to show that the
parent of v
is is set correctly yeah
what's that
oh sorry i forgot that the distances in
this class are ordered yeah that's
absolutely right so it should be the
distance from s to v
yeah sorry i'm really not used to
thinking about directed graphs but
that's that's
a good fix okay so uh now what can we do
well there's this number is distance
here so in particular there's some
shortest path from
s to v so remember our argument last
time right
that essentially when we look at
shortest path and we kind of truncate by
one it's still the shortest path
uh that property doesn't matter so much
here but at least we know that there's
another vertex on the path
which is one a distance one less
away so let's let's take you
which is also a vertex to be the
previous node
on the shortest path
from s to v right
and so in particular we know that the
distance from s
to u is equal to k and conveniently
of course by our inductive uh hypothesis
here we know that our property is true
for this guy
okay so now our algorithm what do we
know well because our property is true
the visit function at some point in its
life is called on this vertex
u right that's sort of what our
induction assumes
so we have two cases um
right so uh when we uh when we visit you
um we know that
when we call this uh uh visit function
well remember that v kind of by
definition is in adj plus of view right
so
in particular dfs is going to consider
v when it gets called
okay and now there's two cases
right so either when this happens
p of v does not equal none
right well what does that mean well it
means that we already kind of found
a suitable parent for v uh and we're in
good shape
otherwise p of v
does equal none well in this case a very
next line of code correctly sets the
parent
and and we're all set right so in both
of these two cases
uh we show that the parent of uh you was
set correctly either by that line of
code right here or just previously
uh and and so in either case our our
induction is done
all right i guess uh given the feedback
i received from our previous lecture
we now can and end our latex uh suitably
okay so what did we just show we showed
that the death first search algorithm
can dig around in a graph and tell me
all of the things that are
are searchable or rather are reachable
from a given source
just basically by calling visit on that
source and then expanding outward
recursively okay so i think this is
certainly
straightforward from an intuitive uh
perspective it's easy to get lost when
you write these kind of formal
uh induction proofs because they always
feel a tiny bit like tautology so you
should go home and
kind of convince yourself that it's that
it's not okay so of course what do we do
in this class we always follow the same
kind of boring pattern
the first thing we do define an
algorithm second thing we do
make sure it's the right algorithm
what's the third thing we need to do
analyze it that's right in particular
make sure that it like finishes before
the heat death of the universe
uh and indeed uh death first search uh
doesn't really take all that long which
is a good thing
um so let's think about this a bit so
what's going to end up happening in
depth first search
well we're going to visit every vertex
at most once right kind of by definition
here
and in each case we're going to just
visit its neighboring edges
can we ever traverse an edge more than
one time
right because the visit function only
ever gets called uh one time per vertex
and our edges are directed
right so kind of you think about the
from of every edge uh the from vertex is
only ever visited one time
and hence every edge is only visited one
time
do we ever visit ah yes does dfs work
an undirected graph uh absolutely so
there's sort of uh different ways to
think about it
uh one is to think of an undirected
graph like a directed graph with two
edges pointed either way which i think
is in this class how we actually
kind of notated it in the previous
lecture um
yeah actually that's that's probably a
reasonable way to reduce it so we'll
stick with that
uh right now does dfs ever visit a
vertex that is not reachable from the
source
well the answer is no right because all
i ever do is recursively call on my
neighbors and so kind of by definition
if i'm not reachable dfs will never see
it so if i think about my run time
carefully it's not
quite the same as breath first search
remember that breath for search took v
plus e time in depth first search
it just takes order e time because i'm
expanding outward from the source vertex
hitting every edge adjacent to every
uh every vertex that i've seen so far uh
but i never
reach a vertex that i have in the that
isn't reachable
right and so because this only ever
touches every edge one time
uh we're in good shape uh and i see a
question here
yeah does vfs reach vertices that are
not reachable
uh does bffs reach vertices that are not
reachable
i guess not now that you mention it but
at least in my boring proof of
of order v time last time our very first
step of bfs
reserved space proportional to v um
which is enough to already uh make that
that run time correct
good question yeah so i guess the way
that we've talked about it where you
construct one level set after a time
um if you think of that as reachability
then then no it doesn't reach it in the
for loop
but just by construction when we started
uh we already
took the time that we're talking about
here so notice these runtimes aren't
exactly the same so for example if my
graph has no
edges bfs still is going to take time
yeah because it still has to uh take
order v
time at least the way in the sort of
brain dead way that we we've implemented
it last time obviously in that case we
could probably do something better
whereas the way that we we've defined
the dfs algorithm it only takes edge
time i see confusion on my instructor's
face
no okay good uh
the one thing to notice is that these
are algorithms for slightly different
tasks in some sense right the way that
we wrote down breadth first search last
time conveniently it gives us the
shortest path
um there are breath first algorithms
that doesn't i think we're in this class
we kind of think of breath first search
uh we motivate it in terms of the
shortest path problem but it's it's just
kind of a strategy
of working outwards from from a vertex
um
whereas here uh the way we've written
down death first search there's no
reason why
the path that we get should be the
shortest right so to think of a really
extreme
example let's say that i have a cycle
graph
right so i get a big loop like this
let's say that i do depth first search
starting from this vertex
well what will this what will happen
well this guy will call
its neighbor uh recursively who will
then call its neighbor recursively
we'll then call his name recursively and
so on
so of course when i do a death first
search
when i get to this vertex there's a
chain of one two three four vertices
behind it
is that the shortest path from the
source to uh the target here
well clearly not right i could have
could have traversed that edge i just
chose not to okay
so that's the death first search
algorithm it's just a essentially a
recursive strategy where
i traverse all my neighbors uh and and
each of my neighbors
versus their neighbors and and so on
okay so why might we want to use this
algorithm well we've already solved the
uh
the reachability problem so let's uh
solve a few more things using the same
uh basic strategy here
so there's some notions that we've sort
of
actually in some sense already used in
the lecture here but we might as well
call them out for what they are
which is this idea of connectivity so
a graph is connected if there's a path
getting from every vertex to every other
vertex
right now connectivity in a directed
graph is kind of a weird
object right like it could be like for
instance think of a directed graph with
just two edges
and one edge goes from u to v right then
i can get from v
to u but not vice versa that's kind of a
weird uh
notion so here uh in in 606 we'll mostly
worry about
connectivity only for undirected graphs
because they're the vertices just
basically come in like big connected uh
clumps
uh or the more technical term for a big
connected clump is a connected component
yeah so let's see an example so let's
say that i have a graph
which has an edge
and then a triangle
this is one graph do you see that
there's a collection of vertices
and there's a collection of edges but uh
it has two connected components right
the guy on the right
and the guy on the left meaning that
each vertex here is reachable from every
other vertex here
vertex here but there's no edge that
goes from the triangle to the line
segment
yep and so in the connected components
problem
we're given a graph like this guy and
initially we don't you know
okay when i draw it like this it's
pretty clear that uh
you know my graph has two connected
components maybe my graph embedding
algorithm failed and it drew an edge
like that
well then maybe i don't know it's still
pretty obvious that there's two
connected components but
you can imagine a universe where you
don't know that a priori and
and the problem you're trying to solve
is just to enumerate all these clumps of
vertices that are reachable from one
another
in a an undirected graph and
conveniently
um we can use depth first search to
solve this problem pretty easily
right so how could we do it well in some
sense
how can we find one connected component
so let's say that i just choose a vertex
in my graph
well what do i know about everything in
this connected component
well it's reachable from that vertex
remember we just solved the reachability
problem which says
if i have a vertex i can now tell you
all the other vertices that are
reachable from this guy
right so i could call dfs on well any
vertex of this cycle here
called the reachability thing and i know
that for every vertex there's one of two
things right either
that vertex has a parent in that object
p or it's the source
right so i could very easily find the
connected component corresponding to
that vertex does that make sense
have i found all the connected
components no i found one right i found
the one
corresponding to the arbitrary vertex
that i just chose so how could i fix
this
well it's super simple i could put a for
loop on the outside
which just loops over all the vertices
maybe and if that vertex is not part of
a connected component yet then i need to
make a new one
so then i call dfs on that vertex i
collect all the vertices that i got
and i iterate so this is a the algorithm
that uh in this class we're going to
call
full dfs by the way you could do the
same thing with full breadth first
search that's perfectly fine um
just kind of by analogy here right so
what is
full d oh this chalk is easier
uh well i'm going to iterate over all my
vertices
where i stands for for loop
right so if v is
unvisited
then i'm going to do d f s starting at v
i guess we use we use visit to refer to
this in the previous slide
and that's going to kind of flood fill
that whole connected component
and then i can connect you know collect
that connected component and continue
be a little bit careful because of
course we don't want like checking
things something to be visited to
somehow take
a bunch of time and make my algorithm
slower than it needs to be but of course
we have a set
data structure that we know uh can do
that in in order one time
at least in expectation okay
so this is the full dfs algorithm
it's really simple well it's dfs because
i called dfs on every vertex it was full
because i looped over all the vertices
uh right and so if we think about it how
much time does this algorithm take
it's a little bit sneaky because somehow
i have a for loop over all the vertices
that i could imagine a universe where i
get like vertices
times some other number because there's
a for loop and there's something inside
of it right i think that's how we're
used to thinking about
run time of for loops but
in this case that actually doesn't
happen because there's never a case
where an edge gets traversed more than
one time
because if i'm in one connected
component then by definition i can't be
in another connected component
right and so what happens is in some
sense this
innocent looking call to dfs i suppose
if you were like a lisp
programmer you somehow wouldn't like
this it has a side effect right
which is that i marked all the vertices
in that connected component as don't
touch me again
right and so implicitly i kind of
removed edges uh in this process
so if you think through it carefully the
runtime of this
full dfs algorithm is v plus e
time because every edge is touched no
more than one time
kind of amortized over all the the
different calls to d of s here
uh and there's this for loop over
vertices so there's clearly an an order
v that you you need here
does that argument make sense so again
we call that linear in the size of the
the input i'm going to
say it many times to get it in my own
head correctly
okay uh right so this is the the basic
problem
this comes up all the time by the way
like it seems like somehow a totally
brain dead weird algorithm like somehow
why would you want an algorithm finds
connected components like why would you
even have a graph that's disconnected or
something
um but of course that can happen a lot
so if like for instance maybe work at
a social media company and people have
friends but like
you know eric and i are friends and
we're not friends with anybody else we
have a we have a there's like a blood
oath kind of thing
uh then you know that might be not so
easy to find uh in the graph because of
course
we're just two among a sea of students
in this classroom
uh uh all of which have different
interconnections that are just
enumerated uh based on the list of edges
right
and and so even though like pictorially
it's kind of hard to draw
uh connected component algorithm in a
way that doesn't make it sound kind of
like a useless technique from the start
because like it's very clear there are
two connected components there
uh of course we still have to be able to
write code to solve this uh this sort of
thing
okay so for once i think i'm almost on
time
uh in lecture today so we have one
additional uh
application of of death first search uh
in our class today
uh which is sort of on the opposite end
of
the spectrum so we just talked about uh
graphs that are undirected and thinking
about cycles uh
now on the opposite end we might think
of a dag
so a dag is a directed acyclic graph
can anybody think of a special case of a
dag i suppose i should define it first
and then we'll come back to that
question uh which means uh exactly what
it sounds like so it's a graph that has
directed edges now
and doesn't have any cycles in it so
actually the graph i
gave you all the meaning of lecture
um i think secretly was an example of
one of these
so let's say that i have directed edges
maybe if i make the header triangle
that's a little easier to see
i'm not so sure uh in any event so i'm
going to have an
edge up and an edge to the right and
similarly an edge down an edge to the
right
this graph looks like a cycle but it's
not because the only direction
that i can move is from the left-hand
side to the right-hand side
so this is a directed graph and it
doesn't contain any cycles meaning
there's no path
that i can take from a vertex that gets
back to itself
along the directed edges okay and dags
show up all the time
now that i've defined what a dag is can
somebody give me an example of a dag
that we've already seen in 6006
a tree at least if we orient all the
edges kind of pointing downward in the
tree
yep otherwise i guess kind of debatable
whether it's a dagger you know if
there's if there's no direction to the
edges then somehow
the definition just doesn't apply um
okay so
in uh in processing directed acyclic
graphs uh there's a really useful thing
that you can do that's going to show up
in this class apparently quite a bit
which is kind of interesting to me i'm
curious to see
what that looks like which is to compute
a topological
order on the graph where topology is
here so as
a geometry professor in my day job i get
all excited uh
but in this case a topological order is
a fairly straightforward thing
actually it's defined on the screen and
i have bad handwriting anyway so let's
just stick with that
so topological ordering so if we think
of like f as a function that
assigns maybe every node an index in
array i should
i guess i shouldn't use the word right
here but it's just like an index in
ordering so like
this is the first vertex and this is the
second vertex and so on
then a topological order uh is one that
has the property shown here which is
that
if i have a directed edge from u to v
then f of u is less than f of v
so in other words if i look at the
ordering that i get in my topological
order
u has to appear before v yeah so let's
uh let's look at our example again so
let's number
let's give our nodes names so here's a
b c d
well what clearly has to be the first
node in my topological order
a right because all the way on the
left-hand side yeah
well after that it's a bit of a toss up
what do we know we know that b and c
have to appear before d
so maybe just to be annoying i do a c b
that's b and then d right so it's a
topological order
notice that things that are on the left
appear in my graph before things that
are on the right
where the word before here uh means that
there's an edge that points from one to
the other
okay by the way are topological
orderings
uh unique no so if we look at our graph
example here
a b c d is also a topological order
uh and what that means is it's somehow
very liberating right it means that
when we design an algorithm for finding
a topological order uh
there's some design decisions that we
can make uh and we just have to find one
among uh many
uh but in any event we're gonna define a
slightly different notion of order and
then we're gonna show that they're
closely linked to each other
and that is the finishing order so in
the finishing order we're going to call
full dfs on our graph remember that
means we iterate over all our nodes and
if we haven't seen that node yet we call
dfs on it
and now uh we're going to make an order
in which
as soon as the call to a node in that
visit function is complete
meaning i've already iterated over all
my neighbors then
i add my node to the ordering
that makes sense it's like a little bit
backward from what we're used to
thinking about so the order in which
full dfs
finishes visiting each vertex
yeah and now here's uh here's the claim
is that if we have a reverse finishing
order meaning that we take the finishing
order and then we flip it backward
that's exactly uh gonna give us a
topological ordering of the vertices in
our graph
um right so let's uh do that really
quickly
so in other words our claim here
i think yeah let's see is that if i have
a directed graph
so g is a dag
then um
uh let's see here then
oops my notes are backwards so i should
switch to my
jason's notes which of course are
correct
[Laughter]
right so if if i have a graph that's a
dag then the
reverse of the finishing order
is a topological order
by the way we're not going to prove the
converse that if i have
a topological order that somehow that
thing is the reverse of
uh dfs at least the way that maybe i
coded it
there's a slightly different statement
which is does there exist a dfs
that has that ordering but that's one
that we'll worry about
another time around piazza or whatever
okay so
uh let's see here
so we need to prove this thing so what
are we gonna do well what do we need to
check if
is a top large quarter is that if i look
at any edge in my graph
it obeys the relationship that i have on
the screen here
uh so in particularly we're going to
take the u
v inside of my set of edges and then
what i need
is the u is ordered
before v
uh using uh the reverse of the finishing
order that we've defined here
okay so let's think back to our
call to the dfs algorithm remember we
call this visit function
right so we have two cases right either
u
is visited before v or it ain't
yeah uh so let's let's do those uh those
two cases
so case number one
is u is visited
before v
okay
all right so what does that mean well
remember that there's an edge
like pictorially what's going on well
there's like all kinds of graph stuff
going on and then there's u
and we know that there's a directed edge
from u to v
right that's our our picture right and
maybe there's other stuff going on
outside of v
so in particular well just by the way
that we've defined that visit function
what do we know
we know that when we call visit
on u well
v is one of its outgoing neighbors so in
particular a visit on you
is going to call
visit v and we know that because
well you visited before v right
so currently v's parent is none when i
get to u
that makes sense now here's where
reverse ordering
we're gonna have to keep it in our head
right because now well you visit a view
called visitor v so notice that visit of
v
has to complete before visited of you
right
v completes before
visit of u well so in reverse
uh uh sorting
in reverse finishing order here what
does that mean
well if this completes before uh the
other guy then they get flipped backward
in the list
which is exactly what i want because
there's an edge from u to v
okay so case one is done now
we have case 2
which is that v is visited before you
okay so now um i'm gonna make one
additional observation
okay so uh let's now i'm gonna go back
to my other notes because i like my
schematic better
right so what's our our basic picture uh
here
i don't know i oh you know what it was i
printed out another copy of this
that's okay i can do it on my head okay
so here's my my source vertex his name
is s
now there's a bunch of edges and
whatever there's a long path
and now eventually what happens well
i have a node v
and somewhere out there in the universe
there's another node u
and what do i know i know that uh
there's by assumption i know that
there's an edge from u
to v that makes sense so that's our sort
of picture so far
okay so what do we know we know that our
graph is acyclic
yeah right that kind of by definition
that's our assumption so
can we reach u from v
in other words does there exist a path
from v to u
right so that would look like this
no because our graph is a cyclic and i
just drew a cycle right
so this is a big x there's a frowny face
here can't do it
he has hair unlike your instructor okay
so uh right so what does this mean well
okay
so by this uh picture i suppose
we know that uh u cannot be reached from
v
yeah so what does that mean well
it means that the visit to v is going to
complete
and never see you right because remember
though the visit to v only ever calls
things that are kind of descendants of v
right so in other words
visit a v completes
without seeing you
well that's exactly the same thing that
we showed in our first case right so by
the same uh reasoning
right what does that mean in our reverse
finishing order
right the ordering from from u to v is
is preserved
okay so that sort of completes our proof
here the
reverse finishing order gives me a
topological order which is kind of nice
and so this is a nice convenient way of
taking all of the nodes in a directed
acyclic graph
and ordering them in a way that respects
the topology or the connectivity of that
graph so we're going to conclude with
one final problem
uh which i don't have a slide on but
that's okay and that's
cycle detection so there's a bit of a an
exercise
left to the reader here so the problem
that we're looking for now
is that we're given a directed graph
there's a g in graph case you're
wondering
but now we don't know if it's a dag or
not and so the question that we're
trying to ask
is does there exist
a cycle in our directed acyclic graph
right so we're just given our graph and
we want to know like can we do this
let's think through the logic of this a
bit so what do we know we know that
if our graph were a dag
then i could call dfs get the ordering
out and then i guess flip it it's
ordering backwards so i could compute
uh the reverse finishing order and it
would give me a topological order of my
graph
right so if i were a dag i would get a
topological order when i called dfs
so let's say that i ran dfs
i got whatever ordering i got and now i
found an edge that points in the wrong
direction i i can i can just double
check my list of edges and i find one
uh that does not respect the
relationship that i see in the second
bullet point here
can my graph be a dag no because if my
graph were a dag
the algorithm would have worked i just
proved it to you right so if if there
were if my
my graph were a tag then i could do a
reverse finishing order and what i would
get back
is a topological order so if i found a
certificate that my order wasn't
topological
something went wrong and the only thing
that could go wrong is that my graph is
in a dag
or yeah it's in a deck in fact uh
sort of an exercise left to the reader
and or to your section do we still have
section i think we do as of now um is
that this is an if and only if
meaning that the only time that you even
have a topological ordering in your
graph
is if your graph is a dac this is a
really easy fact to sanity check by the
way so it's not not like a particularly
challenging problem but you should
think through it because it's a good
exercise to make sure you understand the
definitions
which is to say that if you have a
topological order your graph is a dag
if you don't have a topological order
your graph isn't a dag so in other words
we secretly gave you an algorithm
for checking if a graph is a dag at all
right what could i do
i could compute reverse finishing order
check
if it obeys the relationship on the
second bullet point here for every edge
and if it does then we're in good shape
my graph is a tag
if it doesn't something went wrong and
the only thing that could have gone
wrong is not being a dag
okay so in other words uh secretly we
just solved
well i guess the way that i've written
it here we've solved the cycle detection
problem here which is to say that well i
have a cycle
if and only if i don't i'm not a dag
which i can check using this technique
of course the word detection here
probably means that i actually want to
find that cycle and i haven't told you
how to do that yet
right all we know how to do so far is
say like yeah somewhere in this graph
there's a cycle and that's not so good
um so we can do one additional piece of
information in the two minutes we have
remaining
to sort of complete our story here which
is to modify our algorithm ever so
slightly
to not only say like thumbs up thumbs
down is there a cycle in this graph
but also to actually return the vertices
as a cycle
and here's the the property that we're
gonna do that which is uh
the following which is that if g
contains a cycle
uh
right then a full
dfs will traverse
an edge from a vertex v
to some ancestor v
i guess we haven't carefully defined the
the term ancestor here
essentially uh if you think of the sort
of
the running of of the dfs algorithm then
an ancestor is like something that
appears in the recursive call tree
before i got to v okay so how could we
prove that
well
let's take a cycle
um and we'll give it a name in
particular we'll say that it's
a cycle from v0 v1
to vk and then it's a cycle so it goes
back to v0
okay and i can order this cycle any way
i want notice that if i permute
the vertices in this list in a cyclical
way meaning that i like take the last
few of them and stick them at the
beginning of the list
it's still a cycle it's the nice thing
about cycles uh so in particular
without loss of generality
we're going to assume uh
that v zero is the first vertex
uh visited by by by dfs
what does that mean that means like when
i do my dfs algorithm making all these
recursive calls
the very first vertex to be touched by
this technique is v naught
okay well now what's going to end up
happening
well think about the recursive call tree
starting at v
zero by the time that completes
anything that's reachable from v zero is
also going to be complete do you see
that
so like for instance v zero somewhere in
his call tree might call v one if it
and notice that v one was not already
visited so in fact it will
for v1 i got to call v2 and so on
and in particular we're going to get all
the way
to vertex k right
so in other words
we're going to visit vertex v
k and notice what's going to happen
so remember our algorithm in fact we
should probably just put it up on the
screen would be easier
than talking about it a bunch well
v k is now going to iterate over every
one of the neighbors of v
k and in particular it's going to see
vertex v naught
right so we're going to see
the edge from vk to v0
which is an edge kind of by definition
right because we took this to be a cycle
here
well notice that's exactly the thing we
set out to prove right namely that full
dfs
traverses an edge from a vertex to one
of its ancestors
here's the vertex k here's his ancestor
v naught why do we know that it's an
ancestor well because v naught
was called in our call tree before any
of these other guys
right so we wanted an algorithm that not
only did cycle detection but also
actually gave me this cycle
what could i do well it's essentially a
small modification
of what we already have right so whoops
uh right if i want to compute
topological order or whatever i can just
do dfs
and that'll tell me like year nay does
their existing cycle if i want to
actually find that cycle all i have to
do is sort of
check that topological order property at
the same time that i traverse the graph
during dfs and the second that i find an
edge that loops back
i'm done and so that's our basic
algorithm here
and this is a technique for actually
defining the cycle in a graph using the
dfs algorithm