[SQUEAK]
[SCRATCH]
[CLICK]
JASON KU: Welcome to our
fourth problem session.   Today
we will mostly talk about
binary trees.
We're going to talk a little bit
about binary heaps, it's a
topic we won't
cover until next Tuesday,
but it will appear in
very small ways
in your Problem Set 4, which is due
next Friday.
So I'm going to
look into this material a little bit today.
But it's mostly a concern -- the
subject matter
today is mostly binary trees,
specifically, which are used
for set data structures
and sequence data structures,
as Professor Demain talked
to you about earlier this week.
But by now-- actually,
as of yesterday--
you've seen all the
data structures that we're
going to cover--
that implement the
set interface and the
sequence interface.
Those beautiful tables that
Professor Demain showed you are
now ready.
We have some
data structures that are
really good - constant-time operations
for some operations.
Therefore, we can use them
for some applications.
And this week we've
been describing to
you trees that
achieve, really, pretty
good results for any kind of
query operation on my sets
or sequences --
pretty good, meaning logarithmic
time, not exactly constant.
But for our purposes, log n -
I mean, on your
computer, practically--
not asymptotically,
but practically-- log
n will be no more than
on your computer?
Something like 64, right?
Any input data you work with
, in machine terms,
is your input data.
You have to be able to
address all those machine
words in your input.
And on your computer, the
machine word address size
is 64 bits, right?
And we assume that the
word size is at least the
logarithmic size of your input
so that you can address the input.
So for your purposes,
on your computer,
log n
will be no more than 64,
which means you'll get
maybe a 50x overlap,
or for smaller cases
it could be more than 10
if you have 1000 things
you're working on.
Not so bad, right?
This is a constant - it's not a
constant factor for theoretical
purposes, but for your purposes
log n is much better than a
polynomial factor -
another factor of n.
You've seen all the code.
You've seen implementations of
all those set and sequence interfaces
, right?
So I went ahead and
wrote a little bit...
I put all this code together
from your recitation notes,
all the different
interface implementations.
I
wrote a small test program
to see how they work
on a real machine.
I have a small test code.
I have a small folder that
lists an array that implements
a sequence, a binary
tree that implements
a sequence, a dynamic
array that implements...
all of these things.
Then set things up-- a sorted array, which
is a set in a binary tree,
and a hash table.
These are our implementations.
I don't use
Python dictionaries for hash tables,
I use the implementations
that are in your presentation.
And I'm going to
run this little
Python code efficiency test
that will basically just
fire everyone.
It will perform a series of
these different operations
and measure to see
how long it took.
I'm just recording
This is not an asymptotic
analysis, but hopefully we
see some separation.
So when you click this,
it runs a bunch of tests.
Let's take a look.
good.
I have a bunch of
consecutive operations.
We have build, set_at,
get-at, insert, delete
in different places.
And these are actual
timings at a certain scale --
at a certain resolution that I had
for these data structures.
And you see that assembly--
actually, assembly,
on this machine,
just allocating some
array and cleaning it up,
is a really efficient thing that
Python is going to do for me.
And actually... this is a
misnomer for log n.
But these other things,
get_at and set_at-- they're
really, really fast, right?
This is constant time.
And then these other
things, I basically
can't do any better than
scroll through it,
so it takes linear time.
And again the sequence,
setting_at and getting_at is
slow, but by deleting and
removing from the first one,
I'm just rebinding
the pointer, right?
Dynamic arrays.
Again, set_at, get_at are
fast because they are
regular arrays.
And then inserting
and removing the last one,
it's
essentially constant time.
Now I actually... when I
run these tests to deal
with averages, I
actually run
these things, many times,
and test their performance.
And so I don't see the
worst case scenario, do I?
I average all the
things, which is
exactly what
depreciation means.
That's why I get
good results here.
Hash table.
Again, really...
oh, this is what
we talked about
in
last week's problem session, implementing a
kind of two-way queue
with a hash table.
Here is the implementation.
I just wanted to show it to you.
But it's actually very good.
This is what JavaScript
uses for arrays.
And then a binary sequence
represented as a binary tree - a
balanced binary tree.
This is our AVL code that I had.
And all the other things
were really bad
in insert_at and
delete_at, but this one
works comparably to all the
other things.
Now you see that this is
a little more machine
cycles than other things,
but it's really not that bad.
And then,
again, we had a sorted array.
Sorry, this is a
set from an array.
Essentially, it is an
unsorted array.
I'm just looking for all
this - these are really bad times.  A
sorted array makes these
operations great,
but insertion and
deletion are bad.
This is why we need binary trees.
Hash tables get good dictionary
operations but very
poor order operations.
And then the binary
search tree, the tuned binary tree, again,
does
all of these things pretty well.
In fact, it gets
really quite good - somehow it
gets better
than even a sorted array.
I don't know why.
Our implementations are
not optimized at all.
But it's pretty
good asymptotically.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Can
you explain again
why the first
data vault [INAUDIBLE] registers n?
JASON KU: It's just
marked based on time.
It so happens that
there is probably an internal C under Python
that allocates this thing,
and therefore does it very quickly.
My program, which
looks at these numbers
and tries to guess what the
asymptotic running time is,
is just labels based
on these things, ranges.
I just... it's mischaracterized.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes.
Well, I mean, actually,
if this was C code--
if all of this stuff
was in C, maybe
we would see that this strip would be
longer because it actually has to
go through and
touch all of this memory.
It's still being done here,
but all things Python are
extremely terrible.
It's about 100 times slower
than anything C does.
And you see
that discrepancy.  Does
this make sense?
good.
I just wanted to show you this.
We could have released this for
you to play,
but we just wanted to give
you a taste.
Okay, any questions
before we continue?
How do I turn this off?
Up and away.
Turn off.
so
good.
Let's move on to the problems -
let's solve some problems.
You have a set of
problems here.
First, we
will consider an AVL sequence tree.
This is an AVL sequence tree.
How do I know this?
You don't have to.
But these things are
definitely not
in the order of what
I store in them, right?
So it's better not
to be a tuned AVL tree.
Is this an AVL tree?  Is
this balanced--
balanced in height?
Yes, basically.
In fact, if you calculate
the size of each subtree, the
left and right subtrees
on all of these (you
can verify for
yourself) are balanced.
They are within plus or
minus 1 of each other.
In fact, this is
so far from the balance
you could get
for this many nodes while
maintaining
height balance--
while maintaining the
AVL property-- that
it's an instructive example.
It's like being on the edge.
And what will I do?
What is missing from this
image if I claim that
it is a sequential AVL tree?
Any ideas what's missing?
What does the
AVL sequence tree store that I don't
show in this image?
AUDIENCE: Counts.
JASON KU: What?
JASON KU: It counts.
and?
This is a sequential AVL tree.
Height, right?
A sequence of AVL trees,
different from the established AVL trees,
is complemented by
two things, right?
Because I need to
maintain balance while
spinning, so I
need to maintain altitude.
I need to be able to determine
the height of these subtrees
in constant time
as I climb the
tree, fixing things.
And consistency requires me
to store their subtree numbers
there.
I don't know... I
won't draw it
for all these things, but
what about number four?
What is its height?
1, 2, 3.
This is the longest path from the
root subtree.
So this is height equal to 3.
This came from height equal to
2, and height equal to 1. Does
everyone see that?
Yes?
And then the size
here, how big is it?
This is 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
This is... I'm going to
put a size here that's 7.
And this comes from
this guy, 1, 2, 3, 4.
And this guy is 2.
So how do I calculate
the size of the subtree?
This is the size of my left subtree plus the
size of my right subtree plus 1.
And my height takes the
maximum value of 2 plus 1.
Okay.
So, we did all of this yesterday.
I'm just marking these things.
I am asking you
to perform a delete operation.
This is a sequence tree.
So I find things by
their index in the tree.
So I'm going to ask you
to remove the eighth thing
in my sequence.
What is the 8th
in my sequence?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: To clarify,
because delete-8 is not a deletion of
a number.
JASON KU: That's right.
Well, delete_at 8. Do
you see that?
This is a sequential operation.
AUDIENCE: Oh, okay.
[INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes.
Therefore, it is very
important
to distinguish between
sequence and set semantics.
If I'm dealing
with a sequence,
I'd rather not
look for internal things
in that data structure, because
it's not an internal
data structure.
This does not support this.
If I wanted to support searching for,
say, key index 8
or something like that,
then all I could do
is look like an array.
I would just need to scroll through the
entire sequence
and tell me if there
is a thing in it.
It's impossible to do better
than linear time.
This data structure is
not designed for this.
What is it for?
It is designed to search for things
by their index in a sequence.
So how do I find the 8th index?
Well, I mean, I
look at the tree
and I can just count
along the circuit in order.
What is a walkthrough in order?
0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Okay, found 8.
But what
does a sequential AVL tree do?
I'm storing
the dimensions of the subtree, and when I'm here,
I don't know what index I have.
How can I find out what
my index is from the root?
I look at my left subtree, I
see how many there are.  There
are seven things here.
1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.
Yes.
Because I'm looking for the
9th item at index 8.
That means
I'm the 8th item.
I'm a guy with the index number 7. Does
that make sense?
Because I'm looking at the
size of the subtree.
So what do I know?
I know the index I'm
looking for is to my right.
I come in here
and I happen to know...
what index am I
looking for in this subtree?
0, right?
I want the first one
in the subtree.   Now
my search index has changed
, because I have actually dealt
with all eight of these points.
Here I am looking for the
0th thing in my index.
I look to the left—
if I didn't have a left subtree,
I would be zero,
and I would turn myself around.
But there is something here.
So I'm looking for the 0th thing here
, which is just him,
and I'm returning it.
And actually,
I'm deleting it.
So I'm deleting it.
What's the problem here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: The height is unbalanced.
What is unbalanced in height here?
AUDIENCE: Left subtree -
or, sorry.
[INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: This guy doesn't have a
balanced growth, does he?
AUDIENCE: --right subtree of
right [INAUDIBLE].
JASON KU: This guy's subtree is
not balanced in height, right?
This guy 2.
This guy 1.
So how do we fix this?
AUDIENCE: Turn around.
JASON KU: We do a few rotations.
This is actually a
bad case, the
third bad case
we talked about yesterday.
If I tried to just
turn this guy to the left,
what would it look like?
This will be 12.
This will be 10.
And 8 will be added to that.
Now the height is misbalanced
in the other direction, right?
This is bad.
So how do I solve
this case where
I'm heavily skewed
to the right, but my right subtree is
skewed to the left, I
have to do a rotation here,
a rotation to the right, and
then do a rotation.
This is a formula.
Here we first do
a right rotation
of 10, which gives me something
like 8, 10.
Now, obviously, this is not
better than what was before,
but it was an intermediate
step so that we could fix it.
We turn right here, and
then we turn left here.
By default, we
rotate to the left here,
but since this has a
skew in the wrong direction,
I need to rotate this to the right first,
and then we can do that.
Now I rotate
all these guys
and put 12
here, 8 here, 10 here.  Does
everyone see what the
rotation looks like?
good.   It will
take you some time to understand
what
transformation is, but
hopefully you
have all followed this transformation.
There was a bit of magic
when I tried to draw.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: I still don't
feel like this tree is
balanced in height.
JASON KU: That's not true.
Good observation.
why is that?
This thing still has a height of 3.
What is the height of
this thing?
1, right?
This is height 1.
And actually when I
did this rotation,
I needed to update all of
these extensions.
What extensions did
I really need--
what subtrees
changed during these things?
I don't remember what
this thing looked like.
What did the thing look like?
10 had 8 in its subtree, so
its subtree definitely changed.
Subtree 8 has been modified.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: 12 hasn't changed--
after all.
AUDIENCE: It's
10 and 8 [INAUDIBLE].
JASON KU: Okay.
So, there is a case analysis
that is in your lecture notes
and was done during the recitation.
This tells you that
these subtrees A, B, C, D
,
the ones that can
change in these things,
these subtrees don't change.
The only subtree that
has changed during one
of these patch operations, when
you do one or two rotations,
are either the two nodes
or the three nodes
whose subtree has changed.
Here it could be that
three subtrees have changed
.
But in the easy case, only
two nodes-- x and y, I think,
in the notes--
could change.
And so when I do that, I have to
recalculate their expansions
from their expansions of
their children,
but that's just a constant
number,
so I just recalculate them
because the subtrees underneath me
haven't changed.
good.
So we have a
height mismatch here.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes.
So, initially
in the image, 12
has a bunch of things
in its subtree--
10 and 8, and we just removed 7.
So its subtree has
definitely changed.  There
used to be three...
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Oh, no, sorry, that's what it was.  so So
, here three subtrees of nodes have changed
.
But this is actually the biggest thing.
I'll show you the worst case scenario.
Only three nodes
possible in performing
one of these
double rotations
could change
their subtrees.
And so we just have to fix the
increase in these three
things.
In a mild case,
it's just two things.
Okay,
we're unbalanced.
How can we fix this?
I could have been angry.
I want to be able to
rotate right here
to restore balance, I could be
angry and switch these two.
If I were to swap those
two, I would have to
do two rotations
to fix this thing
because the middle one is
heavier than the left one
compared to what I'm doing.
But I'm not that angry, so
I'm going to turn right.
How do I do this?
Well, turning right
by 6
will drop all of
that below 4
and attach that subtree
as the left child of 6.
Does that make sense?
Phew,
this will be fun to draw.
I'll just redraw it.
That makes more sense, doesn't it?
4, 11, 3, 2, 1, and
then 6, 5, 9, 8, 12, 10.
That's the correct rotation for 6. Does
everyone like that?
Rotation - my
x is 6, my y is 4.
I have subtrees A, B, C.
What I'm doing is sort of
switching which of x and y
is the root here.
So now y is the root, and
subtrees B and C become
descendants of x under y.
And note that, hopefully,
my order of operations has
not changed throughout this process.
We had to update our
additions along the way,
but that's a constant
as we climb the tree.
And we only walk the tree a
logarithmic number of times.
Yes?
so
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
So every time we do a
rotation, you just
update the extension
with [INDISPENSABLE]
before we do another rotation?
JASON KU: Exactly.
AUDIENCE: Part two.
Updating
the increase means just
updating the quantity,
height, and just
the properties that remain...
JASON KU: Yes.
Essentially, what we
did was we defined--
when we added--
Professor Demain
defined for you yesterday
what the subtree property is.
This meant a property
that I could calculate just
by looking at my children--
incrementing my
children, recursively.
So, instead of
trying to increment or trying to
think locally what
that increment should be,
I'm going to throw away
my old increment
and just enumerate
it using its children,
because that, recursively,
should be correct.  Does
this make sense?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So, just looking
at how the rotation works.
It's hard for me to
wrap my head around.
So, essentially, you swap
4 and 6, and so
4 becomes the parent node
and 6 becomes the right node.
JASON KU: I'm going to
draw this picture.
It's just something
you have to remember.
This is x, B, C, and A.
See this image?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: What?
JASON KU: Yes.
It's in your notes.
It's not a big deal.
But if you have a
structure like this
where x has a left child,
these subtrees
may or may not be empty.
It doesn't really matter.
What I can do is
go from here to there--
has the same
traversal order,
but has a different shape.
In particular,
the height of the subtree has changed
, which
may help us restore the balance of the tree.
And that's the
whole point of AVL.  Does
this make sense?
AUDIENCE: Is this the
correct rotation?
JASON KU: This...
this is a right rotation.
This is a left rotation.
Any more questions?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: As I
climb the tree,
every node I might have to
fix with a rebalance,
but that rebalance does
at most two rotations,
and there are at most log
n ancestors that I have,
because my tree was
balanced at height 2
log n or something like that.
This means that
at maximum I might
have to do four log n rotations
because each of them can
do two rotations.  Does
this make sense?
Now, in fact, you can prove
that in a deletion operation
, it's possible that you'll have to
do a logarithmic number of
these rotations up the tree.
It was a bad case.  The
original tree I gave you
is called a Fibonacci tree.
This is a few... this is
the largest balanced tree in height that
you can have on a
given number of nodes.
Yes, the smallest number of nodes
for a given height.
You can think about it anyway.
And if you generalize this
to a large enough thing,
then that thing
will need a logarithmic number of
revolutions going up.
Now, actually,
with the insertion
you can actually prove-- you can
go through the case analysis.  The
insert operation
always rebalances the tree
after one rebalancing operation
, which
may include two rotations.  Does
this make sense?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes.
Right spin, this guy
becomes the right kid.
AUDIENCE: Yes.
So, you can't... are there
certain rotations that you
can't do, depending on
whether you've had a child...
JASON KU: Yes.
If I didn't have a left subtree, I would
n't be able to make a
right turn.
Right rotation requires
me to have a left child.
So if you do this –
and you'll see,
our code actually
checks to see if
you have a left child element.
This is a statement
you can
make before
doing one of these rotations.
Something else?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Just
repeating, so it
might take no more than two turns to insert
[INAUDIBLE]??
JASON KU: Mmm.  A
constant number of
revolutions, and removal
may take a logarithmic
number of revolutions.
This is not what
you need to know.
That's not what I'm trying
to prove to you here.
Just something
interesting.
There are
rebalancing schemes, like in CRS.
They introduce red and black
wood to introduce balance.
And these trees actually
have weaker connections –
they are not as
balanced as an AVL tree.
This allows for more than skew 2.
And since this is
supposedly a weaker constraint,
they get away with only doing a
constant number of rotations -
they can afford it
before fixing the tree.
But it's a little more complicated.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Very good.
good.  Do
you have any questions about this?
Okay, now this is more of a
mechanical question that you will
get in your problem sets.
And now we will move on to
theoretical questions in more detail.
These will be
issues of reduction.
good.
This is the first problem, Fik Nouri.
Is this... someone?
Nick Fury, right?
So, this is a reference to the Avengers.
So basically what
happens in this case is
he has a list of
superheroes, each of whom
has their own opinion on whether
they should go to battle with Thanos.
And their opinion can
be strongly positive
or strongly negative.
So what Fick
is trying to do is
find among
his Avengers who are the Avengers with the
most extreme views
so
he can talk to them.
He doesn't want
to talk to everyone.
He wants to talk to a
logarithmic number of them.
good.
It's like-- whatever.
Essentially, we have a
secret situation
where you are given as a
read-only input storage
these things in an array.
And I want to find
magazines with the strongest
opinions.  Does
this make sense?
And I want to do that,
and the first problem
is linear time.
You don't really know
how to do it yet.
You'll know how to do it with the
material you cover in--
well, they'll teach you how
to do it one way in 046,
but we're not going to
do it to you right now.   On Tuesday,
we'll teach you another
way to do this
using binary heaps.
Binary heaps are an
interesting thing.
It implements a subset of the
established interface.
Really, it's simple-- you can
build on some iterated x.
I'm collecting a bunch of things.
These items have keys.   In the same way,
it is a key data structure
.
It implements what we call a
priority queue interface.
I can build these things.
I can insert things, but I'm
not going to do that here.
All I really need
for this situation
is the delete_superlative operation--
in this case, probably max.
Delete_max.
So it's like--
I have a data structure,
I call these things.  Does
this make sense?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: What is
priority queue?
JASON KU: Yes.
Priority queue is
essentially what
implements these two things.
Actually, there's a third one
where I can put something new,
but I wo
n't need it right now.
That's what
priority queue is.
And in fact, a set
is a subset of the
set interface.
right?  The
nice thing about a
heap-- I won't show
you how to do it,
but what a heap can do--
if I were to implement both of these
operations
using a fixed AVL tree, how long would it
take me to do these things?
How long does it take
to build a set of AVL trees?
n log n, right?
Because essentially I
get sorted order
if I
insert these things one at a time
,
or I can sort them
and then put them
into a tree in linear time,
like you saw a couple of days
ago in the recitation.
But I'll have to sort them out someday
, right?
I need to take
at least n log n time,
because if I want to get
their traversal order back
in linear time, and I have a
lower bound of n log
n for sorting, I needed to
spend n log n time here,
right?
And how long
will this delete_max take?
AUDIENCE: This is sorted, so enter n.
JASON KU: Log n, right?
So this is a set of AVL trees.
Where is my maximum?
This is the most correct.
I can just walk over this
thing, take it off.
Maybe I need to rebalance.
But this is a log n operation.
This is the same as
inserting the last one in my subtree.
For a fixed AVL tree,
this is n log n.
This is magazine n.
Now there is another
data structure that performs
one of these operations better.
And the same for the other one
we learned about earlier.  Does
anyone remember?
Fitting an AVL tree
didn't really give us
anything over a sorted
array in a dynamic array.
What this gave us was...
we could sort this in n log n time
using merge sort or something
like that.
And then we could just
pull out the last n times.
It would be amortized...
I mean, if I didn't
care about taking
that size, I could do it, at
worst, constant time.
I just read
the first-- the last one.
I never need to resize the
array.
I can just ignore it.  Does
this make sense?
good.
But that's... okay.
If I had a data structure
that implemented these two
operations, could someone
tell me an algorithm
for creating fixed lists--
don't worry about the
running time right now-- but that
only uses these two operations?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So we create
this data structure.
It is ordered from
smallest to largest
in the direction of the absolute value of x.
JASON KU: Don't worry
about where they
order things or anything like that.
I'm not telling you how these
things are implemented, am I?
I'm just saying that I can
take a bunch of this stuff,
and I can remove the
maximum and bring it back.
good?
AUDIENCE: I think
we just create this--
make sure you create this
so that the thought levels are the
absolute value of the
thought levels, not--
JASON KU: Sure.
good.
So that's a good thing.
What I'm going to do, as
your colleague said,
is I'm going to look at
all the things in my contribution.
I'm going to copy it to
some memory storage for recording.
This read-only thing is
irrelevant to this part of the
problem.  What
I'm going to do is...
right.
sorry
I'm thinking about your
problem set that we're writing.
I'm mixing it up.
Okay, we'll copy it into
our new linear-sized array.
But instead of putting
their values ​​there,
I'm going to put the absolute
values ​​of their values.  Does
this make sense?
I'm just checking to see if it's negative.
If so, I put
positivity there.
good?
Then I insert this
array into this assembly.
I put it there.
This will take some time,
regardless of the creation time.
And then I can
delete at most k times.
Or I can delete the maximum number of
times, however many things
I need.
right?
If I want to register the top n things,
I can just register it n times,
right?
So, if I had a
data structure like this,
I could do it in one
run of this operation
and log n runs of
this operation.  Does
this make sense?
I could solve this
problem by reducing
this data structure.
Now, for a sorted array
or a fitted AVL tree,
this operation is
already killing me.
This takes n log n time.
The nice thing
about the binary heap
is that it performs this
operation in linear time.
You'll see it on Tuesday.
And it performs this
operation in log n time.
What is the running time
if I use a binary heap
to implement this
data structure?
Order n times order
log n times log n.
How big is log n squared--
log n squared-- compared to n?
It's smaller, right?
So if I add these two
running times together,
it will still be linear.
This is how you solve the
first problem.
I didn't need to tell you
what a binary heap is
or how it does what it does.
All I needed to
tell you was that
this operation was performed
in linear time
and this
operation was performed in log time n.
Okay,
the magic will be shown to
you on Tuesday.
Part B says: now suppose that
Fick's computer
is only allowed to write into
log n space.
Well, okay.
Here is the problem.
Because before we copied the
entire array,
filtered it, and
then performed some operations.
But we couldn't even afford to do
that if we
couldn't store it all
externally in writable memory.
Therefore, we cannot do this.
So in a way it's a
more restrictive environment.
I can do fewer things.
It is less powerful than my
previous situation where
I had as much space
as I wanted to use.
So it makes some
sense that I may
not have been able to limit the working hours
that we had before.
I may have to
sacrifice something
because I am in more limited
computing conditions.
Now this is something you
can solve with binary heaps,
but it's not necessary.
You can solve this
using a set of AVL trees.  Does
anyone have any ideas
on how this can be solved
using a fixed AVL tree?
I'm limited by my number--
my space is at most log n.
AUDIENCE: So how much space
does a set of AVL trees take up?
JASON KU: That's right.
Space - there is a constant
number of pointers
to each of these nodes.
And I keep it in
notes and space.
Essentially, every data structure
we've shown you takes up space -
the order of things
we store.
This does not use any additional space.
It may take longer
to do certain things,
but the space is taken up by
the number of items
we store plus
perhaps a constant factor.
So I'm going to draw my contribution here
, which I can only read, but I
can't write.
Do I give it to you...
I'll just call
it A. So that's my list of
all the Revenger thoughts.
I can only read.
But my computer can only write
to this logarithmic amount of
space.
What can I put in this space?
AUDIENCE: Magazine [INAUDIBLE]?
JASON KU: Well, I can definitely
put log n things in there.
So, if I'm given
this constraint,
I'll probably want to create a
data structure of that size,
holding that
many things.  Does
this make sense?
Because what
else are you going to do?
So I gave you an idea.
Maybe we could use an
AVL set here.
I see the logarithm in my answer.
It's possible that we
sorted arrays
or set AVL things.
These things give me a journal
somewhere in my work time,
right?
How logical
that I could
have a set of AVL trees here.
Why might a fitted AVL tree
be useful to me?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Since
it's sorted and you
don't have a
passing order,
can you calculate the passing order
and insert [INAUDIBLE]??
JASON KU: Of course.
I can do all of this.
But, specifically,
this will help
me
find a big one quickly, right?
If I have a set of
things, it's going to be...
and I store
this data structure,
by adding
elements to it,
I can find out which one is the
largest--
or the smallest--
pretty quickly in log n time.
So if I have
n things in this tree here,
what is the height of this thing?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Journal of the magazine n.
This looks familiar.
So what can I afford?
I can afford a linear number of
AVL tree option operations
over this data structure.
Okay, did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Okay, sorry.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: For this to
be an AVL tree,
does it have to be a BTS tree?
JASON KU: Uh, BTS...
BST.
So when I talk about...
someone likes Korean K-Pop.
good.
So, BST-- but naturally-- in the
jargon
that you're probably
used to hearing
in other contexts,
what we mean in this
class is an AVL tree.
Sometimes what
people call a
binary search tree doesn't
have balance semantics,
so what we can call in
this class is a binary set tree.
But they are actually beneficial
because they are balanced.
So we will
usually just assume
that we are talking about
balanced things here.
Now the AVL tree set has this
semantics of a binary search tree
where the keys are ordered.
These items have keys
and they are ordered.
This is the installed interface.
Whereas we also introduced
you to the serial
interface, for which these
things don't even have keys.
How can I store the set semantics
there?
So that's the
distinction we
mean when we talk about a binary
search tree versus, actually, a set of
AVL trees versus [INAUDIBLE].
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So if we look at this
to create an AVL tree from this, would that
mean that when
we create a node, we're telling it that
we're putting in an absolute
value of [INAUDIBLE]??
JASON KU: Okay, when you
create a set of AVL trees,
you have to tell us what--
if you're storing objects,
you have to tell
me what their key is.
You just keep
some numbers
like I'm doing here.
Now this is not an installed AVL tree.
But if I'm just
storing numbers, I
have to tell you that the elements
I'm storing are keys.
And then everything follows.
But if you have an
object that you're
trying to sort, like the
students in this room,
you have a lot of properties.
I want all people to
have a phone number--
maybe I want to
include your phone number for some reason.  Will
this help me
find out where you live?
I don't... it's
getting a little...
I don't want to go there.
But if I give you a
set of AVL trees,
I have to tell you
what it is tuned to.
If I give you a
sequential AVL tree, it
will be obvious what
my traversal order will be,
since
I am giving you the sequence.
This is what the entrance was like.  Does
this make sense?
Okay, I have a
set of AVL trees of size log n.
What should be the key to it?
AUDIENCE: Absolute value.
JASON KU: The absolute
value of their preferences--
or their opinion.
I don't remember what
it's called.
But what kind of magazine items
can I put here?  I don't
know.
I don't know anything
about these things.
What makes one
better than the other?
Let's just put the
first log of n things.  Does
this make sense?
Okay,
what can this tell me?
Now I put this thing there.
How long did it last?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Register n times,
register, register n times, right?
But it's much less
than our long-term time
that we're looking for,
so I'm not concerned.
I mean, I want you to
say how long it took,
but for my purposes
I know it's
less than the amount of time
I'm looking for.
And I did such an operation once.
I do
n't care about that anymore.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: How did you get
log n by multiplying log log n?
JASON KU: Because
the number of things
I store in this
thing is log n.
So if I match the pattern to the
AVL tree creation time
and put log n in there,
then it's going to be log n times log n.
good.
AUDIENCE: So this is
just one iteration?
JASON KU: Well, right now,
I just created this thing.
Maybe... I just built it once.
I also argue that maybe
I don't need to build it again.
What could I...
as far as I know...
I didn't filter
my data at all.
I just keep these things
in a certain order.
What can I do to
maybe start processing
the rest of the data?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] try to
scroll through the A list
and try to find someone who is
bigger than...
try to keep
the maximum [INAUDIBLE].
JASON KU: Take this guy
through putting things in,
and always supporting...
if I do this, and I
keep sticking things in,
I'll get this at the
end.
And now I can just read the
largest k things.
However, when I insert
things here,
my thing grows.
AUDIENCE: Okay, just
delete the smallest one.
JASON KU: Oh,
remove the small stuff.
I like this idea.
AUDIENCE: So
replace it.
JASON KU: Yeah,
basically replace it.
right.
What I'm going to do--
here's a suggestion.
We're going to take the
next guy, put him in.
Perfectly.
Which one do
I care about right now?
The smallest one there.
So drive out the smallest.
Now this one
I got stuck in May.
Be the smallest.
So I just went
through it,
but how long did it take me?
This took me by
the height of this tree.
What is the height of this tree?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Journal of the magazine n.
So I put one down and took the
other out.
This is the smallest, right?
And I will continue to do so
until the end.
How long did it take me?
JASON KU: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes.
Processing n minus log n
elements, which is basically equal to n.
And each of these
operations took me as much
time as a tree.
This gives me the
running time we're
looking for, n log log n.
sense?
AUDIENCE: Does this resemble the
sliding window technique?
JASON KU: Yes.
This is a kind of
sliding window technique.
Maybe you've
used it recently.
good.  Does
everyone agree with this?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Could you just
remind me of the context
we're talking about, which is log
log n, like a tree and where...
JASON KU: So this thing...
the size of this thing is
log log n?
AUDIENCE: Yes.
JASON KU: I mean... sorry, magazine n.
And the height of this
thing is the size of a log.
AUDIENCE: I'm sorry, as far as
our small logs of size n
[INAUDIBLE] small
logs of logs of n trees, or...
JASON KU: No, yeah... sorry.
I'm taking this stuff-- there's
no intermediate
data structure here--
I'm just putting all
this stuff into an AVL set.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Into one
AVL set of size log n.
I put in a guy, I
put forward the worst guy.
Looking through all the things.
I need to make sure that
when I insert it,
I keep track of
which Revenger it is,
and that I take the
absolute value,
and all those
little things.
But that's the basic idea.
I just take it, I
close the window, I
put something in, I
take something out,
which may or may
not be the same.
And at the end of
this procedure, the
invariant that I
keep here is that
my thing always has the
k largest thoughts of the ones
I've processed so far.
This is obviously true
in the beginning
when I'm building this thing.
And when I get to the end, I've
processed all the stuff,
and it has a log of size n,
so I have a log of the biggest-- the
highest-- extremist thoughts.
And then I can just do a
detour of
this thing in order and come back.  Does
this make sense?
And I only used
logarithmic space.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Wait, I don't understand.
Are all the thoughts
in this AVL tree?
JASON KU: Are all
the thoughts in this AVL tree?
All these thoughts
are in the AVL tree.
And at some point I
will insert each thought
into this AVL tree.
But I will delete
the ones I don't care about as I go along
.  Does
this make sense?
I always maintain the
invariants
that this thing, before
inserting anything,
contains exactly log n elements
, and then I
maintain this invariant
by inserting one, removing one
.
AUDIENCE: Oh, okay,
which one do you delete?
JASON KU: Always the
minimum because I
want the biggest.
AUDIENCE: And the min of
absolute value.
JASON KU: Yes.
I am guided by the absolute
value of these thoughts.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
JASON KU: Total working hours here?
This is accounting.  It
took me log n
times log log n time
to create this
data structure in the beginning,
plus n times log log n.
I did, essentially, n operations--
asymptotically n operations.
So it's actually
n minus log n operations.
And each of these
tree operations --
doing one insertion, one deletion --
each of them took up
the height of the tree's time.
And that's it.
good?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: If instead of one
we just insert and delete,
you can do a comparison and then...
JASON KU:
Inserting and deleting an
AVL tree
actually performs a comparison
in its data structures.
AUDIENCE: Just
compare with min.
And then...
JASON KU: Sure,
you could do that.
I could have done it differently.
I could remove
the smallest element here,
for starters, right?
And then I compare
it to this guy,
and then whichever is
bigger, I put it back in.
The same.
Just do I do
the delete first and then the insert,
or do I do
the insert first and then the delete?
Any more questions?  There are
many questions.
Okay
, well, I guess I'll have to
skip the problem.
We're going to move to CS--
no, SCLR.
What is the link here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JASON KU: Yes, CLRS.
These are four academics
who wrote a popular
computer science textbook.
This is the same type of
k.
They found first editions and
want to sell them at auction.
People can go
to their website.
They have a bidder ID.
This is a unique identifier.
And they can bet
on one of these books.
And they can change that
during the bidding period,
but at the end of the
bidding period,
academics want
to know who--
what is the expected
revenue I will
get by selling k to the
highest bidder?  Does
this make sense?
Yes?
good.
Note that before creating
this data structure,
I know what k is.
k is a fixed thing.
Since my run time of this
get-revenue depends on this k,
it is not an input
for this operation.
So k is like I don't
know what it is, a priori.
It could be n to the power of 2.
It could be log n.
It could be 1.
But the data structure
I create must
satisfy these
runtime properties,
no matter what choice of k the
scientists told me.  Does
this make sense?
What I need to do is that
over time
people place new bids
and update their bids.
And these updates
can take log n time.
But as soon as I
close the window,
I want to be able to determine
in constant time what the k
highest bids are.
Any ideas on how to do this?
What surgeries
should I have?
I have the opportunity
to make a new bet.  Associated
with the bidder is
an idea and a bid,
which is also a whole number—
how many dollars am I going to
pay for this book.
Update your bid.
In a sense, I need to find out
if this person has placed a
bet before, in
my data structure.
So at some point I will
need to find the bidder ID.  Does
this seem possible?
So I could have
some kind of dictionary of
bidder IDs.
When I say I want to have a
dictionary about something,
right, I'm
not yet telling you
how I'm going to
implement that dictionary.
What are my usual options?
Hash table.
But what if I need
time in the worst case scenario?  A
set of AVL trees, right?
This would be your
choice for the dictionary
because it would give
me time to look things up
using the key.
That's the only thing--
well, besides sorted--
you can also use a
sorted array,
but it
won't be dynamic.
And here we are constantly updating
who is in my data structure
.
People come in
and place bets -
new people place bets.
Therefore, my set of things
that interest me is
constantly changing.
So this will probably
steer me away
from sorted arrays
as they are not
suitable for dynamic operations.
So I would need
some kind of dictionary of bidder IDs,
but I would also need to
maintain the sum of the k
highest bidders.  Does
this make sense?
And so, in a
sense, I need to
keep track of an ordered notion of
bidders, the bids that
are in my data structure.  Does
this make sense?
So the order
in the bets will be important.
I will need to
review the bidder ID.
And that's about it, isn't it?
good.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Just checking.
So, if something
is executed at the worst possible time, it
is executed as expected [INDISPENSABLE].
JASON KU: Yes.
Right.
yes
This is a very good observation.
If it runs at the worst possible
time, it also
runs at the expected time, right?
Because there is essentially
no randomization here, which is what
I'm talking about.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
JASON KU: Yes.
So,
we want you to point out the stronger point,
which is that there is actually
no randomization here.
We don't use a hash table.
In this class, this is really the
only situation where
this would be a problem.
But if it's the case that this problem
says for every [INAUDIBLE],
regardless of whether your running time is
worst-case expected and/or
amortized, we're really
trying to get you to say
that it's...
estimate the
running time of your algorithm
with proper qualification.
If this was the worst
case scenario, I want you to
say it was the worst case scenario.
If it was needed... if you
used a hash table,
I want you to say expected.
And if these operations
were sometimes really bad,
but on average they're really
good-- if I did a lot of them,
it amortizes.
Or if I reduced
the use of the dynamic array,
or if I reduced
the use of the hash table,
those dynamic operations would
still be amortized.
good.
Dynamic.
The nice thing about
linked data structures
is that dynamic operations are
not amortized.
So we
can get one.
Now for this problem we can
actually get the worst case bounds,
so we'll try to do that.
You can also do this in an expected way
by using some hash tables
for this dictionary.
When you approach the problem of
data structures
in this class,
you want to first tell me
what exactly you are
storing.
Tell me what
these things should have--
some invariants in
this data structure
to make sure that when
I query later,
these things are
taken care of,
so that if I'm storing a
sorted array,
and I'm supporting
an operation to find the maximum,
I'm better off...
everything I do with
this data structure
should support
invariants that
these things
are in sorted order,
and the last thing
has the maximum element.
Because my maximum return thing
will be
to look there and return that.  Does
this make sense?
So you want to tell me
what is stored
at a common point in
time during your
data structure that is
stored
so that when I support a
dynamic operation or a query,
in the dynamic operation
I insert and coming out
of that, I
need to make sure that I
preserve those invariants.
And when I ask,
I can
rely on these invariants
to answer my query.  Does
this make sense?
So for this
problem-- it's 4-3.
Any ideas?
I have two types of keys that
I may have to deal with.
One is the bid ID and
the other is the bid, right?
So how can I, if I have two
keys that I might
want to order on one
and search on the other,
how many data structures do
you think I'm going to use?
AUDIENCE: Two.
JASON KU: Two.
That's a pretty good guess.
So one of them...
let's just guess, shall we?
I need to be able to
search for bids,
so let's store these bidders
in some kind of dictionary
that can
quickly look up these things.
So, two data structures.
One of them is a dictionary
with a bidder identifier.
What more do I want?
What's there?
On the contrary, a
dictionary stored at the rates?  Do
I want a dictionary here?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
set up an AVL tree [INAUDIBLE]??
JASON KU: I want to
maintain order somehow.
Because I want to
preserve the greatest thing
I've seen so far.
Right now, if I have...
at some point in time,
what will happen?
If I keep k the
largest at any given time,
it is possible that
one of these participants
lowers their bid so that
it is no longer the highest.
I'll also need to keep
an eye on the other guys
to see, for example, who I should bring back
to this set.
Here's an idea.
I'm going to save not just one
data structure, but two
other data structures.
Maybe it's a leap.
You shouldn't do this.
There is a way to do this
with just one other person.
But I'm going to keep two more.
One of them is a
data structure for
storing participants with a -
storing the k participants with the highest bid
and a data structure
for storing n minus
k participants with the highest bid.  Does
this make sense?
That pretty much sums up my problem
, doesn't it?
Every time someone
interacts with this
data structure, I can
check if it's
bigger than the
smallest thing here.
If that's the case, I can do the
same trick I did before.
I can take it off and put my
new one in there.
And here we go...
but I deleted it.
I have to maintain
this property.
So I'm inserting it here.
There is another case.
What other case?
He is smaller.
In this case, I'm
not doing anything
with this data structure, I'm
just inserting it here.  Does
this make sense?
What operations should
these data structures support
?
Finding the minimum or
maximum of these two sets.  Does
this make sense?
Actually, really, where are
those operations?
I don't have them anymore.
But these were the
first priority operations in the queue.
They had delete_max--
and also insert--
these are things he did well.
So any
priority queue, anything that
can deal with maximum
and minimum values, is fine.
And what
data structure do you know that
can handle maxima
and minima quite efficiently?
AVL set, right?
So instead of a
data structure here I will
say, set up AVL.
And, obviously, it
will be received with enthusiasm.
Because that's what
I want to find
the maximum and minimum values.
Everyone follows
the logic,
why do I keep
these things?
This is the level of
invariance
that I want to maintain
because when I,
for example, do this
get-revenue query,
I can just run through and
summarize all of these things.
Oh, wait.
How much time do I have?   Do
I have k time?
No, I don't have time.
So I don't... I can't afford to
summarize all these things
at the end of my topic.
I must return it to
you in a constant time.
Any ideas?
Yes, just calculate--
update the amount.
Along with this
data structure, I'm
going to store a
fourth thing, which
is just the total number of their bets.
I'm going to call it t.
And that's what
I support.
This is part of my data structure.
You can think of it
as me adding a
number to it.
And the point of increasing
this thing by a number
is that I can just--
if I need to know what the
total amount of this stuff is,
I can just look at this number.  Does
this make sense?
Okay
, so I think
we're almost done.
We're basically done, right?
How do we do this?
Someone tell
me how I can generate revenue
with this data structure.
I basically told you.
Look at this number.
Turn it over.
Because it's an invariant
that I've stored in my
data structure.
I rely on this invariant.
Now I better
make sure it's good
when I do dynamic operations.
I make sure to support him.
But if I use induction to guarantee
that all of this is good,
and when I perform a dynamic
operation, all of this is
preserved,
then I'm fine.
So it's very easy to get an income after I do all this
extra work.
I just look at that
number and turn around.
When we grade a
data structures problem,
we usually award you a few points,
first for setting up your
data structure, separate
from the operations,
then we give you
points for the operation
you successfully
completed, and then
a few points for correctness
and running time.
Yes, did you have a question?
AUDIENCE: So the
total is the thing
that we update
every time we mess
with the tree of the highest-bidding participants
and then the tree of the participants with n minus k?
JASON KU: Sorry, could you
repeat that?
AUDIENCE: Do we view
the total as an increment
that we update
every time we do something?
JASON KU: Yes.  so So
, it's just one number.
It's not actually a
data structure,
it's just one number that
I store in my database.
good
How do I implement a
new bidding operation?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
Can we assume that the
rates will also be unique?
JASON KU: Can you suggest
that the rates might be unique?
No.
This is actually a
very useful observation.
We talked about a
set of data structures
that require unique keys.
How can I work with
non-unique keys?
In fact,
it turns out that it is very important for a hash table
that these are unique keys.
Because I need to check
if it's there.
I am looking for that one key.
When I find it,
I must return.
If I had multiple
items with this key,
I might not get the one I'm
looking for back.  It
doesn't even make sense.
But you can generalize the
set infrastructure
to work with multiple sets.
How can I do this?
Well, with each key--
again, I store unique keys.
With each key, I can associate it
with a set of sequence structures
or any other data structure.
And what I'm going to do,
I'm going to do... anything
that has that key,
I'm going to put it
into this data structure.
So instead of storing
one item there,
I have the ability to
store many things there.
Now I have to change the
semantics here.
If I say, find on this
key, well, now, I could say,
I'm going to return all the
things with this key,
or I'm going to keep
some things with this key.
But you understand.
All I need to do is map this
to another data structure
to support [INAUDIBLE].
Maybe I need all the
things with this key.
I want to find the one
who has this key.
So maybe I'm referring to a
set of data structures
that can look up
other things, right?
But the idea is that
we maintain
this key property of uniqueness.
I need to loosen my
semantics so that I
store multiple things
in this key location.  Does
this make sense?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Why does it
matter whether a
set of AVL trees has unique keys or not?
JASON KU: It will matter here
because I have stakes.
And the rates may
not be unique.
Two people can
have the same bet.
And according to our definition of a
data structure,
it must have unique keys.
So, if I get stuck with all
these things entered by the bidder,
you're going to have a problem.
Now, actually,
we can
avoid this by
essentially keeping a linked
list of all the things with
that key, and everything will be fine.
And then when I want to
return one, I can just do it.
But
in reality, a binary tree is
flexible enough that
in most implementations
you can just store
a bunch of these things.
But, in reality, our
running time is worse.
What does it mean
to find the next in my sequence?
to return the next bigger
thing above this key?
This doesn't really make
sense, as there
could be several.
Which one should I return?
And if I do find-next multiple times
on this data structure,
I might not loop through
all the stuff.
So, some things are
breaking in our interface.
So I would prefer using unique
keys in such a situation.
Next Tuesday, I think
we'll be dealing with non-unique keys with binary heaps.
that's fine.
But if you're going to use
non-unique keys here,
you just need
to be a little
careful about the semantics.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
JASON KU: You'll
get the same
amount of work – you'll just have to
change the semantics of what
you mean by
"find something."
I just want to return
anything with this key.
AUDIENCE: What if
everything has the same key.
Then...
JASON KU: Then it
takes constant time.
I'm just returning the first one.
I mean, these are
special cases that you
need to think about, right?
I don't like to
think about them.
That's why I just like
unique keys.
And if I need a situation
where I have non-unique keys,
I'm going to
put the collisions of that key
into a new data structure.   It's
just easier for me
to separate
what's happening in my head.
Because all the
runtimes we proposed
have very clear
definitions of the unique key.
When you're dealing
with a multiset,
it's a little
more common.
Any more questions?
We really need to
move on, don't we?
Dictionary with key on tender.
We haven't implemented
any dynamic operations yet.
New bet.
What should I do?
What will I
need to upgrade?
I will
need to find
in each of these
data structures
where this bidder is located.
And if I just
point to their rate,
the interface doesn't tell
me what their old rate was.
It just tells me what
their bidder ID is.
So if I only had the auctioneer ID
and the new bid, how the heck do
I figure out
which of these data – where
they are in these data structures?
What I can do is I can
store in this dictionary--
which I can look up after a
certain amount of time-- a
pointer to where it
exists in these things.  Does
this make sense?
This is called cross-linking.
Maybe you did a little bit of that
in
Problem Set 2 or something like that.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Restore
a pointer to a specific participant?
JASON KU: Yeah, exactly.  The
invariant that we
have is that all the
bettors that we've
processed so far
exist in these data structures--
in one of these
data structures--
because we've used an
AVL tree set.
Specifically, it
exists in a node of one
of these data structures.
What we can do is
maintain pointers that map
each bidder ID
to its location in
these data structures.
And why would that be
useful?
Let's say I draw this dictionary.
What can I use
for this dictionary
to get the
required uptime?
I could use a hash
table or an AVL set.
If it's AVL set, I'll
get logarithmic time, worst
case.
With a hash table I
get constant time,
but that's expected.
So in the worst case, it could be linear
time.
We will use the installed
AVL tree because that is what
we are doing now.
And this
will lead to the worst case scenario.
I'm going to keep this pointer for each of these things.   The first thing
I'm going to
do is I'm going to
do that
surgery that we did.
If I add a new bettor,
I'll take D and B--
these two values, this
object, this bettor object
or whatever--
I'll look at the
smallest thing in this
data structure, see if their bet is
greater than what
I'm inserting.
If so, then I'm not going to
touch this data structure.
I'll just
paste it here.
And now, after
inserting it here, I
know exactly where it is
in the data structure.
I just inserted it.
So now, with
this in my hand-- the
node-- I can go and
insert this bidder here
by bid ID.
So, it
will take logarithmic time.
And now I can store
my pointer
to this data structure using this node.  Does
this make sense?
Otherwise, I
do the same thing.
If it's bigger than the smallest
thing here, I take this smaller
thing out, put it in there,
and I put my new guy in here,
connecting each of these
pointers as I go.
I hope this makes sense?
Like?
good.
And for the update it's very similar.
If I want to update a
particular bidder,
I look in this
data structure, find the bidder,
move that
pointer to where
it is in one of these
AVL trees, right?
If it's in there, I just
remove it from the tree
or remove it from the
tree and then
reinsert it with a
new bid.
And if it's in
this, I
remove it from the tree again,
insert it back into any
of these things,
and then I might have to
swap a constant
number of things back and
forth to maintain
that this has the highest k .
And when I do these
dynamic operations,
I always remove
some constant number of
nodes in each of these
trees and add back a
constant number of things.
And while I'm doing that, I'm just
updating this total
as I go.
This amount was the sum of
all the bets here.
And if I insert a
new rate here,
I have to add to this amount.
And if I remove one, I have to
remove from that total.
But again, it's a
constant number of things that
I'm putting in and out of
these data structures,
so it can update
that in constant time.  Does
this make sense?
Now, the search here, and the
insert and delete
here, each of them took
logarithmic time, in the worst case.
But I made a
steady number of them.
So, again the logarithm of time.  Does
this make sense?
That's essentially the
problem.
It's hard, right?  There are
a lot of
moving parts here.
But if you just break it down
and describe it to me...
like, you did a really
good job on this part,
describe it to me well, what
your data structure is, then
these descriptions of
these algorithms
can be pretty short.
In this case, you tell me
these three data structures,
you tell me this guy
maps to his location
and these things, I
serve this guy,
and then you just maintain these
things with dynamic operations,
and then you use these things
for query operations.  Does
this make sense?
Wow, do we have 10 more minutes?
I'll
make it 4-4 for you briefly.
Register of recipients.
We have a coach.
She has a bunch of
football players--
receivers.
And wanting to
start on her team,
a certain number of players who
have the highest efficiency.
And by performance, we
mean the average number of
points they played
in the games they
registered in their system.
But in reality, their
data is incomplete.
They don't know in which games
and how many they scored
and all that stuff.  There
may be errors.
And so these interns are
constantly
updating this database with
queries like "oh, never mind,
this person didn't
play this game,
or actually did play it and they
scored this many points."
This is... cleaning
and writing things down.
And then, at some
point in time, like
when we want to
play a game, I want to be
able to return
the shirt with the kth highest
efficiency in log n time.
This is a kind of
rank request, right?
k-th highest.
Now, actually, I can
return all the top k players
so that can be my list.
But this is a more
generalized request.
It's more specific, more...
it's not really comparable.
But you understand why this
can be useful for a coach.  I
don't know.
Maybe not.
So what's the idea here?   There are
many different things floating around us
.
We have games.
They have identifiers - unique identifiers.
We have receivers.
They have unique identifiers.
And each receiver could
play a lot of games.
Oh, that's kind of disturbing.
And many receivers can
play in one game.
These
many-to-one mappings are
a bit confusing.
And then each player--
receiver-- has a certain
number of points per game.
And we try to sort them
by performance,
which is a rational number.
Ugh, right?
Which is related to
the number of games played
and the total number of points.
Now I see a rational number,
I can't calculate it.
This is what we talked about in the
last problem session, right?
But what I can do
is keep track of the
total number of
games they have played
and the total number of
points they have.
And you can imagine that
with an extension
like this, every time
I add a game, one
of these little operations, I
can update this information
for each player.
If one of these
dynamic operations
only affects
one receiver, I
can update any information
in constant time,
perhaps if I just store the
player's
total number of games
recorded in the database
and the number of points
they have scored.
Then, if I have a
data structure that
requires sorting the receivers
by their performance
so that I can
find the kth one — the
kth largest — then I can't
compute that performance.
But what can I do?
I can compare two players based on
their performance using
cross multiplication.
Because I have the
numerator and denominator of
each of these
rational numbers, and I can
cross-multiply and
determine which is
greater or less.
And as long as I
have a comparator,
I can do AVL sets.  Does
this make sense?
good.
I'll just outline
the components of this
data structure.
Well, first, I'll
need to record the receiver.
And there can
be a lot of games in the receiver.
But the important thing is the problem
centered on the receiver
.
Does this make
sense to you guys?
I never want to
filter out all the receivers that
play a game.
I never delete a
game from the system,
I delete
the receiver so that it can never
play a certain game.  Does
this make sense?
So if I'm storing a
receiver, and each receiver
has certain games
associated with them, it
makes sense, I
could have a nested
data structure where s--
maybe I have a
dictionary about receivers.
And for each of them, I
store all the games
they played in a
different data structure.
With each receiver, I store a
different — its own
data structure containing
all of its games.  Does
this make sense?
Okay, that's an idea.
We have something like...
I need to be able to
look for receivers
because I'm clearing them
or recording them.
So I'm going to have a
dictionary or...
here, I'm looking for the
worst time journal.
So I'm going to skip the
dictionary abstraction
and go directly to the AVL set.
AVL key on receivers.
I before E, except
C. Is that I--
E-I?
This rule never works.
good.
Set up an AVL tree on the receivers,
and each of these nodes
with each of these
receivers I'm going to save--
for each one I'm going to save an
AVL set in the games.
Why do I keep an
AVL set in games?
Why don't I just save a
list of all the games?
Because if I want to remove
this game from the receiver,
I need to do it in log n time.
And here we say
that n is the number of games,
but the number of
players on a team is
always less than the
number of games.
If I search this AVL tree
and search its AVL tree,
I can be sure that these two
searches have only been registered n times.
Because I need to
delete the game, right?
So, here it is.
Then what do I do?
I return the kth
highest performance.
Well, I need-- with each
of these guys I also keep--
what was that increase?
The amount of points
saved in these games.
The sum of the points and--
what was that-- numbers games.
Because if I keep both of
these things in constant time,
I will be able to
calculate their performance,
where I will
be able to have the data I
need to compare performance.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
JASON KU: Yes, that's right.
Just numbers.
These are data structures.
This is a data structure.
These are just numbers.
And I keep that
with every receiver.
But that won't help
me find the kth highest player.
None of these things are
sorted by performance.
So I need the last data structure.
Fifth, I need to store
something dynamically sorted
by performance.
AUDIENCE: Install AVL?
JASON KU: Install AVL, yes.
Install AVL that keeps receivers
tuned for performance.
Now, when I talk
about performance,
you want to mention
something about
cross multiplication.
For example, I store with
each of these things
this increment, and when
I compare two things,
I use cross multiplication.
But beyond that, we
can abstract from that, right?
We abstracted
this function call.
And I can imagine
comparing the two keys.
I can do it.
This is a theory.
I'm not asking you
to implement this.
But this is enough for me,
as a reader of your decision, to
say: yes, you
know what you're talking about.
Okay,
how do you combine these things?
The thing is, I'm going to
need to...
I need to update these things
when I insert or remove a game.
So how do I know where these
receivers are in this thing?
I'm storing a pointer to
this data structure, right?
So, I keep
a pointer to where
it is in the data structure.
Again, I keep
all the receivers.
It's the same size
as data structure number 1
there, has the
same number of receivers.
But we're not done yet
, because I don't
want to know who has the
best result.
I want to know who has the kth
best performance.
ugh
How do I find the kth
best thing in this tree?
I have a tree.
Install the AVL tree.
This is reflected in productivity.
I know where the last one is.
But if I want to find the
kth from the end,
how do I do that?
This AVL tree is a
tuned AVL tree.
All I keep is the heights.
Is there any surgery
you've been thinking about?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE] you
don't keep the size of each one.
JASON KU: The
default AVL tree
doesn't preserve dimensions, right?
That's what consistency does.
But do you think that maybe it would be
useful in this situation?
So
, actually, if I decided to
also increase in size,
I could do exactly the same
find_at sequence operation,
and I could
find the n minus the kth element here,
using the same
function for the subtree that I
had in the
AVL sequence of the tree material.
In fact, in CLRS
they don't even
worry about AVL sequence trees.
They jump right to the fact that if I wanted
this rank search feature
in an ordered order of
things,
I could increase the
subtree sizes.
But it's actually a much more
useful general property,
so we decided to present it to
you in the context of
AVL sequence trees, because then I
can just reduce
to it when I get here.
So, this is a kind of
data structure framework
that works on this problem.
I leave it as an
exercise for you to perform
all these operations
for yourself,
or take a look at the solution.
The latter
will be posted online - the
solution.
This is quite difficult.
This is what is called - you can
think of increasing the size of
finding-rank as a
one-way range query.
Essentially, how many things
are to the right of this value?
What the last problem does is
it walks you
through a two-way
range query where
I want to know how many nodes are
between these two values.
So, this is a step-by-step guide.
Okay,
thank you.
AUDIENCE: Thank you.