[SQUEAK]
[SCRATCH] [CLICK]
JUSTIN SOLOMON: Okay, team.
Let's start the day.
It's nice
to see you all, guys.
If you don't
remember, I'm Justin.
I'm the third instructor of 006,
which you've probably forgotten about,
but you'll see
me a lot more in the
graph theory part of our course because that's the
part of algorithms
that I enjoy.
If I were reincarnated as a
theoretical computer scientist,
I would probably
go into this field.
Hello, guys.
good.
We have a visit from the PhD soon,
I'm
working on my
camp cheerleader voice for the next few days.
So don't make me wake
you all up for the day.
You won't like it.
But anyway, so at
6.006, if you look back
at the course outline,
we officially
start the second part of this class.  There
are several consequences of this fact.
So, if there are no
questions about that,
we'll start with
our new unit in 6.006,
which is graph theory.
If you're interested, there's
a graph on the screen here.
But of course, today we will provide
a little more information
during our lecture.
When I was studying
to teach, which I still do,
my PhD actually
told me that if you want someone to
learn something, you should
write it down as much as possible.
And so I really lean
towards that approach
today in our slides.
So anyway,
today we're
going to have our first
lecture on graphs,
which I think will be somewhat of a
review for a lot of you guys.
And if not,
that's cool too.
Because we're going to start
from the beginning
and kind of
build up all the concepts
needed to understand and
process graphs, and hopefully
by the end of the lecture
we'll have some style of
algorithm for computing
the shortest path from one vertex
to all the others.
So, if we're a little bit lost in
terminology, a graph -
some people call it a network,
but sometimes that term
is overloaded with several
different variations on the
theme -
is a combination of two things.
Here's what
this notation in parentheses means.
There is a set of vertices
and a set of edges.
And the edges, as you can
see in the third point
on our screen here, are a
subset of v cross v.  Now that
's a fancy
term for something
very, very simple.
Because what does that tell me?
This tells me about the
edge, like in the image
we see here on the screen.
it's just what
connects the vertices together.
So if I think about having a
pair of vertices, like from
and to, then that's a
subset of the cross product of
v and itself.
So, hopefully the notation in
that third line on the screen
makes some sense.
This is just a fancy notation, since
edges are pairs of vertices.
But of course, there
are two special cases in this notation that
we care about in this class.
One is a
directed graph, the
other is undirected
because I said them in the
opposite order to what is
on the screen.
So in an undirected graph, I
think we still think of an edge
as a pair of vertices, but
I should actually have labeled
it a little
differently-- actually,
maybe I'll go over this in the
slides before they go
to OCW--
where instead of writing
e equals w comma v,
I should write
actually equals v comma w.
And notice that there is a slight
difference between the notation
on the slide and what I
wrote on the board, which is the
established notation here.
What's the difference between
brackets and wavy lines
is that this guy is not ordered.
This is a set of things.
And what's on
the board is orderly,
or rather what's on the screen.
And of course, in an
undirected edge,
there is no such thing
as an edge from w
to v that is different from an
edge from v to w.
It's the same.
They are not directed.
It's simply a concept of
connectivity.
Whereas in a directed
graph, we
will now use this
notation in parentheses
to say that
the edge from w to v
is different from the
edge from v to w.
This will be of
great importance.
So, for example, in
the graph on the right -
let's maybe redraw
it on the board here.
So, we have four vertices.
I drew this last night and
I hope this example
actually works.
So... can I go from the
top right vertex
to the bottom left vertex
along the edges of this graph?
I heard one person.
Three for everyone... 1, 2, 3.
AUDIENCE: No.
JUSTIN SOLOMON: No, that's right.
Because if I wanted to--
I mean, maybe I'm thinking about
drawing this path here--
but of course, if I
went from the top right corner
to the bottom left--
that would be the ugliest thing
I've ever done, I'm sorry,
you might notice that the
edges are pointing
up here.
So I would have to go against the
flow of the water,
but that is not permissible
in the case of a directed graph.
Of course, I
already sense a
notion of a path that we have
n't yet defined.
But I
intuitively think that this is a
big difference between a
directed and an undirected graph.
Does this distinction make
sense to all of you,
or have I managed to lose
you in four minutes or less?
Perfectly.
So I flipped things around a bit
from the
course notes because I
decided that we would
first define what a graph is
before telling you
what the implications are.
But anyway,
I think it's
not a big stretch of the
imagination
to say that graphics are
literally everywhere
in our daily lives, right?
Whenever we think of a
network of things connected
together, the implicitly
correct abstraction that often pops
into our heads
is to think of a graph.
So some simple
examples that I think
everyone can think of are
like computer networks --
so the nodes or vertices of
your graph in that case
are maybe computers,
and the edges are kind of like the
cables that
connect them together,
my very rough understanding of
how networks work --
or maybe in a social network
-- the nodes are the people
in your social network,
and the edges are the
friendships
, the hostility,
or whatever.
In fact, I think you can think
of a directed and an undirected
version of this
particular network.
Regarding road networks, maybe
I work at Google
and want to tell
you the shortest route
between your house and MIT.
Of course, to
do this and essentially
behind the scenes, we
solve some version
of calculating
the shortest path between two
vertices in the graph.
This is a small
lie in the sense
that there
is a lot of structure in this problem
that we will not
use in this course.  A
road network is a very
special type of graph,
and if you take an
advanced level course, maybe
you'll say, okay, if I know
a little bit more about my graph,
I can do better than the general
case that we're going to talk about here.
But the basic algorithms that
we'll talk about in 6.006 are
certainly
relevant in this case
and are actually the
building blocks
for what happens
in the tools that are
used every day on your
phone when you open Google Maps
or Ways or something.
And of course,
there are many others.
So, for example,
an example that might
be a little more
subtle
would be the set of states
and transitions of a
single thing.
So think of it like a
Rubik's Cube.
So I could build a
graph where
each configuration of
my Rubik's Cube is a node,
as is each rotation.
And then the facets are like
, can I
go from this
configuration to another one
by making one simple
transition, like one flip.
I don't really know
the terminology in Rubik's Cube,
I feel like you
know, one turn at a time.
Twist-- thank you.
And of course,
there are many other places.
So, for example, in
my day job here at MIT,
I usually teach
courses in computer graphics.
And
graph theory itself, although we
talk about it in completely different ways,
appears in that world
all the time.
Because, of course,
sitting behind any 3D model
on your computer is a
giant network of triangles.
This is called a
triangular surface--
like this torus that we see here.
And this is nothing more
than a schedule.
And in fact, if you
look at the algorithms
that we cover in chapter six
eight three eight,
you'll see that they're roughly
graph algorithms in disguise.
In fact, if you take my graduate
course, one thing we'll do
is spend a lot of time
on differential geometry.
And then we'll step
back 10 feet and notice
that
the algorithms we
use to calculate curvature
and bending on triangular
meshes look
like graph algorithms
and can be applied to networks in
exactly the same way.
So this will be a nice
fun discovery.
And of course, there's one
last fun application.
I was actually absent for the
last couple of days
at a conference on
political redistricting.
And funny thing is,
most of the discussions
at that conference
were about graph theory.
The reason for this is
a theme that
often appears in the world of geometry.
If I take my state,
in this case I think it's the
precincts in a
given state,
and I look at the
adjacency relationships,
then maybe I'll set up a node for
each precinct and an edge
every time they share a
border.
Now I have a network.
And perhaps the region on my graph
is like a connected part of
this network.
Either way, this is one
of those examples where
graphs, networks,
connectivity, and so on just
appear literally no matter
where you go.
They are absolutely impossible to avoid.
That's why we'll
spend a lot of time
on this lesson.
Now, you could easily
take, I think,
at least three entire courses
in graph theory here at MIT,
and you could easily build a
PhD
just doing really simple
graph problems.
Of course, in this class
we are limited to just a few
lectures out of many.
So we will make
a few assumptions
both for the problems we want
to solve and for the graphs
we are interested in.
In particular, one
simplifying assumption
that
doesn't really affect
many of the algorithms
we'll talk about here,
but it's worth making
clear, is
that we'll be
thinking mostly about a particular type of
graph, which is a
simple graph.
And in fact, often, depending
on how you define your schedule,
you've somehow accidentally
made your schedule simple,
even if you didn't intend to.
So, for example, we
wrote that our edges
are a subset of v intersecting v.
This probably means that I can't
have multiple edges
crossing the
same pair of vertices.
So let's look at an example of a
complex graph.
Sorry, I
didn't actually define that.  A
simple graph is a graph
that has no self-cycles,
so it cannot go from a
vertex to itself,
and each edge is distinct.
So, let's create the most complicated
graph we can think of.
Let's say I
have two vertices.
So maybe if I want to make my own...
so there's a graph, right,
two vertices and one edge.
It's simple.
If I wanted to be annoying
and make it difficult,
maybe I'd take that advantage and
copy it three times just
for fun.
This violates the
second assumption.
And now, even worse,
I could break the first one
by adding an edge that goes
from this vertex to itself.
It's not easy.
I don't know what you would
actually call it-- the overall graph,
I think-- complex
because it's not simple.
I don't know - multigraph.
I've always thought about it--
anyway, it doesn't matter.
But anyway,
in this class we wo
n't worry about
that particular circumstance.
And of course, in many
applications of graph theory,
this is a perfectly reasonable
assumption.
Have questions about
the definition of a simple graph?
So, from now on, every time
we think about a graph,
in our
head we will
think that our graph is simple.   A simple graph
has one wonderful property
,
which I wrote here in very
large text on the screen
, which is that the
edges are the big O of v squared.
And actually, let's
expand this formula a little bit.
So, there are
two cases: one is
when my graph
is undirected, the other is
when my graph is directed.
So, if I have a directed graph...
okay, let's think about how many
edges we can have.
So an edge is a pair a
from vertex to a to vertex,
and I can never repeat that twice.
This is something like a
second assumption.
So, specifically,
what do we know?
We know that mod E--
or rather, the number of
edges in our graph is an
upper bound on what?
Well, I can take any
pair of vertices-- like
this-- but I have to
be a little careful
because my graph is directed--
so from and to matter here.
So this v select
2 means I
can take any unique
pair of vertices,
but I have to put
a factor of 2 in front of it
to account for the fact that
the source and target
can be rotated back and forth.
And of course, if I want
to make a film without directing,
I don't need to
worry about that.
We're going to get that E here is less than
or equal to just mod v select 2.
So this is just a
fancy way of saying
that each edge consists
of two vertices,
and my edges are unique.
And one thing, if
you just write down
the formula for our
binomial coefficient here,
we'll see that both of
these things--
oh, oh, yeah, sorry--
have the worst value mod v squared here.
And this is quite logical,
because, of course, an edge
is a pair of vertices.
You kind of expect there to
be a square there.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JUSTIN SOLOMON: I'm so sorry.
I can't hear you
AUDIENCE: So the 2
comes from the fact that
it's from the source.
JUSTIN SOLOMON: Yeah, exactly.
So, 2 for the
director case comes from the fact
that the edge from v to w
is different from the edge from w
to v.  So remember that the
binomial coefficient here
simply counts
the number of ways I
can choose two things
from a set of size v,
but it doesn't care
about the order.
Yes, are there any more questions?
Perfectly.
Why does this matter?
These kinds of
boundaries, I mean,
they might seem
a little obvious to you,
but we're going to
write down graph algorithms.
And now, when we analyze the
execution time and the space
they take up, we now have
two different numbers
that we can think about:
the number of vertices
and the number of edges.
And so, for example,
if I write an
algorithm whose running time is
proportional to the number of
edges, maybe
then in general I
could also think of the
algorithm as
having a running time that looks
like the number of vertices
squared, unless I make
additional assumptions
about my graph.
So there is some
connection between all
these different
constants, and it's
useful to keep that
in the back of your mind.
Sometimes you'll see a
bunch of different expressions
that actually encode roughly the same
relationship, just in
different languages.
Of course, this also means
we can be more precise.
So sometimes the graph is what
we call sparse.
So in my universe,
almost all the graphs
I deal with in
everyday life are extremely sparse.
This is a consequence of
topology.
And because of
this, an algorithm
that scales as the
number of edges
can actually be much
better than an algorithm
that scales as
the number of vertices
squared, because
in practice there are often
fewer edges than
each individual possible pair.
That's why
we think
about these numbers.
Okay, let's continue creating
boring definitions here.
So, some others that
we need to think about are
related to the topology or
connectivity of our graph,
specifically thinking
about neighbors.
So, in general, we consider
pairs of vertices to be
neighbors of
each other
if there is an edge between them.
We have to be
a little careful,
because of course, when
we have a directional advantage,
we have to be careful about
who transmits
and who receives
these neighborhood relationships.
So, let's draw a
very, very simple graph.
So here's vertex 0, here's
vertex 1, here's vertex 2.
And maybe we'll have an edge
going up, an edge going down,
and then a cycle here.
good.
Now we can define many
different concepts of
neighbors-- like an
output neighbor set, an
input neighbor set.
And the basic idea is
that we
want to track the edges
coming from the vertex and the edges
pointing into the whole.
So, for example, the
original
neighbor set, which we'll
denote as Adj plus here...
what is the original
neighbor set of node 0 here?
Well, if we look, we'll
notice that there's
one edge coming out of node 0
that points to node 2.
So of course, this is a
set that
contains only one other node.
And similarly, the incoming
neighbor set of node 0,
notice well that there is one
incoming neighbor from vertex 1,
so this is such a set.
Of course, in an
undirected graph,
the distinction
between these two things
doesn't matter.
So if you look at our
last marker point
here, often in the
undirected case
we just drop the
superscript "plus" or "minus"
because it
supposedly doesn't matter.
In any case, there is one
additional piece of terminology
that is quite
important, and that is degree.
And this is nothing more
than simply calculating
the size of this set.
Thus, the external degree is
the number of edges
that exit from a vertex.
And a degree is the
number of edges that point inward.
So notice, in this case
both of these numbers are equal to 1.
Let's look at an example
where this is not the case.
So, at node 1, notice, there are
two edges.
So the outgoing degree of
node 1 is 2.
There is one edge that points
inward, so the incoming degree is 1.
Okay, so why are we
going to do this so often?
Well, we will get
many graph algorithms
that have a FOR loop
over the neighbors of a given
vertex.
And then
this number of steps will come into play.
It's worth limiting these things a bit
.
So, in particular, one thing
we can think about--
I'm writing too big, and I'm going to
run out of space here very quickly--
is the following.
So, let's look at
all the possible nodes
inside my graph,
and now let's
sum up all their degrees.
So I'm going to--
let's see, if I
look at this graph, I'll
notice that there are three edges
adjacent to this vertex
, three edges adjacent to
that one, two edges adjacent to that one.
So, we summarize them all together.
So this is just a convenient
connection -
it's summing these
things up, because we'll
have algorithms that
look like for each vertex,
each neighbor does something.
So we could roughly know
how long
it would take.
Let's think about this.
So, what do we know?
In an undirected
graph, each edge is
adjacent to two vertices.
So if we think
about how we account for
degree, what do we know?
We know that an
edge seems to
affect the degree of
two different vertices.
So if we think about
it carefully here,
we'll see that
if our graph is undirected--
oh, sorry-- that's right,
wait, I'm back again.
So if I have a graph with
two vertices and one edge,
and it's undirected, notice
that the number of edges
here is 1.
What is the degree sum?
Well, this is 1 plus 1 equals 2.
So, there's a 2 here
if my graph is undirected,
and an E here if my graph is
directed, if what I'm counting
is just the original degree.  Does
this make sense?
I think I managed to
completely mess up that sentence,
so maybe let's try it again.
So if I just count
the number of edges pointing
to each vertex,
and I count that
over all
possible vertices,
then there are two cases--
one is directed and the
other is undirected.
So in the undirected
case you get 2
because effectively every
edge is both an
outgoing and an incoming edge.
Whereas you get 1
as the coefficient
in the directional case.  Does
this make sense?
I'm sorry I
ruined it for even a second.
Okay, great.
Okay, this will come in
handy later.
We're thinking about
graphs now, of course,
we just spent the
last couple of weeks
thinking about data structures.
You need to think about how
to save the schedule on your computer,
and there are
many options.
Actually, really, one thing
you can do is something like a pair-- just like
when we were
talking about sets.
There are many different
ways to store kits.
And one way to think
about it is, depending
on how we're going to interact
with this set, we can choose one
data structure or another
to optimize
the types of interactions that we're going to
have with this set
and make them as
fast as possible.
It's exactly the
same story for the graph.
So, for example,
the stupidest representation of a graph in the world would be to
simply
have a long list of edges.
So, for example, for
this graph here, maybe
I have 0, 1, which is an
edge, and then 0,
2, which is another edge, and
then 1, 2, and then 2, 1.
There's a big list of edges.
This is truly a set.
I don't care about order.
AUDIENCE: The first one is 1, 2.
JUSTIN SOLOMON: 1—
oh, you're right.
I'm sorry.
Yes, the edge is pointing up--
thanks Eric, or no Eric--
Jason.
Okay, let's say I
have a graph algorithm
and I
need to do something
like check if an
edge from v
to w exists multiple times.
How long will it
take in this data structure?
Well, if I just have an
unordered list of edges,
and I want to know if
there is an edge from v to w,
all I can do is write a
FOR loop that just goes along that
and says, here's the
edge I'm looking for.
No.  Is
this the advantage
I'm looking for?
No.
Every time I
want to find an edge,
it will take
time proportional to
the number of
edges in my graph,
which could potentially
be up to v squared.
Yes, it's not such a
great representation of
the graph on my computer.
So if we think
about our data structure,
we can say, okay, so a bounded list is
probably not the way to go.
Although note that the way
we labeled
what a graph is
looks like a limit list.
But in any case,
the most common thing to do
is to create something like an
adjacency list.
So the basic idea of ​​an
adjacency list
is that I'm going to store a
set that maps a vertex
u to everything that is adjacent to u.  In
other words,
I'm just going to
keep track of all the
outgoing edges
from each vertex.
And now I have to decide how
I will store this item.
And often
we will have to
answer questions, such as whether
there is an edge from v
to w.  So
how could I do that?
First, I
look up v, and I get a
list or
set of all things
that are adjacent to v.  And
I have to ask this thing.
And I want it to be pretty quick.
So maybe
I store a set of
related materials as
something like a random access array
or hash table for
quick lookups.
So, for example, how
long would it take--
I see, I'm going to
finish the sentence here--
how long would it take
me to check
if an edge exists in my graph?
Well, what would I do?
I would first
pull this object out
and then look inside from here
.
So if I stored this
as a hash table, the
expected time I would
have an order one lookup
because it's an
order one, and then
you have another order
one lookup.
So we went from v squared to
unity with one simple trick.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Does the
direction matter [INAUDIBLE]
JUSTIN SOLOMON: That's a
great question.
So, this is a design
decision.
Sorry, I
think a lot about undirected graphs in my head,
and I'm going to
make this mistake a lot.
And I'm glad you caught me.
There is a perfectly
reasonable thing
that could possibly be done, which is to
keep track of the outgoing edges
for each vertex.
This is a design decision.
For an algorithm,
maybe I want to
keep track of incoming edges.
Whatever it is, I just have to
make sure
it aligns with what I
want to do with my schedule later.
Excellent point.
Sorry, but we geometric people
rarely encounter directed
graphs.
But it's important
to remember
that not everyone is working on the
same problems as me.
Okay, now if I wanted to be
absolutely extreme about this-- just as a
third example of a
representation
that can actually,
in a sense, be
thought of as an
adjacency list--
we need an adjacency matrix,
where I'm now just storing a
giant v by v array of
like does this exist,
does that edge exist.
Now it's very, very easy
to check if an edge exists.
But now suppose I
created a graph algorithm that would
have a
FOR loop over all the
neighbors of some vertex.
So, if I wanted to go
through all the neighbors of u,
I could do it in
time proportional to the
number of neighbors of u.
But if I just have a
big adjacency matrix,
just a bunch of binary values--
like for each pair of vertices,
are those vertices
adjacent-- yes or no.
If I want to iterate
over all my neighbors,
now I have to go
through all the vertices
and check if it's number
one and then do something.
So it may actually
require extra time
and extra space.  Does
this make sense?
So in any case, it's
kind of a lazy graph
.
I often use it when I code
because adjacency matrices are
easy to work with.
But this takes up a lot of
extra space,
and it's not always the most efficient,
even if you have the space,
because iterating over
neighbors can actually
take quite a while.
Okay, the real goal of
our lecture today is to
start introducing the
canonical problem
we all worry about
with graphs, which is
computing paths,
specifically shortest paths.
So, the first thing we
need to do is, of course,
define what a path is
in a graph.
So we'll talk about
our schedule as a road network.
Let's think of each
node here as an intersection.
So, this is roughly
Kendall Square.
Look, it's a square.
But anyway,
let's say what I want to find...
maybe the question
would be: is
there a way to get
from vertex 1 to vertex 3?
And then the better
question is, is
there a
shortcut to get from vertex 1
to vertex 3?
Then, of course, the
first thing I have to do
is identify my enemy.
I have determined what I am
looking for, which is the path.
So, a path is nothing more than a
sequence of vertices in a graph,
where each pair of adjacent
vertices in that sequence
is an edge.
I think all of this is consistent
with our intuition
about what a path is in a graph.
Here, for example,
path p is equal to v1, v2, v3.
So notice that there is an
edge from v1 to v2,
and also an edge from v2 to v3.
Therefore, it satisfies the assumptions
stated in our definition.
What wouldn't be a
path on our graph
would look like v1, which is v3,
because there's no edge there.
So, if we're talking about
paths, there's a
very natural concept,
which is length.
Length, I think, can be thought of
as the number of vertices
in your path minus 1,
or the number of edges
that your path crosses.
It's the same.
So, for example, the
path length p here is 2. Does
everyone see that?  A
very common coding error
that I often encounter
is accidentally adding 1 to this
number.
Because, of course, there are
one more vertex than edges on your path
.
Okay, and there are
many different ones - there
could potentially be
more than one path
between any pair of vertices.
So, let's say I have an
undirected graph that
looks like this.
So it's just a square
plus a diagonal.   So,
here are the nodes.
So, a perfectly valid
way to get from the bottom left corner
to the top right corner would be to
go up one and then down the other,
but of course there is a
more efficient way
to get from the bottom left corner
to the top right,
which is to go diagonally.
So, when we talk
about the shortest path,
it is nothing but the
length of the
path that has
the least number of edges
or vertices between any pair of
vertices in my graph.
Okay, this is our enemy.
This is what we strive for.
This is the calculation of the shortest path
between vertices in a graph.
And this is something
we will
talk about quite a bit in this course.
Because, of course, it's a
very practical matter.
For example, when I want to
solve routing problems,
I want to move packets out
of my network,
I would prefer not to do that-- well,
unless I'm using Tor--
I would prefer not to have them hit
too many computers in between.
Then maybe I want a
computerized shortcut.
Or on the surface, maybe I
want to move the information
not too far.
But of course, there are
many variations
on this theme when we
talk about the shortest path
or even the
existence of a path.
So, these are the three
types of modeling problems
that we can solve on a graph.
So the first one,
which
we of course call
one-pair reachability,
would be the idea that
I take two vertices s
and t on my graph g,
and I ask you if there
is a path between s and t.
So, what would be an
extreme example
where this problem
doesn't always
give a "yes" answer?
For some reason in our heads, I
think we consider all graphs
to be connected.
But a perfectly correct graph,
as we defined it, would
have 10
vertices and no edges.
This function would be
very easy to code
if it were the only
graph you were ever interested in.
But any event, the
existence of a path,
is a query
that requires a bit of
algorithmic thinking.
We haven't figured out
how to do it yet.
Now another problem we can solve is the
shortest path.
Given a graph and
two vertices, we
could say how far apart
these vertices of my graph are
if I want to use the
shortest distance from one
to the other.
Note that I can use the second
problem to solve the first.
Because what is
the length of the shortest
path between two vertices
between which there is no path?
Infinity or shrugging
is a
perfectly valid response.
Yes, that's true.
So, how can I implement
accessibility code?
Well, I could call the
code of my shortest path,
and that gives me infinity.
Then I return no,
it is not available.
And if it doesn't give me
infinity, I return yes.
So remember that the key
idea in the algorithm class
is this idea of ​​reduction.
That I can use one
function to solve another.
So in case we can
solve the shortest path,
then we can definitely solve the
reachability problem
by calling this part of the code.
And finally we can talk
about the shortest path from a single source
.
So, notice that there
is only one input node s here –
so this problem is to
give me
the length of the
shortest path from s
to every other
vertex in my graph.  Does
this make sense?
Maybe I'm returning a large
array with all the information about
each shortest distance.
So, can we solve one
pair of shortest paths using the
shortest path from one source?
Absolutely.
I could take s in my
one-pair shortest path problem,
calculate the shortest path from
s to literally everything else,
and then throw away all that
information except the shortest
path to t, and now I'm good.
I didn't argue that
this is the fastest possible
way to solve
the second problem,
but at least it shows that
if I can solve problem three,
I can solve problem two.
If I can solve two, I
can also solve one problem.
So in today's
lecture we will only be concerned
with problem three.  In
other words, these
things
are listed in
order of increasing complexity.
So, to think about the problem of the
shortest path from a single source
, we will create
one additional construct.
And this is an idea called the
shortest path tree.
I was too lazy to draw on
PowerPoint slides at 2:00 AM yesterday,
and thought of
drawing a picture on the board instead.
So, let's draw a graph.
So here we have a, b – from now on
I will use letters
instead of numbers
to denote nodes
because I don't want to
confuse the length of the
shortest path
with the index of my node.
So here's a, b, c--
I'm going to match
my notes here--
d, e, f.
Here's the graph –
undirected again,
because your instructor likes to
think about undirected graphs.
But I know I'll
get feedback that I
shouldn't have done it later.
But anyway,
let's say I
want to calculate the shortest
path from a to everything
else, or rather the length.
So, first of all, without even
talking about the algorithm,
I think it's pretty easy
to guess what it is.
So obviously the shortest path
from a to a has length 0.
The shortest length from a
to b is 1, from a to c is 2,
because I can follow these guys.
Now it gets complicated.
It is branched.
So the next shortest path has
length 3, and then 4 like this.
Does everyone agree
with me that the numbers
I've decorated here are the
lengths of the shortest
path from a to everything else?
But what didn't I do?
I didn't tell you how to
actually calculate the path,
I just gave you the
length of the path.
So I might need a piece of
code that, in addition to determining
the length of the shortest path to a single source,
also gives me the
shortest path to a single source.
So initially, when I think about
it, I might think about,
well, how do I even
write down a data structure that
can store all these paths.
Well, each path can have
like v vertices, right.
Maybe
for whatever reason,
my schedule has a lot of branches.
And all the paths are
very long.
Actually, I think I need to
consider
whether branching
will make them longer or shorter.
But in any case, I could have a
really boring data structure
that just keeps track, for
each individual vertex, of the
shortest
path from a to that vertex.
How big
will this data structure be?
Well, if the only constraint I
have on the length of a path is
that--
it definitely spans at most
all the vertices in my graph--
then any path
will span v spaces.
Thus, it will occupy v
squared of the total space.
That wouldn't be so good.
Because in a way,
my graph
now has linear information.
It's just the
length of the path.
If I want to actually
reconstruct this path, then I
first spiritually
feel that I need much
more space to do so.
But the answer is that
we don't actually do that.
We will
only need a linear space,
and the idea is to
store an object
called a shortest path tree.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Just for [INAUDIBLE]
the previous [INAUDIBLE]..
JUSTIN SOLOMON: So
the question was about recursion.
We didn't actually
write down any graph algorithms.
So we're going to put it off
until we actually repeat.
And then
we'll think more carefully.
Yes, but it's a perfectly
reasonable question.
There are many recursive
graph algorithms.
And then we'll
probably have to do some very careful calculations.
So, instead, we will
define an object called a
shortest path tree.
And the main trick
here is to say:
how did I get from a to c?
Well, on the shortest path there is always a vertex
that is its predecessor
.
And the shortest path has this
wonderful property,
which is that the shortest path
from a to c, if I truncate it--
right, so it goes from a to b to c--
then the truncated path
is also the shortest path
to the previous vertex.
So let's think about
this for a moment,
because this sentence
, as usual, was poorly
worded by your instructor.
So, let's say
I have a shortest
path from a to d, which
very clearly means a, b, c, d.
I think we can all agree.
And now I take
this sublist.
I'm just looking from a to c.   Is
there ever a
circumstance where
this is not the shortest path
or the shortest path from a to c?
No, that's right, because if there
was a shorter path
from a to c, I could
connect it here
and find the shortest
path from a to d.  Do
you see that?
So, based on this
reasoning, I can just think about the one vertex that's in front of me on my shortest path, instead of typing a
string like this giant
set of shortest paths,
sort of actually
applying, in a sense, a
recursive proposition.
I'm going to trace back.
So, let's look
at our schedule.
Essentially, the object
I will be monitoring is
similar to its predecessor, right?
So what is the predecessor of
f on the shortest path?
Actually it's either d or e.
In this case, it doesn't matter.
Maybe the predecessor is
for fun, right?
What is the predecessor of e?
Obviously, the previous
vertex on the shortest path
is c.
Similarly for d-- now we
have b and a and a bunch of
arrows pointing in that direction.
So for each vertex,
I'll just
start an arrow that points
to the previous vertex
on the shortest path.
I'm not going to store the
entire shortest path, just the
last edge.
So, first of all, how much
memory does this take up?
This takes up v places.  Do
you see that?
Or the size of the
vertex space.
Because each vertex
only has to store one thing,
which is the previous
vertex on the shortest path.
Now what does my algorithm
for tracking the shortest path mean?
It's very simple.
I just start walking
along these edges
until I
get back to a.
This object is now called a
shortest path tree.
Notice that I stole
another word, which is tree.
why is that?
Can I ever have a
cycle on this schedule?
That wouldn't really make
sense, right?
These are the shortest paths.
You should be able to
sort of follow the gradient back
to the original vertex.
Okay, in other words, I'm
going to decorate my schedule with
one extra thing.
We'll call this p of v, which
is the previous vertex
on the shortest path from my
starting point to my vertex v.
And I think what I tried to
prove to you today is
that if I have
this information,
it's actually enough to
reconstruct the shortest path.
I just keep taking p from
v, and then p from p from v,
and then p from p from p
from v, and so on, which
sounds more
complicated than it is,
until I keep track of
my original vertex.
And this object
is conceptually called a shortest path tree.
Any questions about this?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JUSTIN SOLOMON: If I had an
edge that connects a to d, fine.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
JUSTIN SOLOMON: Oh, okay,
the question was,
let's say our colleague
added the advantage –
that's a great question.
You know, someone was angry,
my adversarial neural network
got stuck here because
it was adversarial,
and it wanted my
shortest path code to fail.
And now somehow the tree I
gave you is no longer the same.
And my answer to that is yes.
Why is that?
Well, by adding this edge here,
the length of my shortest path
has changed.
The shortest path
from a to d is now 1.
So this tree is no longer valid.
I need a new Christmas tree.
So what would be the
preceding p of d here?
Well, instead of
being c, it would be a.
Yes, that is absolutely correct.
And in fact, this reflects a
really nasty property of the
shortest path: if
I add one edge to my graph,
the length of the shortest path
to each vertex can change.
Well, I guess
except for the starting vertex.
Yes, and it's a
really big headache
in some programs.
So, for example,
I'll stop talking about programs
and go back to math,
I work a lot with 3D models.
And there is a large dataset of
3D models like ballerinas.
And ballerinas are really
annoying because sometimes they
fold their arms like that
.
And then suddenly the shortest
path between your fingers
becomes
like 0.
And so incremental algorithms
for calculating the shortest path
can fail here, right.
Because I have to
update like everyone else
if I accidentally
glued my fingers like that.  Either way
, I'll let
you think about how
you can solve this problem.
If you want to know more,
you should take 6,838.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
JUSTIN SOLOMON: If you
change your source node,
again, change it as short as possible.
Yeah, this is going to be one
of those really boring things
that I'm going to
keep answering,
like every time I
change something in my problem--
I change my source,
I change my bounds--
I just have to list
all the shortest paths.
Obviously,
there are algorithms that don't do this.
But we wo
n't think about them for now.
good.
So as usual, I
talked too much
and left myself about
10 minutes to work out the
actual algorithm that's
interesting in the lecture,
although it's actually
not that difficult,
so I think we'll get it,
i.e. how do I actually
calculate the shortest paths?
Yes, and the main thing
we're going to do
is kind of build
this analogy with a tree.
We're going to define another
object that I really like--
actually I like this from
Jason's notes because it looks
like a calculation,
and I like it--
and that's the idea of ​​a
set of levels.
So this is a whole
set of things L sub k.
And these are all the
vertices that are within a distance k
from my source.
So, for example, if my
source vertex in this example
is the vertex
all the way to the left,
then L0 obviously contains that very
vertex on the right.
L1 is next.
L2 is the third.
But now L3 is a set
of three vertices
because they are all
at a distance of
3 from the source.
This is what I've
marked in pink here.
Okay, that's all
this notation means.
Oh, I made a small mistake
because in this class the distance is
delta, not
d, but still.
AUDIENCE: [UNINCOMPLETE]
JUSTIN SOLOMON:
Shortest distance
is absolutely correct.
So for example, I might
have a very large distance
from L0 to L2, right.
I could just flip back and
forth between L0 and L1,
maybe go to L4
and then back.
But that wouldn't be very
useful for calculations.
That is absolutely correct.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE].
JUSTIN SOLOMON: Oh, the
red background
is the set L. So for example,
L3 contains these three vertices
because they are all within a
distance of 3 from the left edge.   Late last night
I drew
my diagram too cleverly.
I'm somewhat proud of this.
Okay, so basically, if
I wanted to calculate
the length of the shortest path
from the entire left side
to all the other
vertices, one way to
do that would be to calculate
all of these level sets and then
just check which
level set I'm on, right.
So we're going to introduce an
algorithm called
Breadth-First Search
that does roughly this.
So, breadth-first search
, as we'll
introduce it today,
would be an algorithm to compute
all of these sets of levels, L
sub i, and then from that
we can construct
the length and even the
shape of the shortest path.   .
And I'm going to go
to my handwritten notes.
Okay, and here's what
our algorithm will do.
I'm going to write this
a little differently
than what's in the notes and on the
screen, but only slightly.
So, first of all,
I think we can all agree
that the level set 0--
oh, this-- this
chalk is bifurcated--
it contains one node.
What should this node be like?
The source, because the
only thing at distance
0 from the source
is the source node.
Okay, and in addition to that,
we can initialize the distance
from the source to ourselves.
All three,
what is the distance
from the source to itself--
1, 2, 3.
AUDIENCE: 0.
JUSTIN SOLOMON: Thank you.
You see, you wake up
, it's almost 11:00--
12:00.
What time is it? It's
almost 12:00.  Okay,
and then finally,
maybe at first
we do
n't know anything about the array
p, so we just make it empty.
Since p is a source,
it somehow doesn't matter.
Because once I
got back to the source,
I finished calculating the
shortest path.
So, we'll
write an algorithm that
computes all the level sets and
fills this array p and fills in
the distances in
one big frame.
We'll call this
breadth-first search.
Okay, let's do this.
So, we can use the notation here.
And notice that
basically what's
happening is induction, which is that
I'm going to compute the level
1 set from the level 0 set, the
level 2 set from the level 1 set,
and so on until I've filled
all my level sets.  Does
this make sense?
So, here's a slightly different
way of saying the same thing.
I'm going to use a
WHILE loop, which
I know is a little
unkosher, but that's okay.
So I'm going to initialize
the number i to 1.
This will be
like our counter.
I'm going to say UNTIL the
previous set of levels is not
empty, meaning there
is potentially a
path that goes through the
previous set of levels
to the next one.
Because once one
of my levels becomes empty,
notice that as
Li for even larger i
will also be empty.  There
is never a case where there
is something that is not distance
i and then distance i plus 5.
Okay, so what am
I going to do?
Well, let's
get back to our schedule.
Now I know
this guy is at distance 0.
That's where I started.
So now I'll look at all the
neighbors of this peak.
And I'm going to force
their distance to be 1. Does
that make sense?
And so here
this guy has a distance of 2.
And eventually I'm
going to get into trouble because maybe...
well, what a
good example here.
I won't even try to draw.
I might run into
problems if I don't
want to add a vertex twice
to two different sets of levels.
When I put this
in Li, I don't
want to put this in Li
plus 5 because I already
know that this is distance i.  Does
this make sense?
Okay, what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to repeat all the
vertices in my previous
set of levels.
And now I'm
going to look at every vertex that
is adjacent to u.
Because what do I know?
I know that if I can get
to you in i minus 1 steps, then
how many steps would it
take me to get to any neighbor of u?
i steps, because I can
take a path that's
length i minus
1, add one more edge,
and I'll get to this new guy.
So what can I do?
I can iterate over
all v that
is in the neighboring set u.
But I have to be
a little careful, because what
if I have the edge backwards?
So, for example,
here I have an edge
to the source.
I think this is...
yes, this is a strong example.
I wouldn't want to
add the source
to the third level set
because I already
added it in the previous one guys.
So I want to get rid of
merging all the
previous level sets.  Does
this make sense?  In
other words,
I only consider
adjacent vertices
that I haven't yet visited
in my
level set computing algorithm.
And all I need to do is
update my arrays, right.
Specifically, I'm
going to add vertex v to the level set i,
since I haven't seen v yet.
I'll set the distance
from s to v to be i
because right now I'm
filling my level i.
And finally, what is p of v?
What is the previous
vertex to v on my shortest
path from the source?
It's you, right.
Because this is the guy
from the previous level that
I'm building
my path from, right.
I'm going to set this up for you.
And then... sorry, I'm
out of space,
but I also need to increase the i.
Okay, so what does
this algorithm do?
It's just creating one
level at a time.
If we go back to our image,
so it starts by initializing L0
just as the starting vertex,
and then it looks at all the edges
coming out of it--
in this case just one--
it makes that length 1--
and so on.
And so it's
just a gradual
build-up of all
these sets of levels.
Now there is a fairly
simple
induction proof that this
algorithm correctly
calculates L,
p, and deltas, which is
all the information we
need to calculate the shortest
path.
I think you guys can do
this during the recitation
if you still need a little
practice with inductive proof
.
And the last thing
we need to check
is the execution time of
this algorithm.
I'm going to squeeze it in there
at the last second here.
So let's take a look.
So, first, I did something
small... oh no, that's okay...
in my algorithm,
actually at step zero,
I had to create an array
whose size is equal to the number of
vertices.
Remember that in 6.006
how long does it
take to allocate memory?
Yes, it takes an amount of
time proportional to
the amount of
memory I allocate.
So... Steph, I see your
hand, but we're short on time.
So we have to get to the end.
We have already spent v time,
since our array of shortest paths
takes up v places.
But in addition to that, we
have this funny FOR loop
where for each node I have to
visit all of its neighbors.
But first, do
I see a double knot here?
No, because I go in
order of distance.
And the second thing I
saw was a node in one
set of levels, it can't be in another.
This is our basic
design.
Well, as
you wish, you have already
proven exactly the
formula we need.
And if I'm lucky,
I won't track it down.
Yes, we are here.
So, if we look here,
this is exactly the scenario
we are in.
Because what have we done?
We iterated over all the
nodes of our graph,
and then over all the
neighbors of those nodes.
And this is the base
computation time
in our algorithm.
Thus, the FOR loop, or
more precisely the WHILE loop, in my code
takes time proportional to the
number of edges.
So, what is the total running time
for a broad search?
Well, we need to
build this array.
So, at step zero
we got v time.
And then we have to repeat
something that
takes up the most edges.
So, overall our algorithm takes
mod v plus mod e time.
Now notice that this...
you may consider this
redundant.
By the way, I have a
little
argument with Jason.
But in this class, we'll call
it a linear time algorithm
because it's linear in the
space you
use to store your graph.   Personally,
I think this is
a bit suspicious
since this scale can
scale quadratically in v,
but I digress.
In any case, why do we
need both of these terms here?
Notice, if I
had no edges in my graph,
this term
would now dominate.
But when I add edges to
my graph, it
can grow to v squared.
So this is in some ways a more
informative expression
than just saying, well, in the
worst case, it's v squared of time.  Does
this make sense?
This is a slightly better
formula.
Okay, with that we just
creaked to the finish line.
We have an algorithm for
calculating the shortest paths.
And I'll see you guys again
on Tuesday.