[SCHEET]
[SHUTTER] [CLICK]
ERIC DEMAINE: Okay, welcome
back to the land of data structures.
Today we continue and conclude
our segment on binary trees.
So, this is the second part.
If you missed part one,
go back and watch part one.
Last time we talked about
binary trees in general.
Each node stored an
element, as well as left
and right pointers
to other nodes,
as well as a parent pointer
to another node.
This was an example of a tree.
B and C are children of A.
A is the parent of B
and C and also the root of the
entire tree.
We have determined the height of the node.
We haven't used it much yet.
But today we will
use it often.
So remember, the height
is drawn in red here.
The height of a node is the length of
the longest descending path,
including edges.
So, B, for example,
has a path length of 2.
So we write here 2.
You can also think
of it as if you just
live in a subtree that is
rooted in a subtree of B, B,
so what is the maximum
depth of these nodes,
if you prefer to
think of it that way.
Anyway, good.
Specifically,
we have selected
h, the height of the
root node, as the height of the
entire tree.
Last time we achieved that basically
all our operations
were performed on the order of h times.
So we had subtree insertion,
subtree deletion, subtree first
and last.
We could compute
the predecessor and successor of a
node, all in about h time.
So while h was
little, we were happy.
And remember what
predecessor and successor mean?
This is about the implicit
order in the tree, which
we call the traversal order,
which is defined recursively
as recursively traversing the left
subtree, then exiting the root,
then recursively traversing the
right subtree.
So in this example, the
traversal order is: F —
if you go all the way to
the left, that was first
in the traversal order.
Then we have... okay, I'll
make some space for myself here.
Then we have D,
then we have B. Then
we make the right
subtree of B, which
is E. Then we have
the root, because we finished the
left subtree of the root.
So this is A. And then we have C.
So there is an implicit linear
order encoded by this tree.
And the whole point of
binary trees
is that we can efficiently
update the tree much faster
than we could explicitly
write down the order in an array
or something like that.
So binary trees allow us to do fast -
now, fast
now not so fast.
Because everything is in order h.
And in the worst
case h is linear.
Because we can have
such a tree.
But today we're
going to do... we're going
to guarantee that h is equal to log n.
So the goal
today is to take
all these operations
that are executed in order h times
and make them run the
order log n times, simply
by modifying the
data structure we've already seen.
So we've done a lot of the
hard work, just a little
more work we need to do
today on what's called
AVL trees or height balance.
But before we get to that, I want to
talk a little bit more--
at the very end of the
last lecture,
we talked about how when you have
these subtree operations--
so that I can insert and
delete in a subtree--
how do I actually use that to
solve the problems that we're
interested in in this class, which is the
sequence data structure and the
set data structure?
So last time we mostly talked about the
structure of the dataset.
So, in general, we're going to
define what traversal order
we support using a binary tree.
And so for a set, because
for a set interface
we are interested in doing
queries like find_next
and find_previous, given
a key, if it is not there,
tell me the previous
or next,
that is what we can
do with binary search.
And so the big, cool thing
that binary trees allow us to do is
if we allow the traversal order to
always be all elements
stored in
ascending key order, then we
actually maintain the
order of the elements
in the sense of traversal order.
Again, we clearly don't
keep them in order.
But here at the top, we
maintain a tree that
represents the elements in key order.
So this allows us to perform a
subtree_find operation,
which can be easily
used to implement find,
find_previous, and so on,
as shown below.
We start from the
root of the tree.
Thus, we can say that
initially the node is equal to the root.
And then we can recursively
search for key k as follows.
We check, okay, if
the element at the root
has a key greater than k--
let me draw a little picture.
So, we're at a kind of a crossroads here.
This is a node.
And it has a left subtree
and a right subtree.
And there is some
object with some kind of key.
So, if the key we're looking for is
smaller than the node element,
that means it's
here, in the left subtree.
And so we recurse to node.left.
If they are equal, it
means that this element
is the one we are looking for.
So we can just return
it or the node,
depending on what
you're looking for.
And if the key here is
bigger than the key
we're looking for, then
we'll turn right.
If you
think about it a bit, this is
exactly binary
search in an array.   Instead,
he just ends up
in a tree.
If you think about an
array like this,
what does binary search do?
First, look at the
key in the middle.
I'm going to draw
this as a root.
And then it recurses
either on the left side,
which I'll draw recursively,
or on the right side.
So if you
have a perfect binary
tree like this, it
simulates exactly
binary search on this array.
But we will be able to
maintain this dynamically -
no longer perfectly, but close.
Whereas we couldn't
keep it in order.
So, it's like a
generalization of binary search
to work with trees
instead of arrays.
And for this reason, tuned binary
trees are called binary
search trees because they are a
version of a binary search tree.
Therefore, there are many
equivalent names.
So, a binary search tree is another
name for a binary tree set.
The key thing that makes
this algorithm work is the
so-called
binary search tree property, which is that
all keys in the
left subtree of a node
are smaller than
the root or that node,
and that key is smaller than all
keys in the right subtree.
And this is true recursively
to the end.
Thus you prove
that this algorithm is
correct by this property.
Why is this true?
Because if we can
maintain the traversal order to be an
increasing
key, then that's
exactly what
traversal order means.
It tells you that all things
in the left subtree
precede the root, which
precedes all things
in the right subtree.
So, this property
implies this.
And how do you keep things
in ascending key order?
It's pretty easy.
If you want to insert an
element, where does it belong?
Well, you do this
search to find where it would
belong if it were there.
If it exists, you can overwrite
the value stored with that key.
If not, this
search
will fall out of the tree at some point, and this is where
you insert a
new node into your tree.
This was described in the recitation,
so I don't want to dwell on it.
What I want to focus on today
is a different program.
How do we... this is for
representing the plural, which is
relatively easy.
The challenge
we have to address,
but we
still need to work on a little more, is
to create binary sequence trees.
Let's say I have a binary
tree, and I would like -
we mentioned at
the end of last time - for the
traversal order of my tree to
be the
order of the sequence, the order that I'm
trying to represent that is
changed by operations
like insert_at.
So I would just like to
do the same.
But now I have to think
about how I do the search,
how I do the insert_at,
etc.
And here is the algorithm for what
I would like to work on.
But it wo
n't quite work yet.
So, suppose I give you a
subtree defined by a node like this.
So, there are all the
descendants of this node.
And I would like to know what the
order of traversal of
this subtree is, which
starts here and ends here,
and the root would be
somewhere in the middle.
Give me the ith node.
So if I ask that i is
0, I want to get
that leftmost child.
If I ask for i to be equal to
the size of the tree minus 1,
I want to get the
rightmost child.
This was the first and
last in the subtree
we were talking about.
But we know how to find the
first and last.
Just go left or go right.
But we don't know how
to find the ith node
because the goal right now is time h
, not log n.
The idea is that
size matters.
[Laughs] Sorry if
you heard otherwise.
So, in particular,
I mentioned size
when I was talking about the
last node in the sequence.
The index of this node is equal to
the size of the subtree minus 1.
So let's define
the size of a node
as the number of
nodes in its subtree--
we called
it a subtree(node)--
including the node itself.
So, if I somehow
knew the size, that
seems important for
understanding indices.
Let's just assume
I knew this magically
in constant time.
So I'm saying that
the size of the left subtree--
so why don't I expand
this diagram a little bit?
So, we have a node, just like before.
But we have a left subtree
and a right subtree.
So this node here is node.left.
This node here is node.right.
They may not exist, but let's
ignore these exceptional cases for now
.
Suppose we knew not
only the size of the node,
but also the
size of node.left,
so that's the size of the
tree on the left.
I'm going to call it nL.
So, let's assume there
are nL nodes here.
I claim that this allows me to perform the
equivalent of binary search.
Because I'm looking for
some index i.
And if i is less than nL, then I
know it has to be down here.
For example, if i
is 0, it
will be in the left subtree
if nL is greater than 0,
right?
So this is the check.
If i is less than nL,
I'm going to recurse
left, call subtree
in node.left, i.
That's what's written here.
If i is equal to nL, if you think
about it for a second-- so nL
is the number of nodes here.
This means that this
node has index nL.
The index of this node is nL.
So if i is-- if
the only index we're looking for
is that, then we
just return that node.
We are finished.
Otherwise, i is
greater than nL.
And this means that
the node we are looking for
is in the correct subtree,
because it is after the root.
Again, here's what it means.
This is what the
order of passage means.
So if we define this
as the order of the sequence,
then we know that all the things
that come after this node, which
is the index nL, must be here.
Now, when we recurse here,
our numbering system changes.
Because for node here is 0.
And then for node.right here.
So we need to do a little bit of
subtraction here,
so when we go
to the right, we
take i minus nL minus 1--
minus nL for these guys,
minus 1 for the root node.
And that will give us the
index that we're looking for
in that subtree.
So, what I'm saying is that this
algorithm is basically the same
as this algorithm.
But keys are used here because
we are dealing with a set,
and in sets we assume that
elements have keys.
Here, objects don't
necessarily have keys.  In
fact, we
don't touch the objects at all.
We're just asking what is the ith
element in my sequence, which is the
same as what is the
ith element in my traversal order,
which is the same as
asking what is the ith
node in the traversal order?
And this algorithm
gives you that
exactly the same
in order of h time.
I'm not going to show
you all the operations now.
But you can use subtree_at
to implement get_at set_at.
You simply find the corresponding
node and return the element
or change the element.
Or you can use it to...
most importantly, you can use
it to do insert_at delete_at.
This is a new thing that we have
never been able to do before.
what do you do
Like here, if I
try to insert an element,
I look for that
element here.
So, for example, if I try to insert
i, I look for i.
And then for insert_at i
you need to add a new element directly
before that.
And conveniently,
we already have...
I didn't mention it, but we
have a subtree insertion.
We had two versions--
before and after.
I think we covered after which
I use the successor
before using the predecessor.
But we can just
call subtree insert
before on that node, and
boom, we'll add a
new element right before it.
And wonderfully, so
magically, somehow, we
inserted it into the
middle of this sequence.
And all indexes are updated
because I don't store
indexes.
Instead, to search for
the element at index i,
I use a search algorithm.
But there is a problem.
What's the problem? It
seems too
good to be true.
I insert into the
middle of this tree,
and then somehow
magically I can search and still
find the ith element, even if
all the indices to the right
of that element are incremented by 1.
That's almost true.
Respond?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ERIC DEMAIN: Because we
need to update the dimensions, right.
I didn't say how do I calculate
the size of the left subtree?
So that's the next topic.
We're almost done.
This will really work.
This is really great.
But for this to work,
we need something
called
subtree expansion,
which I'll talk about in general.
And then we'll
apply it to the size.
So, the idea behind
subtree augmentation
is that each node
in our binary tree
can store a constant
number of additional fields.
why not
And specifically,
if these fields
belong to a certain type,
maybe I'll call them properties.
I will define
a property of a subtree
as something
that can be computed
from the properties of the child
nodes.
So I have to say it's a
knot.
So, the child elements are
node.left and node.right.
You can also access a constant
number of other things,
such as the node itself.
But the essence of the
subtree property
is that it is directed downwards.
If I have a node here
, and I want to
compute some
property on it--
call it, we want to
store P of the node--
and let's say we already
know P here,
the property computed
for the left subtree
or for the left
node, and we already
know the property for the
right node, then I would like that to be
computable in constant time.
So I can calculate the P of this
node given the P of the left node
and the P of the right node.
This is a property of a subtree.
Now, in particular, size
is a property of the substrate.
why
Because I can write
this type of iteration,
node.size is equal to
node.left.size--
that's really boring to write--
plus node.right.size, plus?
1, thank you.
The size of the entire
subtree, called a node here,
is equal to the size of the left subtree
plus the size of the right subtree
plus 1 for the node itself.
So, this is the update rule.
It takes constant time to evaluate.
These are two editions.
Sorry, my T's look
like plus signs.
I'll add
a few more pluses.
So, we're just summarizing
these three things.
Boom, we can get node.size.
So I argue that as long as
my property has this feature,
I can maintain it dynamically
by changing the tree.
Now this is a bit of a
preliminary reference
because we haven't
said exactly how we're
going to change the tree yet.
But the question?
AUDIENCE: If node.size is
recursive,
how does this happen
in constant time?
Won't this
happen [INAUDIBLE]??
ERIC DEMINE: Why is that...
Okay, good question.
So you can think of
it as recursion,
which gives you a
recursive algorithm.
So I wrote, but I didn't
write.
But I could write that
the size of a node is equal to this-- the
size of node.left
plus-- and that would
give you a linear-time algorithm
for calculating the size.
And if you
don't have any information,
you would.
And that would be very painful.
So that would make this
algorithm very slow.
If I call size as a
recursive function, that's bad.
Instead, I
store the dimensions
on each individual node
and pre-calculate that.
Actually, I'll
define the size of the node in...
this is a
mathematical definition.
But the algorithm
for this function
will only
return node.size.
So it's constant time.
So the challenge is that I
have to keep these dimensions up to date
, no matter what
I do with the tree.
And you can
look back at the last lecture
and see, okay, what all the
changes did I make to the tree?
We only made changes
during insertion and deletion.
And I'll just tell you,
when we were inserting and deleting,
what they
ended up doing was
they were adding or removing
a leaf from the tree.
Remember that the leaf was a
node with no children.
So let's just think about it, if
I add a new leaf to the tree--
here's the tree, let's say
I add a leaf here--
what subtrees are going to change?
Well, what subtrees
contain this node?
This is actually a new subtree.
Then it is in its parent subtree, in
its grandparent subtree,
and in the general subtree.
In general, these nodes
are called ancestors of
this node that we added.
And these are the ones
that are being updated.
This subtree has
not changed.
The size has not changed.
And since this is a
property of the subtree,
no property of the subtree will
change here,
since the subtree
was intact.
So when I touch this
guy, I just need to
update the
subtree property here,
update the subtree property here.
How many are there?
Yes?
h-- I will say the order h to be safe.
But I think that's exactly it.
Likewise, when I delete a
leaf, the same thing happens -
if I delete that leaf, the
subtrees
that are changed are
its former ancestors.
Cool, so we're going to
update these ancestors of order h
in order up the tree.
So what do I mean by update?
I mean the application of this rule.   As
for size, this is the rule.
But in general the
subtree property
gives me an update rule
that takes constant time.
And so I'm going to
apply this update rule
to this node, which will fix
all the properties that are
stored there.  There
may be more
than one property.
And then I'll apply
that to this node.
And since this is already
correct by induction,
and it's already correct
because I didn't touch this
subtree-- it hasn't changed--
then I can update
the value at this node-- the
property at this
node in constant time.
Then I will update this one.
And since this
is already correct by induction,
and this is already
correct because this subtree is
immutable, I can
correctly update the property here
in constant time.
So when I
change the order h times,
because I make h calls to
this constant-time algorithm,
I can update a constant
number of subtree properties.
This is very powerful.
Extending the data structure is
extremely useful.
You will use it for
your task set.
We will use it again today.
Let me give you some examples of
subtree properties.
They can be-- common ones are,
for example, the sum, or the product,
or the minimum, or the
maximum, or the sum of squares,
or all sorts of
things, of some characteristics of
each node in the subtree.
In fact, the size of a subtree is an
example of such a thing.
This is the sum of all nodes
in the subtree of value 1.
This is another way
to count the number of nodes.
But can you also
say what is the sum of the
keys in these nodes?
Or can you tell me what the
maximum key is in these nodes?
maximum value is at these nodes?
You can take any property.
It shouldn't be key.
It doesn't have to be
anything specific.
This is very powerful.
You can take all the sums,
products, and maintain them
as long as they
face down,
as long as you
only think about the subtree.
Some examples of things
you can't support are
no node index.
So, if you get too
excited about augmentation,
you might think, oh,
I could do anything.
I needed to support
subtree_at, or
let's say get_at
globally, I wanted
to know what is the ith
node in my tree?
Well, I'll just use a
data structure extension
and store in each node
its index from 0 to n minus 1.
I can't maintain
that efficiently.
Because if I insert
at the beginning of
my traversal order, then
all the indices will change.
So, this is an example of editing.
So if I insert a
new node here,
this guy's index
was 0, now it's 1.
This guy's index
was 1, now it's 2.
It was 2, now
it's 3, and so on.
Each node changes its index.
Index is not
a property of a subtree,
so we cannot support it.
Since it depends on all
the nodes in the tree.
Or it depends on all
the nodes on the left —
all the predecessors.
So, for example,
this guy's index depends
on the number of nodes
here on the left that aren't
in the subtree of this node.
So you
have to be careful here.
Do not use global
tree properties.
You can only use
subtree properties.
Another example is depth.
Depth is annoying to maintain,
but it's not yet clear why.
We'll see that in a moment.
The rest of today is dedicated to
the transition from order h to the order
n log, which
this slide shows us.
So, for now, you have to
believe that we can perform all operations on the
sequence data structure
in order h,
except for construction and iteration,
which take linear time,
and that we can perform all
operations in order h.   time,
excluding assembly and
iteration, which take
n log n and n respectively.
And our goal
now is to relate h to log n.
We know that this is possible
at some level
because there are trees with
logarithmic height.
This is the
perfect tree.
But we also know that we
have to be careful
because there are bad
trees, like this chain.
So, if h is equal to log n, we call
it a balanced binary tree.
There are many
balanced binary trees in the world
, maybe
a dozen or two -
many different
data structures.
Question?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
You said not to
think about things
on a global level,
so we'll think about
them [INAUDIBLE].
Can you explain what
that means a little more?
ERIC DEMAIN: Okay,
what does it mean for a
property to be local
to a subtree, rather than global?
The best answer is
this definition.
But this may not be the
most intuitive definition.
That's what I mean.
Something that can be calculated
simply by knowing information
about your left
and right children,
here is the value of
such a property.
And that's the only thing
you're allowed to support.
Because it's the
only thing
that's easy to update by
going this route.
And the contrast is that a
global property, like an index,
is global,
specifically because I
can make one change, add one
node, and all
the properties of the node will change.
So this is an extreme
example of global.
We want to have this very
specific notion of local
because it is something we can
afford to enumerate.
I hope this clarifies things.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Doesn't size
work with this [INAUDIBLE]??
ERIC DEMINE: You're
right, if we add...
oh, no.
Okay, let's think about it.
If we were to add a new
parent to the tree,
we would never have done it.
But even if we did,
which subtrees would change?
Only this one.
This node, this is a
completely new subtree.
But the subtree of this node is
completely unchanged.
Since subtrees
always look down,
if I added a new root, I
didn't change any subtree
except one.
So, size is a property of a subtree.
Now there's...
I mean, I could completely
redraw the tree.
And this is an operation
that requires
listing everything.
So there are limits to what
I am allowed to do in the tree.
But I argue that whatever
we do, the last class
and today, we can afford
this increase.
So, this is a property not
necessarily of all binary trees,
but of the ones
we would cover.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: What is a mine?
ERIC DEMAIN: What is a minute?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]
ERIC DEMAIN: Binary tree, yes.
Okay, it will make a little
more sense
when I tell you what we are actually
going to do with the trees.
We need a new tool for
manipulating wood.
What we've done so far is we've
done some item swapping.
And we added
and removed a leaf.
This is not enough.
We'll need
something else to
guarantee logarithmic height.
And this is something else
called rotation.
What
else is needed for this?
It is simply a tool to
restore the balance of the tree.
Thus, this should not change the data
represented by the tree.
What data
does the tree represent?
The order of passage.
The order of circumambulation is sacred.
We are not allowed to touch it.
This is already defined in
two different ways,
depending on whether
you are using a set or a sequence.
So, we want to modify
the tree in a way that doesn't
change the traversal order.
That's why we use reservations.
If you wrote down the
traversal order in an array,
there will be exactly
one representation of
that order.
But there are many representations in the tree
.
It can be a long line.
It might be a balance thing.
They can represent
exactly the same order at the nodes
if they are labeled correctly.
In fact, there are exponentially
many different representations of the
same thing.
And we're going to use this, the
same order, and define...
it's just something
you need to know.
Let me label A, X, B,
Y, C. You can tell I've
drawn this diagram
many, many times.
This is a very powerful tool
in all tree data structures,
which are most
data structures.
And they are called right rotation
y and left rotation x.
So if I have this tree,
I just
put some of the subtrees
into little triangles.
If I have a node, and
it has a left child,
then I'm allowed to rotate
that edge to the right, which means take
that edge and move it like this--
90 degrees, like.
Or you can just think of
it as rewriting in this way.
Now you can also have
parent pointer tracking.  The
parent pointer is moving.
It used to be
y's father.
Now this is the father of x.
So, x and y are swapped.
But we couldn't just
swap these elements
because that
would change the traversal order.
In this figure,
x comes before y
because x is in the left
subtree of y in the traversal order.
And now y is
in the right subtree of x.
So it comes after x.
So in both cases
x comes before y.
And indeed, in all of these
figures, the traversal order -
I mean, not only for x and
y, but also for A, B, and C, the
traversal order
is sequential.
It's A, X, B, y, C, where
when I write triangle,
I mean the recursive
order of traversing all the
things in the triangle.
So if you just apply the
traversal order algorithm here
and here, you
will get the same output,
which means that these operations
preserve traversal order.
Great, this is something
we
can do in a tree that won't
affect what
we've done so far.
This is a tool we
can use to restore balance.
Notice how deep things are
in the change tree.
Our problem with
this linear tree
is that there are some
nodes of linear depth.
We want to get rid of them.
as?
Well, we can take these edges
and start rotating them upwards.
If you look at the depths,
in this image,
A and B are deeper than
C. And in this image,
B and C are deeper than
A. So it's a trade-off.
This one rose.
This one went down.
This one remained
at the same depth.
So hopefully if A is too
deep and C is too shallow,
they can trade that way.
This may sound complicated,
but there is actually a
fairly simple method
called AVL trees that
maintains balance in a
way called height balance.
This is if we take
the height of node.left--
actually, I would prefer--
node.right, minus
the height of node.left,
so this is called
node skew.
I want it to always be
minus 1, 0, or plus 1.
So that means
if I have any node,
and I look at its left
subtree and its right subtree,
I measure their
height-- remember, this is the
distance down, the
maximum distance to the leaf--
I measure the height of
this tree-- the
maximum height-- and I
measure the maximum height of
this subtree, I want them to
be within 1 of each other.
Ideally, they are equal.
This would be an ideal case.
But let's say they differ by 1.
So maybe this is k,
and this is k plus 1.
Or maybe this is k,
and this is k minus 1.
In this picture, what is
the height of this node?
This is good practice.
k plus 2, okay.
What is the longest path
from this node to the leaf?
Well, it can go
through this subtree.
And this is going to be length k
plus 1, because it's k
plus 1 for this edge.
Or it could go over here,
and it's k plus 1 plus 1.
So the biggest thing is to
go to the right.
So the height... if I tell you
the height of these subtrees,
we can get
the height of this node.
We're going to use
this a lot in a moment.
So the first statement
is that if I can
maintain
height balance, then I
guarantee that h is equal to log n.  In
other words,
height balance implies balance.
So, let's
quickly prove this.
And then, the interesting part
is how do we actually prove...
or how do we actually
maintain the balance property?
We will do
this using rotations.
But how is the big question.
So why does
height balance imply balance?
This suggests
that all trees with balanced height
have logarithmic height.
So, I would like to
think of
the least balanced
tree with a balanced height.
The least balanced
node will have an inconsistency.
Let's say the left
subtree is smaller
than the right subtree by 1, and
recursively to the end.
So at each node there is a
gap,
as we call it--
skew 1, which
I'm going to write--
I'm going to introduce
some notation.
I will write a distinct
right arrow if this arrow is
above the left subtree.
So the easiest way
to think about it is this is
our worst case scenario.
This will be the least number of
nodes for maximum depth.
Let's just count how many
nodes are in this tree.
I'm going to write this
as a recurrence, which
is the number of nodes
in a tree of height h.
So if this whole tree has height
h, as we said in this picture,
if I just subtract 2
from all of these numbers,
then this tree has
height h minus 2,
and this tree has
height h minus 1.
So how many nodes are in here?
Well, this is the recap
I'm going to write.
So this is going to be N sub h minus 2.
This is going to be N sub h minus 1.
And then I just count how many
nodes there are in this picture.
This is Nh minus 1 plus Nh
minus 2 plus 1, or this node.
Now you may ask,
why Nh relapse?
But this is the number of nodes
in such a worst case
if the
total height of the worst case is h.
So you can also
think of it as what is the
minimum number of
nodes I can
have in an AVL tree, which is a
height-balanced tree, which
has height h in a
height-balanced tree?
Okay, now I just need to
solve this repetition.  Does
this repetition
look familiar?
It's like Fibonacci numbers.
If I take away the plus
1, it will be Fibonacci.
And if you happen to know that the
Fibonacci numbers grow
as the golden
ratio to n,
then we know
that it's exponential, which is what
we want.
Because if Nh is
exponential in h,
that means h is
logarithmic in N,
because log is the inverse
of exponential.
But maybe you don't know
about Fibonacci numbers.
And so we can easily
show that it is exponential,
as shown below.
I want to prove that this is
at least an exponent,
because that gives me that
h is at most logarithmic.
Therefore, we need a lower bound.
So we have these two terms
that are hard to compare:
Nh minus 1 and Nh minus 2.
It's kind of ugly.
But if we're allowed
to be sloppy--
and we'll see if
we're too sloppy--
and still get an
exponential answer,
let's just make
them equal like this.
So this is a true statement,
in fact, strictly more than.
why
Because I removed the plus 1.
It should only make
something smaller.
And I replaced Nh minus
1 with Nh minus 2.
Here I'm implicitly
using the fact,
obvious by induction,
that this tree is height--
if I take this tree
against this tree,
it has more
nodes than this one.
If I am taller,
this design
will build a larger
tree, at least as big.
It doesn't even have to
be strictly bigger.
So of course, Nh minus 1 is
greater than or equal to
Nh minus 2.
Now this is 2 times Nh minus 2.
And this is easy to repeat.
It's just powers of 2.
I keep multiplying by 2
and subtracting 2 from h.
So this solves
2 to h over 2,
maybe with a floor or something like that.
But I'm using the base case here,
which is N sub 0 is equal to 1.
Maybe then it's a ceiling.
But the thing is, it's
exponential.
So this means that the height is
always at most 2 times
log n.
This 2 corresponds to this 2.
If you just reverse
this formula, this
number of nodes
is at least 2
to h times 2.
So h is at most 2 log n.
So it's not log n.
That would be ideal.
But this is within
a factor of 2 of log n.
Thus, AVL trees are
always fairly balanced.
The number of levels is
at most twice
the number needed to store n nodes.
Great.
We're left with the main magic--
not the domain magic.
This is different.
And let's see, we're going to
use subtree addition.
Hold this.  The
big remaining problem
is how do we
maintain this high balance property
with rotations?   We
have all the ingredients
.
We have a subtree expansion.
What does this allow me to do?
This applies to AVL trees.
Well, it allows me to maintain altitude.
I need to be able to calculate
the height of a node.
This, in general,
takes linear time
because I have to go through
all the descending paths--
all the leaves
in this subtree.
But height is
a property of a subtree,
so yes, height.
why
Because-- let me
just write it here--
node.height is 1 plus the
max of node.left.height
and node.right.height
and the max.
Let me put this in a box.
This equation, or I guess
this is an assignment operation--
this is 1-- this is something
we
do over and over again.
When I said what
the height of this node was,
you just
figured it out, right?
You took the height of the
left subtree added
to the height of the
right subtree
and added 1 to account for
those edges.
So, this is a
general rule of thumb for updating.
It matches this
subtree property pattern.
If I have a
left and right property,
I can calculate that for a node.
And this requires
constant time.
And so this is a property of a subtree.
And this way I can maintain the height of each node through
all the actions I take
.
By the way, every time
I do a rotation,
I will also have to
update the subtree properties.
When I rotate this edge, A
doesn't change, B doesn't change,
C doesn't change.
So that's good.
But the subtree x changes.
Now he has y.
This didn't happen before.
So we'll also have to
update the extension here
in y.
And we'll have to
update the increment in x.
And eventually we will
have to update
the extensions of all
ancestors of x.
So, rotation
locally changes a
constant number of pointers.
So I usually think of rotation
as a time constant.
But ultimately we'll
have to do...
it's a constant local time.
But we'll need to update the
ancestors to
keep all... keep all
our additions up to date.
We'll take care of that later.
Okay, great.
Now we have the height of
all the nodes.
We can calculate the skew of
all nodes, cool.
We have this rotation operation.
And we want to preserve this
property of height balance.
The height of the left node-- to the left
and right of each node--
is plus or minus 1, or 0.
Cool, so I said here
somewhere when we--
so the only things
that change the tree
are when we insert
or remove a new node.
And the way we've
implemented this so far is to
add or remove a leaf.
So we still have to think
about adding or removing a
leaf.
The problem is that when
I add a new leaf,
now that tree is perhaps
taller than it was before.
Therefore, some nodes here may
be unbalanced in height.
But since height is
a property of a subtree,
the only nodes we
need to check are
those at the top of that ancestor path.
And they are only log n,
because now the height is log n.
This is what we just proved,
as long as we have this property.
Right now we don't
have that for
maybe these few nodes.
But that was long before that.
This is at most log n--
2 log n plus 1 right now,
because we just added a node.
So what I want to do is
check all these
ancestor nodes sequentially from bottom to top
and find
the one that is unbalanced.
So, let's take the lowest
non-equilibrium node.
I'll call it x.
Now, since we just inserted
or deleted one leaf,
it's only out of balance
by 1 because we just
changed the height -
one height increased by 1 and
one height decreased by 1.
And before, all our skews
were plus or minus 1 or 0.
So now... the bad case is that it's
plus or minus 2.
If it happens to still be in
that range for all nodes,
we're happy.
But if it's outside that range,
it's only going to be by 1.
So that means the skew
is n plus 2 or minus 2.
And let's say
it's 2 by symmetry.
So my image is...
I'm going to draw a
double arrow to the right
to say that this subtree is
2 higher than this subtree.
Okay, that's bad, and
we want to fix it.
The obvious thing to do
is to bring this edge back.
Because that will make it...
that's too high
and that's too low.
So if we rotate, this
should decrease by 1,
and this should increase by 1.
And that works most of the time.
Thus, the first case is a y-skewed condition.
What is y?
I want y to be a
correct descendant of x.
Since we have a positive skew,
we know there is a correct child.
Now, since this was the
lowest bad node,
we know that y is actually good.
It's either right-heavy--
or even two subtrees
have the same height--
or left-heavy.
Simple cases
where the y-skew
is 1 or 0,
which I'll draw.
So, double arrow to the right,
let's say single arrow to the right--
so I'll just
add some labels here
to make this
picture consistent--
k plus 1, k plus 2.
I'm going to the top.
So this is an example
where C is taller
than B. A and B are the
same height.
And then if you calculate
the height here,
it really does
have the right slope.
This is a double
right slope.
Because this one
has a height of k plus 1.
This one has a height of k minus 1.
That's bad.
But if we do this
proper rotation on x,
we get exactly what we want.
So I'll just copy
the labels to A, B, C--
we have k minus 1,
k minus 1, and k--
and then I'll recalculate.  So that
means this
guy has height k,
this guy has height k plus 1.
And now all the nodes in this
picture that I selected--
A, B, and C-- haven't changed.   Previously,
they were
balanced in height.
They are still there.
But now x and y...
x wasn't
balanced in height before, but y was.
Now both x and y
are balanced in height.
This is the first case.
In the second case, the
y skew is flat,
which means that
this is k, and this is k,
and this is k plus 1,
and this is k plus 2.
But still, all the
nodes are balanced –
balanced in height.
They are still plus or minus 1.
So these are simple cases.
Unfortunately,
there is a difficult case -
case three.
But there is only one, and
it is not much more complicated.
So when the skewness of
y is negative 1.
In this case, we need
to look at the left child of y.
And to be alphabetical, I'll
rename this to z.
So, this is a
double arrow to the right again.
This is now a left arrow.
And this is the letter y.
And so we have potential subtrees A, B, C, and D
hanging off
of them.
And I'm going to mark
the height of these things.
This is k
minus 1 or k minus 2.
This is k minus 1.
Now calculate the intrinsic value.
So this would be the height k so that
it would be tilted to the left.
So this is k plus 1,
and this is k plus 2.
But the problem is, this is
2 more than this.
The height z is 2 higher
than the height A. In
this case, if I
do this rotation, it
actually makes things worse.
I'll just tell you
what the right thing to do
is what
you need to remember.
And let me draw the results.
You can also think of it
as redrawing the tree in this way.
But from an
analysis perspective, it's easier
to think of it
as two rotations.
Then we can just reduce.
As long as we know
how rotation works,
we know that
this thing works--
"works," meaning it
preserves the traversal order,
and we can support
all the additions.
So if I copy these
labels-- the height labels--
I have k minus 1.
I have, for these two guys,
k minus 1 or k minus 2.
The largest of them is k minus 1.
This is k minus 1.
So this is going to be k.
This will be k.
This is going to be k plus 1.
And so, we have a
nice, height-balanced tree
in all three cases
for this one node.
Now it was the lowest knot.
Once we update
this one,
we may have changed the
root height.
It used to be k plus
2, now it's k plus 1.
Or sometimes we leave it the
same, like in this case.
And so now we have to
check the parents.
Maybe the father
was out of balance.
And we just keep
moving along the node
and also supporting all the
additions along the way.
We will then keep track of
the height and size of the subtree
if we desire them, or any
other extensions.
And after operations of order h,
we will
have the
height-balanced property restored, which
means that all the way through
h is of order log n.
And so all our operations are
now magically ordered in the log n.