[SQUEAKS]
[SCRATCHES] [CLICKS]
ERIC DEMAIN: Okay, welcome
back to 006 Data Structures.
Today we will
look at another type of
tree-like data structure
called a heap - a binary heap.
This will allow us to solve the
sorting problem in a new way.
Let me first remind
you of one part:
the problem we're
going to solve today
is called priority queuing.
This is the interface.
We will see several
data structures,
but one basic
data structure for today.
And this is a subset of the
installed interface.
And subsets are interesting
because we
can potentially solve them better,
faster, easier.
So you recognize...
you should recognize
all of these operations,
except that we don't usually
highlight the maximum operation.
So, we are interested
in storing a bunch of items.
They have keys that we
consider to be priorities.
And we want to be able to
identify the element with the highest priority
in our set and remove it.
And there
are many motivations for this.
Maybe you have a router,
packets are coming into the router.
They have different
priorities.
You want
to address the highest priority first.
Or you
have processes on your computer that are trying
to run
single-threaded — single-core,
and you need to choose
which one to run next.  Typically,
processes with higher priority are launched first.
Or you are trying to model a
system where events occur
at different times
and you want to process the
next event, ordered by time.  These are all
examples of a
priority queue interface.
We'll even see applications
in this class
when we get to graph algorithms.
But the two main things we
want to support
are inserting the element
that contains the key
and keeping the maximum
element and returning it
at the same time.
We will also talk about
the possibility of building a structure
faster than just inserting it.
But of course, we
could implement
assembly by starting from empty
and inserting repeatedly.
And also the difficulty of
simply finding the maximum
without removing it, you
can simulate this with these two
operations, removing
the maximum and then inserting it back in,
which works.
But often we can do it faster.
But the two key basic operations
are insertion and deletion max.
And we'll see a few
data structures for this.
Any suggestions for the
data structures
we saw in this class?
What should we use to address the
priority queue interface?
Many possible answers.
AUDIENCE: AVL sequence?
ERIC DEMAIN: AVL sequence?
Oh, that's interesting!  The
AVL sequence is a good answer,
but perhaps a more fashionable version.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Install AVL?
ERIC DEMAIN: Installing
AVL sounds good.  The
AVL set supports these
and many other operations.
Everything in log n time, except for
the collection, which takes n log n time
because it has to be sorted first.
So install AVL as a good
way to do it.
We'll come back to your
idea of ​​an AVL sequence later.
This gets the log n for the operation.
great
I mean, this... the
AVL set is our
most powerful data structure.
It performs all the operations we
need on the dial side.
And the AVL sequence
performs all operations
on the sequence side.
But note that this is a
set, not a sequence.
We take care of the keys.
There are ways around
this using sequential AVLs,
but let's do that later.
So great if we
want to, for example,
speed up find_max in a set AVL.
We could add magnification.
Could we... mention
expanding subtree properties?
We can use this to get
constant time find_max
by storing in each node
the maximum key element
in the subtree.
And this is a property of a subtree.
We
mentioned him in the last class.
So we could even improve
this to reduce the time.
Great.
So, we're done.
End of the lecture.
[CHUCKLES] In a
way, that's true.
But what we're
going to look at today is
another data structure
called a binary heap,
which is in a way a
simplification of the AVL set.
It achieves basically the same
time limits.
The build will be faster
by a log factor.
But that's not the main
reason we care about them.  The
main advantage is that
they are simpler
and give us an in-
place sorting algorithm.
So, I have the
three operations
I was talking about:
build, insert, and delete_max.
So, we set up AVL trees there--
n log n build, log n insert,
log n delete.
So on the way to our heap, I
want to mention two more
data structures.
One is a dynamic
but unsorted array.
And the other is a
dynamic sorted array.
These are simpler
data structures that
we have
already talked about many times.
And they are a useful
motivation to
start with, because the heap
will be built on top of arrays
instead of...
well, it's kind of a fusion
between arrays and trees.
So, if I have an unsorted
array, it's very easy
to insert, right?
I'm just adding it at the end.
This is what we
called insert last.
Thus, the insert is fast,
constant depreciation.
We may have to
resize the array,
but that's
amortized part.
But remove the maximum slowly.
In an unsorted array, I don't
know where the maximum is.
So I have to scan the
entire array.
So I look through
the array, I find
that the maximum is somewhere
in the middle, and then
if I want to remove it--
I want to remove this
maximum element, well,
in a dynamic array,
all I can really
do is remove the last
element effectively.
So I could, for example, swap
it with the last element.
So I take this element
and put it here, and then I
delete the last element in this
array, which is pop in Python
or delete_last in our world.
So overall it's
linear time, which is bad.
But I wanted to emphasize exactly
how this is
done, for a reason we'll
talk about in a moment.  A
sorted array is
the opposite.  It is
very easy to find the max.
Where is it?
At the end.
delete_max, the maximum element
is always the last element
in an ascending sorted array.
I guess it's constantly
depreciating because then I'll have to
delete it, which
could result in a resizing.
However, the insertion
will be linear
because I might be able to use
binary search to find the
location of the inserted element.
Let's say I just
added this element here.
I could
find a binary search,
but then I would have to
make some serious changes.
So I could
just swap places a few times
until I find the position
where the added element x belongs.
And now I have restored the
sorted order.
This takes linear
time, which is bad.
And we want the
best of both worlds.
Insertion is fast for an array.
Deletion is fast for a
sorted array.
We can't get consistent
time for both.
But we can get log
n time for both.
We already know how to do it
with a set of AVL trees.
But today we will see
another way to do it.
And the main motivation for
another way to do this
is sorting.
Therefore, I want to define
the sorting of the queue by priority.
So, given any data structure
that implements the priority queue interface
, including
insert and delete_max,
I can create a sorting algorithm.
What should I do?
Insert all elements,
delete all elements.
But since when I remove them,
they come out largest first,
I get them in
reverse order.
Then I could turn back linear
time and I would sort my items.
So, we can insert (x) instead of
x in A or (build(A))
and then delete_max several times.
How long
does this algorithm take?
I'm going to introduce
some notation here.   Creating n elements
takes whatever amount of time
,
call it T sub build (n) plus--
sorry-- plus n times
the time to execute delete_max.
Or we can write
it as n times the
insert execution time, plus the
delete_max execution time.
So I use these T-functions
to simply abstract the
runtime provided by
my data structure that
implements this interface.
The interface says it's
correct,
and these T-functions give
me performance limits.
So, if I connect each of
these data structures,
I get a sorting algorithm.
I get AVL sort,
I get array sort,
I get array sort.
What do they look like?
It turns out that many of
them are familiar.
So, the AVL set takes
log n per operation.
So, we get from them an n log n sorting algorithm
that
inserts all
elements into the AVL tree.
I don't want to use AVL assembly
because it uses sorting and
sorting is forbidden
for implementing sorting.
But we saw how to
insert into an AVL tree
and maintain balance.
Thus, log n is required for each.
And then we can find
the maximum, remove it, restore balance,
and so on.
The total time will be n log n.
This is an algorithm
we call AVL sort.
This is a little more complicated because
AVL trees are complex.
But this gives us the optimal
comparison limit and log n.
What about sorting an array?
So, let's say I'm using an
unsorted array.
I insert the object.
So, if I'm inserting items,
I do all the insertions
here before the deletions.
So what happens is
I'm just going to insert the elements
in the original order of the array.  In
other words, I'm
just taking an array.
And then I do it several times by
extracting the maximum element,
searching for it,
moving it to the end of the array,
and then repeating this process.
Sound familiar?
This is an excerpt
from the third lecture.
So this is... arrays give
us selection sorting.
It's a new way of
thinking about what
we were doing back then.
What do we do with a sorted array?
We insert all the elements.  That's where
all the work actually happens, because we
maintain a sorted array.
So, we start with an empty array.
This is sorted.
Add an object.
Okay, everything is still in order.
We add a second
element and swap places
if necessary to sort.
In general, when we add an
element, we shift it to the left
until it is sorted again.
This is a type of insertion.  It's
kind of cool, it's a unifying
framework for the three
sorting algorithms we saw earlier.
We didn't actually talk
about AVL sorting last time,
but it was in the notes.
So, this is the right
side of the table.
So of course these array data structures are
inefficient.
They take linear time for
some operations.
Therefore, sorting algorithms are
inefficient.
But these are ones
we've seen before,
so it's good to see
how they fit in here.
They had...
selection sort and
insertion sort had the advantage of being
in place.
You just need a constant
number of pointers or indices
outside of the array itself.
Thus, they are very effective.
So that was a plus for them.
But they take n squared of
time, so you should never
use them except for n
at most 100 or something.
AVL tree sort is great, and then
it gets n log n time, probably
harder than
merge sort, and you
can stick with merge sort.
But neither merge sort nor
AVL tree sort works.
And so the goal
today is to get
the best of all these
worlds in sorting,
to get n log n
comparisons, which
is optimal in the
comparison model,
but to have it in place.
And that's what we're going to
get with binary heaps.
We're going to design a
data structure that
builds
a little faster-- as I mentioned,
linear time shaping.
So, it does not represent
sorted order in the way that
AVL trees do.
But it will be like a
tree.
It will also be based on an array.
We are going to get the logarithmic
time for insert and delete_max.
It happens that it is amortized
because we use arrays.
But the key is that it's a
data structure in place.
It consists only of an
array of elements.
And so when we plug it
into our sorting algorithm—
priority queue sort or
general sorting algorithm—
we not only get
n log n performance,
but we also get an in-
place sorting algorithm.
This will be our first
and only-- for this class--
n log n
in-place sorting algorithm.
cool
This is the goal.
Let's do this.
So what we're going to do,
since we're in place, is
essentially we need to have an
array that stores our final elements.
This is a kind of
in-place definition,
simply using n memory slots
whose size exactly matches the number of
elements in our structure.
But we obviously won't be
using a regular unsorted array
or a regular sorted array.
We will
only use the array as
the technology underlying
how things are stored.
But we would really like
logarithmic performance, which
should make you think of a tree.
The only way to get the log is a
binary tree, more or less.
So, we want to
insert the tree into an array.
Let me give you an example.
Let me draw a tree.
If I had to choose
any old tree,
I would choose one that is
basically perfectly balanced.
The ideal balance would be
where--
what ownership?
I have all
these levels -
all these depths
completely filled with nodes.
This is depth 0.
Remember, this is depth 1, this is
depth 2, this is depth 3.
So what I would really like to
have is 2 to i
nodes at depth i.
This would be a
perfect binary tree.
But this only works when n is 1
less than a power of 2, right?
I can't always achieve
this for any n.
So the next best
I can hope for
is 2 to i in
nodes at depth i
to the last
i-- the greatest depth.
And at this level, I'm still
going to limit things.
I'm going to force
all nodes
to be as far left as possible.
So what I'm saying is that except for the
maximum depth where the nodes are,
I'm going to call them left-aligned.
These two
properties together
are what I call a
complete binary tree.
Why is this interesting?
Because I claim that I can represent
such a tree as an array.
I've narrowed things down enough
that I can draw an
array here.
And what I'm going to
do is write these nodes
in depth-first order.
So I write A first
because that's step 0.
Then B, C, that's step 1.
Then, okay, they're
in alphabetical order.
I did it this way.
D, E, F, G is depth 2.
And then H, I, J is step 3.
This is very different from
the order of traversing the tree.
The order of the walk would be
H, D, I, B, J, E, A, F, C,
G, okay?
But this is what we
might call depth-first,
execute the lowest
depth nodes first – a
completely different way of laying things out
or linearizing our data.
And this is what the
pile will look like.
So, the most interesting thing is that
there is a bijection between complete binary trees and arrays.
For each array, there is a
unique complete binary tree.
And for every complete binary
tree, there is a unique array.
why
Because total
restriction forces
everything-- forces my hand.
There's only... if I
give you a number n,
there's one
tree shape of size n, right?
You simply fill in
the nodes from top to bottom until you
reach the last level.
Then you must fill
them in from left to right.
This is what can be called the
read-write order of nodes.
And the array tells
you which keys go where.
This is the first node you
write in the root,
this is the next
node you write
in the left child of
the root, and so on.
So here we have a binary
tree represented as an array,
or an array representing a
binary tree.  A
very specific
binary tree, it
has an obvious advantage,
namely guaranteed balance.
There is no need for rotation in heaps,
as full binary trees are
always balanced.
In fact, they have the best
height they could get,
which is a ceiling of n logs.
Balanced, remember, it just
meant you were big O of log n.
This is 1 times log n.
So this is the best level of
balance you can hope for.
So somehow, I argue, we can
maintain a complete binary tree
for priority queue resolution.
This would be
impossible if you were
trying to solve the
entire dialer interface.
And that's kind of the
cool thing about heaps is
that by just focusing on a
subset of the interface set,
we can do more.
We can preserve this
very strong property.
And because we have this
very strong property,
we don't even need to
store this tree.
We won't store the left
and right pointers and parent
pointers, we'll just
store the array.
This is what we call an
implicit data structure, which
basically means no pointers,
just an array of n elements.
How do we do
without storing pointers?
I would still like to
treat it like a tree.
I would still like to know that
the left child of B is D
and the right child of B is E.
We'll see why in a moment.
Well, we can do this
using index arithmetic.
So maybe I should add a few
tags before I get there.
So, this array
naturally has indexes.
This is index 0.
This is index 1, index 2, index
3, index 4, index 5, index 6,
7, 8, 9, because there
are 10 elements, from 0 to 9.
And I can apply those
labels here, too.
These are the same
nodes, so 0, 1, 2.
It's just an order of depth.
But once I get
this labeling, it
will be much easier for me to
understand.
So if I wanted to know that the
left child of B is D,
somehow, given the number 1, I
want to calculate the number 3.
Add 2, there are all
sorts of-- multiply by 3,
there are all
sorts of operations
that take 1 and turn it into 3.
But there's only one that
will work in all cases.
And the intuition here is that
I have 2
nodes i at level i.
If I want to go down to the
child level, there
are nodes 2 to i plus 1 down there--
exactly twice as many.
So, this is the last one,
but it doesn't matter.
If there is a left child element,
it will behave the same way.
So, intuitively, I have
this space of size 2 to i.
I need to expand it to a space of
size 2 to i plus 1,
so I have to multiply by 2.
And that's almost correct, but
there are some constants.
So I would like to say 2 times I.
But if we look at the
examples here, 1 times 2
is 2, which is 1 less than 3.
2 times 2 is 4, which is
1 less than 5.
Hey, we almost got it right.
It's only by 1.
Deviations by 1 -
index errors are the most common
things in computer science.
What about the right child?
If the left child is 2i plus
1, where is the right child?
I hear a lot of mumbling.
2i plus 2-- one more.
Since we write things
from left to right in depth order, the
right child is the right
sibling of the left child.
So, it's just one bigger one, okay?
Given these rules, we
can also calculate the parent element.
This is the
inverse
of both of these
functions, which I want to
divide by 2 at some point.
I want to get back to i, given
2i plus 1 or 2i plus 2.
So if I subtract 1
from i, I'm
either going to get 2i or 2i plus 1.
And then if I divide the integer
by 2, I get i-- the
original i.
Sorry, maybe I'll call
it j to make it clearer.
So, j is a left or right child.
Then I can reconstruct
i, which was the parent.
So, these are
arithmetic operations with a constant number.
So I don't need to store
pointers to the left and right.
I can just calculate them
when I need them.
Whenever I'm at
some node, say E,
and I want to know
what its left child is --
sorry, given the
node index 4, which
contains the
element E, and I
want to know what its left child is
, I just multiply by 2
and add 1.
I get 9.
And then I can do an index in
this array at position 9.
Because I don't... it's
just in my head, remember.
We just think there
's a tree here.
But in reality,
there is only an array on the computer.
So if we want to go from E
to J, we can go from 4 to 9.
If we try to go to the
right child, we multiply by 2.
8 add 2-- 10.
And we see, oh, 10 is
beyond the end of the array.
But our array preserves its
size, so we understand that E
does not have a correct child element.
This is something you can
only do in a complete binary tree.
In a general binary
tree, you don't
have these nice properties.
Cool, so that's
basically a bunch.
I just need to add
one more property, which is
naturally called the
heap property.
So, there are several
types of heaps.
This type of heap
is called a binary heap.
We will talk about the others
in the next lectures.
I'll call it
Q. Obviously,
this is an array representing a
complete binary tree, which is
called the array Q. And we
want each node to satisfy
what's called the maximum heap property,
which says Q[i] is greater than
or equal to Q[j] for both
the children to the left of i and the children to the right
of i.
So, we have node i.
And it has two children--
2i plus 1 and 2i plus 2.
These are two values ​​of j.
We want a ratio
greater than or equal to
here and here.
So this node must be
bigger than both this one
and this one.
Which one is bigger?
We don't know, and
we don't care - this is
very different from
binary search trees
or sets of binary trees, where we
said these guys are less than
or equal to this,
this one was less than
or equal to all the nodes
in the subtree here.
We're just
saying locally that this node is
greater than or equal to
this node and this node.
So, the largest is at the top.
So one good lemma about
these piles is this is strange.
Let me give you some more
intuition.
If you're a binary heap, if you
satisfy this maximal heap property everywhere
, then
you actually learn
that every node i is
greater than or equal to all the nodes
in its subtree.
These are what we call
descendants in subtree i.
Let me look at this example.
That's why I didn't write
any numbers here.
You can imagine.
So here A is greater than
or equal to both B and C,
and B is greater than
or equal to D and E,
and C is greater than
or equal to F and G,
D is greater than or
equal to H and I,
and E is
greater than or equal to J.
This would make this
structure a heap,
not just a complete binary tree.
So, what does this mean?
This means that A
must be maximal.
So you look at any
node here, for example J, A is
greater than or equal to B is
greater than or equal to E is
greater than or equal to
J. And in general we
say that A is
greater than or equal to all nodes in
the tree.
B is greater than or equal to
all nodes in its subtree
here.
C is greater than or equal to
all nodes in its subtree.
This is what
this lemma says.
This lemma can be proved
by induction.
But it's actually simple.
If you have two nodes, i
and j, and j is somewhere
in the subtree,
that means there is
some descending path from i to j.
And you know that
for every edge
we pass on the
way down, our key does
n't go down strictly.
So, each child is less than
or equal to its parent.
i is greater than
or equal to this,
greater than
or equal to j, okay?
So, because of the transitivity of
less than or equal to,
you know that i is actually
greater than or equal to j.
Or, sorry, the key
in i is greater than
or equal to the key in j.
This is what we
call i, the index.
would call the Q of i.
This is the index j Q of j.  A
completely different way of
organizing keys in a tree,
but as you can
imagine, it would be
good for priority queues.
Because priority
queues simply have to
find the maximum number of elements.
Then they need to be removed.
This will be harder
because the leading root node
, like -- it's the hardest
node to intuitively remove.
I would really prefer to
remove the leaves.
But keeping leaves and
maintaining a complete binary tree is
actually quite difficult.
If I want to remove
H, it won't
look like a binary
tree, or it won't
look like a complete
binary tree anymore.
This is not justified.
Likewise, if I want to
remove F, that's bad.
Because right now I
don't have four nodes here.
The only node that is easy
to remove is J, right?
If I remove this node, I'm
left with a complete tree.  The
last sheet, the last
position in my array, is
easy to delete.
This is good because arrays
handle the last element well.
But what I've set up here is that it's
easy to find the max.
It will be
here, at the root.
The deletion is annoying.
I would like to somehow take this
key and put it in a position--
in the last position
on the last sheet,
because that's the one
that's easy to remove.
And that's really what
we're going to
do in the deletion algorithm.
Let me insert first.
I think it's a little
simpler, sort of symmetrical
to what we just said.
So if I want to insert a key or an
element x that has a certain key,
again, the only thing I
can really do in an array is
if I want to add a new element,
it has to be at the end.  The
only thing we
know is to
insert it at the end of the array.
This is what we
called insert_last.
it?
Corresponds to adding a
node containing x--
element x-- to the last
level of a complete binary
tree.
It either goes to the right
of all existing nodes
or starts a new level.
But this
will always be the last leaf.
After we execute
the insert, the
position size will be Q minus 1. However,
this is probably
not enough.
We simply inserted an
arbitrary element into the sheet.
And now it may no longer satisfy the
max-heap property.
So let's just check if it is,
and if not, fix it.
This is what we can do.
But this time
we won't even
need rotations, and
that's cool.
So I'll define an
operation called
max_heapify_up.
This will make things look
more like a max pile.
We will start with the size of
Q minus 1 for our value of i.
But this is going to be recursive,
so we're going to
look at node i,
specifically the one that was
just inserted.
And where
could that have broken things?
Well, with his parent's, because
we don't know what key
we just placed here.
Maybe it's less than our father.
Then we are happy.
But if it's bigger than
our father's, we have a problem
and we need to fix it.
So if the element in the parent
key is less than the key i--
ah, I see I forgot to write the
key and all these blobs.
This must be a dot key
and a dot key,
since Q[i] is the
element that gets its key.
So, this is a bad case.
This is if the father is
smaller than the child.
We wanted parents to
always be
greater than or equal to their children.
So,
what could we do in such a case?
Swap them.
Let's change the Q of the parent element i--
great, more
chalk-- to Q[i].
Now they are in the correct order.
Now we need to think about
another child of
this node?
What about his father?
So I have some numbers.
Let's say it was
5 and it was 10.
What do I know about
this picture before?
Well, I know that 10 is the
element that was just inserted.
This is the only one that
could have caused a violation
when I first inserted it.
So I know that before this...
before I moved 10,
I knew that all the things
in this left subtree were
less than or equal to
5, and everything up here
was created equal to 5.
I also know that the nodes
here were actually less than
or equal to 5.
Except for this node 10
that we just inserted,
it was the right heap.
So, 5 was the separator between
what was above it in the
ancestor chain being
greater than or equal to
5, and objects in the subtree being
less than or equal to it.
So after I make this substitution,
which I'm just going to do--
after I swap the elements 5 and
10, 10 is here, and 5 is here.
And now I understand,
okay, great, this edge is
happy because now 10 is
greater than or equal to 5.
But also this edge is happy
because before it was happy,
and we just
increased its parent element.
Now this edge is perhaps bad.
So we need to do a recursion--
recursion to the parent element.
But that's all.
So we fixed this edge.
First, this happens
at the bottom of the sheet.
But generally
we take our element
that we inserted, which is x,
and it starts at the last sheet,
and it can bubble
for a while.
And maybe it will reach the entire
root
if we insert a
new maximum element.
But on each step,
he climbs one step.
So the
running time of all this
is the height of
the tree, which is log n.
And since there is only
one element that could potentially
be wrong if it
ever stops moving,
we just checked to see if
it satisfies the
max-heap property.
If it hits
the root, you can also
check if it satisfies the
max-heap property.
So there's a base case that
I didn't write here,
which is if i is 0, we're
at the root, we're done.
And then you can prove that it's
correct by induction.
There is only one item that is
not in the right place at first.
And we put it in the right place.
There are many places it could
go, but we'll move it to,
I think, the unique
ancestor position that is correct,
that satisfies the
maximum heap property, okay?
So, this is an insert.
Delete will be almost the
same, delete_min, that is...
sorry, delete_max, thank you.
You can of course define
all these things
for min instead of max.
Everything works the same.
I'm just having a
hard time remembering
which one we're doing.
Just don't switch, you can't use the
max heap to perform delete_min.
You cannot use min-heap
for delete_max,
but you can use
min-heap for delete_min.
that's ok
So, as I said, the only node
we really know how to delete
is the last leaf
at the last level,
which is the end of the array.
Because that's what arrays
can effectively remove.
And what we need to
remove is the root element,
because it is always the
maximum element, which
is in the first
position in the array.
So what should we do?
Swap them, our usual method.
I think the most
interesting thing about heaps
is that we never need to
do any rotations.
We'll just do
swaps, which
we also had to do with trees -
binary trees.
Q[0] with Q the last element--
great, done.
Now we have the last element
we want to remove.
So we do delete_last or enter
Python, and bam, we have...
now we've deleted the
maximum element.
Of course, we could also
mess up the max-heap property
just like we did with the insert.
So with the insert, we
added the last sheet.
Now we
change the last sheet
with...
I point to the
wrong picture.
Let me go back to this tree.
What we did was change point J
to A.  So the problem is that
we deleted this node.
Now the problem is
that this root node
has a possibly very small key.
Because the key that is
here now is what was down here,
very low on the tree.
So it's intuitive
that this is a small value.
This should
be the maximum value,
and we just put a small
value in the root.
So what should we do?
Pour down.
We will take this
element and somehow push it up the
tree
until the
max-heap property is met.
So, this
will be max_heapify_down.
And we'll start at position
0, which is the root.
And max_heapify_down
will be a recursive algorithm.
So, we will start from
some position i.
And first it is the root.
And what we're going to do is
look at position i and its two
children.
Let's say we enter a
very small value here, like 0.
And let's say we have
children, 5 and 10.
We don't know, maybe
I'll change their order
to be more general, because
this looks like a not-quite-
binary
search tree, but we don't
know their relative order.
But one of them is
greater than or equal to the other
in a certain order.
And what would I like to
do to fix this local picture?
Yes, I want to exchange.
And I could swap the places--
0 is clearly in the wrong place.
It should go
lower on the tree.
I can change 0 to
5 or 0 to 10.
Which one?
10.
I could draw a picture of
5, but it wouldn't be happy.
Why 10?
We want to do it
with more,
because then this
land will be happy,
and this land
will be happy too.
If I substituted 5 there, the
5/10 advantage would be miserable.
This will not satisfy the
max-heap property.
So I can make one replacement and
fix the max-heap property.
Also, again, 0 may be
unhappy with his children.
0 is one item that
was in the wrong place.
And so we had to
go further down.
But 5 will be...
5 didn't even move.
So that's happy.
Everything is fine in this subtree.
What about the parents?
Well, if you think about
it, because everything
was the right heap
before we added 0
or before we set 0 too
high, all of these nodes
will be greater than or equal to
10 on the ancestor path.
And all of these nodes were
less than or equal to 10
before, unless
you're equal to 5.
So that's still true.
But you see, this tree is happy.
This tree may still be unhappy.
0 may still need to
press further.
This
will be recursion.
So we check here.
There is a base case, i.e.
if i is a leaf, we are done.
Because there is
nothing under them.
So, we satisfy the
maximum heap property in i
because there are no children.
Otherwise, let's look at
the leaf among the left--
sorry, left, not leaf--
among the two children
to the left and right of i.
That's right, if I don't exist.
Then ignore it.
But among the two
existing child elements,
find the one that has the
maximum key value, Q[j].key.
In our example, it was 10.
And then if those
points are out of order,
if we don't satisfy--
so more than would be
satisfied.
Less than Q[j] will be
the opposite of the maximum heap property
.
If the max-heap property
is violated,
we fix it by
replacing Q[i] with Q[j],
and then recursively execute j--
calling max_heapify_down on j.  That's
all.  So it's
quite symmetrical.  It
was a little easier to insert
because we only have
one parent.
Delete_min, because
we are pressing down, we have
two children.
We have to choose one.
But there is a clear
choice -- a bigger one.
And again, this algorithm--
this whole thing--
is going to take order h of time,
the height of the tree,
which is log n, because our
node just disappears.
At some point it stops.
When it stops, we know that the
max-heap property has been met
.
And if you check by induction along the way
,
all the other
properties of the maximal heap
will be satisfied
because they were there before.
So it's almost forced what
we could do here.  The
amazing thing is
that you can actually
maintain a complete
binary tree that satisfies the
max-heap property.
But as soon as you are told this, the
algorithm kind of falls out.
Because we have an array.
The only thing we can
do is insert and remove the
last element.
And so we have to swap
things back and forth in order--
or from there to make
it work.
And the rest is
just a local check to see
if you can fix the property.
cool That's
almost everything, not
quite what we wanted.
So now our heap has log n amortize
insert and delete_max
.
We haven't
considered linear construction yet.
Now it's n log n
if you insert n times.
And we haven't yet told you how to
do this with an in-place sorting algorithm
.
So let me draw each of them.
I think the first one is in place.
So how do you make this
algorithm work in place?
I guess I want it,
but I don't need it.
So, we want to stick to
priority sorting of the queue.
Maybe I want that.
But I don't want to
expand and contract my array.
I would like to start
with the array itself.
So it's spot on.
So what we're going to
do is say, okay, here's
my array that I want to sort.
This is given to me.
This is the input for
priority sorting of the queue.
And what I would like is to build a
priority queue out of it.
At first it is empty.
And then I want to insert the
elements one by one, let's say.
So in general
I'm going to
argue that Q
is some prefix of A.
That would be
my priority queue.
It will live in this
subarray-- this prefix.
So, how do I insert a new element?
Well, I'm just zooming in.
So to do an insert, the first
step is to increase the size of Q.
Then I'll take the
next element from A
and insert it into this Q.
And conveniently, if we look at
our insert code, which is here,
the first thing we wanted to do was
add an element
to the end of the array.
So we just did it without
any actual work, just
conceptual work.
We just said, oh,
our Q is one bigger.
Boom!
Now it's at
the end of the array.
No more depreciation,
actually, because we never
change the size of our array,
we just say, oh,
now Q is a little bit
bigger than the prefix.
It simply absorbs the
next element of A.
Similarly, delete_max
is going to,
in the end, reduce
the size of Q. Why is this normal?
Because at the end of our
delete_max operation —
not quite at the end,
but almost at the end —
we deleted the last
element from our array.
So we just replaced
the removal of the last with a decrement,
and that
will decrease Q by 1.
This has exactly the same effect
as preempting the last element.
But now it's constant time, at
worst it's not amortized.
And as a result, we never
create a dynamic array.
We just use
part A for this.
So what
happens is we
absorb all the elements
into the priority queue
and then we start throwing them out.
When we kick them out, we
throw out the largest key element first
and put it here, then the
next largest, then the
next largest, and so on.
The minimum element
will be here.
And, boom, everything is sorted.
That's why I created
max-heaps instead of min-heaps,
in that it will ultimately
be an array sorted upwards,
with max at the end.
Because we always
throw away items at the end.
First we remove the max.
So this is what is
commonly called heapsort.
You can apply this same trick
to insertion sort and
selection sort, and you'll actually get the
insertion sort and
selection sort algorithms
we've seen working
on array prefixes.
Great, now we have...
we've reached
y,
which is the n log n
sorting algorithm that's in place.
So, that was our main goal -
heapsort.
Let me briefly mention that you
can create a heap in linear time
using a clever trick.
So, if you insert
elements one at a time,
this would be equivalent to
inserting down the array.
And every time I insert an object,
I have to climb a tree.
So, this will be the sum of
the depth of each node.
If you do that, you get n log n.
This is the sum over i log i.
This turns out to be n log n.
This is the logarithm of the factorial n.  A
cool trick is to
instead imagine that you're
adding all the elements
at once and
not piling anything up, and
then piling up-- sorry,
piling down from the bottom up.
So, we're gathering.
Now we're going to
pile on.
And, oddly enough, it's better that way.
Because it is the sum of the
node heights.
And it turns out to be linear.
This is not obvious.
But intuitively for depth
it's 0, it's log n,
and we have a
whole ton of leaves.
You see that right at the sheet level
we pay n log n,
right?
Because there are n of them,
and each one costs log n.
Here, at the
sheet level, we pay constantly.
Since the height of
the leaves is 1.
Here the height of
the root is log n.
And that's better.
Now we pay a small
amount for things
that are plentiful.
This is not exactly a
geometric series,
but it turns out to be linear.
So, here's how you can
create a linear building pile.
Going back to your question
about AVL sequence trees,
it turns out that you can get
all the same bounds
as heaps, except for the in-
place part,
by taking an
AVL sequence tree, storing the
elements in random
order, and adding
at max, a crazy idea.
But it also gives you
linear creation time.
And yes, there
are other interesting things in your notes.
But I'll stop there.